FOREWORD

Whichever way one looks at ‘Ajeeb Goa’s Gajab Politics’ one comes to the conclusion that it is an interesting and delightful book. If you read it as a person curious about Goa you will enjoy the accounts of transition from colonial rule to the later continuous assimilation into the Indian Union. If you approach it as a student of mythology then the arc of Parashuram’s arrow will engage you with its origin myth and with how contemporary politics wants to make mythology a hard historical fact. If you are a scholar of electoral studies the results of Goa elections, right from the first election in 1963 till the most recent in 2017, will continue to puzzle you with their unconventional outcomes. If, instead, as a demographer you want to examine the consequences of Goa’s in and out migration, for society and politics, the book offers many insights. ‘Ajeeb Goa’s Gajab Politics’ is a treasure house of interesting questions about democracy, demography, and I daresay even of demonology.

What I found fascinating is the little observations that the author makes and that are so inviting for students of social science. Let me just mention three. In the essay on the Opinion Poll he mentions that the teachers imported from Maharashtra, to fill the vacancies in the hugely expanded number of Marathi schools that had come up after liberation, had secretly campaigned against the proposed merger with Maharashtra, i.e., against the state from which they had come, and whose culture they carried, because the merger would go against their personal interests measured in terms of salary, promotion, and transfer. This is an interesting thesis on how and why self-interest takes precedence over cultural identity. How would such a dynamic have played out in today’s heightened politics of cultural nationalism? When does a background culture heightened by political mobilization cause people to act against their self-interest when they are required to make choices in the public domain? Think of demonetization and all that followed.

Another intriguing issue is the discussion in the chapter on Land. The author discusses the phenomenon of ‘negative declarations’ where a tenant swears before the Mamlatdar that his or her name had been wrongly entered in the I & XIV land records. So instead of claiming land rights, given by a philosophy of land to the tiller which one thought was going to be a boon to the marginal tiller, we find the tenant renouncing their rights for some other gain, one that needs detailed elaboration. What is it that outweighs land rights given by the tenancy laws? The interesting issue to investigate is the set of factors that cause this renunciation of rights. What does it tell us about the emerging political economy of Goa? I see this small insight on the renunciation of land rights, the negative declaration, as a master key to understanding the drivers of change in contemporary Goa. Land is the single most important factor that defines contemporary Goa. We know this. But it still needs much more study. The chapter by Sandesh Prabhudesai, on land, has many suggestions. I see it as a good place to begin one’s investigation on the political economy of Land in Goa.

The third observation that I wish to note relates to the relationship between the Communidade, as an institution, and the Gaunkari system. He describes how the former undermines the latter and shows how this happens through the laws introduced by the Portuguese authorities. Not only did it change the structure of the village but it reassigned rights disenfranchising the subaltern groups within the village. This is a huge area of research, not just in terms of the respective qualities of the two institutions but also in terms of how a colonial mindset and policy regime imposed itself on an ancient society. Goa is a prime example of such an imposition which has had many negative effects that we still quarrel over. It has also had some positive effects but we hesitate to name them. There is, in fact, significant interdisciplinary research waiting to be carried on the historical encounter of India with Europe. If we look at contemporary Goa through the lens of tourism studies, then the encounter produced what some have described as colonial chic. Goa, as a cultural and social space, sells well. It is chic. See the data on the number of tourist arrivals both domestic and foreign to confirm this point. Goa, being different from Sindhudurg or Gokarn which are also beautiful coastal areas, is an attractive holiday and leisure destination because of this Portuguese interlude. If, in contrast, we look at Goa through the lens of colonial studies, then it is an interesting case of cultural hybridity, different from the French colonies of Algeria and Morocco, but sharing with them the receipt of a common colonial policy of cultural assimilation. This delightful book on ‘Ajeeb Goa’s Gajab Politics’ provokes such questions.

There are many many such aspects that can be teased out of the study. I do not want to suggest here that it is a well-researched academic study, conforming to all the protocols of social science research. It is not. There are too many long quotations, too many tables of data, selective references to scholars, and a wide sweep of history, folklore, politics, demography, and sociology. Social scientists would be hesitant to make such excursions. But Sandesh Prabhudesai must not be asked to conform to the rules of social science research. They belong to a different profession from that to which he belongs. He is a journalist. He is a gentleman scholar. He has been a student leader of yesteryears. He is an activist involved in campaigns that have extended from fighting discrimination in a crematorium in Verla-Canca to joining the movement to make Konkani the state language. These are many personas. They give him an advantageous location from which to view Goa and to comment on its multiple transformations. These comments are insightful. They are valid. That is what makes the volume so valuable. I see him as a chronicler, and the book as a chronicle. He offers us, through the book, some valuable propositions. Many audiences can gain from it. I have not overlooked the wide generalisations he has made but have chosen instead to argue with them, question their data sources, challenge their formulations, explore their connections with larger debates outside Goa. His book connects with these large debates. I find the discussion on democratic politics, for example, very provoking.

Prabhudesai has titled his book ‘Ajeeb Goa’s Gajab Politics’ . He repeats the phrase often in other chapters as if the narrative he has developed in each chapter confirms, once again, the validity of the title. Perhaps it does. Perhaps it does not. Yeh Goa ke Log indeed Ajeeb hai. QED Sandesh Prabhudesai. But so is the book. A society remains alive because while many remain silent on the distortions in society, and the causes that produce these social pathologies, there are some like Sandesh, who name the culprits, call out the politicians, expose the lies, denounce the liars. This book is the beginning of another interesting conversation on Goa. He deserves a complementary proposition. I offer him one: ‘The geography of Goa undermines its history’. Saudade.

Peter Ronald deSouza
D D Kosambi Visiting Professor, Goa University
Former Director, Indian Institute of Advanced Study, Shimla.

Dona Paula 20 December 2021

WITH A PERSPECTIVE…

“Election is a dirty game.”

This is a common attitude all of us carry. What does it signify? A blame game? Or a shirking from responsibility? This book tries to explore the whole political game of Goa so that all of us can play it wisely and also win it.

This is not a post-retirement exercise of mine to gather all my experiences in the journalistic profession and dump it on the readers. I consciously decided to retire from day-to-day journalism, so that I could do ‘journalism’ rather than spending most of the time on mere reporting. With this book, I am entering a new phase in my profession: Book Journalism! A research-based analytical exercise, with no strings attached. Neither politician centric nor politics-centric but an effort with a sincere people centric approach.

There are only two books available on Elections in Goa, both in Marathi, by the veteran journalist Waman Radhakrishna and my research-minded journalist colleague Suhas Belekar. But that’s not the reason I am providing this book now in English to reach a wider readership. I think I have a responsibility to clear the various kinds of misconceptions about Goa’s politics. These myths prevail within Goan society and even all over India. Goa’s politics is directly connected to Goa’s economy, history, and even its geography. Not just because Goa was ruled by the Portuguese, unlike the rest of British-ruled India. You cannot simply apply pan-Indian political strategies and tactics to play the election game in our tiny state. “Goa is a mere 10-lakh-voter state, smaller than one of our Lok Sabha constituencies” is the attitude I find among most Indian politicians and political analysts. Then they bite the dust and we laugh at them. Both attitudes are not right, I thought and sat down to write this book as my social responsibility.

Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru was not wrong when he said Goans are Ajeeb (strange). More than Goans, Goa’s politics appears stranger. But actually, it is not. We perceive it as Gajab (astounding) because the perspective is missing. This book does not provide just a commentary on elections in Goa from 1963 to 2017. It provides a definite perspective, based on the rationally analysed history, geography, economy, social, and even cultural structure of Goa. Through this emerges the psyche of a voter. The book tries to define this psyche, which is neither Ajeeb nor Gajab.

I have tried to do this based on the little knowledge I have acquired in 33 years spent in journalism, around 10 years spent in student, youth, and street theatre movements, and also my childhood spent in the village of Loliem in Canacona. This southernmost village on the Goa-Karnataka border may be backward economically but has always been a progressive village in terms of knowledge-based education. I have been fortunate to be mentored by freedom fighters, dedicated teachers, social thinkers, writers, artists, and hard-working people. I have to admit that I was first influenced by my freedom fighter parents. My theatre-loving parents were Brahmins by birth and Bhatkars (landlords) by occupation but have brought us up working in the fields and kullagars. They were passionate followers of Gandhi’s and Lohia’s reformist thoughts. They were staunch Marathiwadis and Mergerists against whom I always argued in support of our Konkani movement and our unique identity. The Marxist movement provided me with a scientific outlook at a young age. It also gave me the courage to quit it and embrace a non-affiliated journalistic profession. The dialectical approach made me realise that politicians, per se, are not bad human beings. They are the products of a greedy and selfish culture that an opportunistic society has established in Goa in recent years. They are part of the system as much as we are. They create uncontrolled mindless havoc when civil society fails to provide a well-defined socio economic cultural vision for a prosperous society. A game of social responsibility, not a blame game, is the only solution to this problem.

This book with such a perspective is just the first volume, an introduction to a series of books I plan to write on Goan polity. This book has been made possible by the astute researchers to whose work I have referred to extensively. The priceless conversations I had with many personalities working selflessly at the ground level in different fields have helped me discover many harsh and hidden realities. Nonetheless, the visionary perceptions for Goa provided by people-centric leaders like Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru, Bhausaheb Bandodkar, Dr Jack de Sequeira, Adv Amrut Kansar, Dr Kashinath Jalmi, and Matanhy Saldanha simply cannot be disputed. Their premature exits from life’s arenas have been a great loss for Goa.

My apologies if I have not been able to do justice to their dreams through this book. My apologies if I have not interpreted the scholarly works of these researchers properly. My apologies if I have failed to grasp the socio-economic changes Goa has gone through with the right perspective. My apologies if I have committed mistakes while compiling the databases to reach my conclusions. My apologies if I have hurt anyone at a personal level while tackling the sensitive issue of Politics of Business and Business of Politics. Of course, I cannot help it if I have hurt them ‘politically’, as that could be an unavoidable consequence of this risky exercise. My apologies and my gratitude to my own loving family members, to whom I could not give enough time, even after retiring from 24x7 journalism. Last, but not the least, my sincere apologies if I have failed to convince my readers in putting forward a proper perspective of Goa’s politics!

My sincere thanks to Dr Peter Ronald deSouza, an authority on the politics of Goa as well as of India, for writing a thought provoking foreword. If it were not for my writer friend José Lourenço who edited this book tirelessly, this would have been a Konklish book which you would have struggled with. My sincere gratitude to all my friends, personal and professional, who have worked hard to make this book a reality. This is a debt I cannot repay, and one I will cherish all my life.

Sandesh Prabhudesai

Chapter 2

NATIONAL ‘MINES’ & REGIONAL ‘REJECTS’

Before getting into the history of Goan polity, let us learn a bit more about the presence of national and regional parties in Goa. In the earlier chapter, we have seen how the Congress party established itself in Goa after getting completely routed in the first three elections. The merger of the UGP’s Babu-Willy faction and the so-called Marathiwadis like Pratapsingh Rane, Dilkhush Desai, Dayanand Narvekar, and Vasu Paik Gaonkar, led to the Congress emerging as a strong political force in Goa. For all practical purposes, it was the union of the MGP and the UGP as well as the Hindus and the Christians. With Goa attaining statehood and the strength of the Assembly rising to 40 after the 1989 election, this national party became the unified front of the regional sentiments of Goa. The MGP became a namesake regional party with its leaders waiting for the ‘royal opportunity’ to become ‘loyal soldiers of the Congress’.

The ‘UT Mentality’ (of excessive dependence of a union territory on the Central Government) has been deeply rooted in Goan politics right from the day the MGP formed its first government in Goa in 1963. Even after wiping out the Congress in the first election, the first public rally of the MGP held in Margao congratulated the Congress government at the Centre for their victory, claiming that the MGP victory had strengthened the hands of Prime Minister Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru.^1 Even before he was sworn in as Goa’s first chief minister, Dayanand Bandodkar was all praise for Nehru while refuting the Prime Minister’s allegation that the election had been fought on religious lines.^2 He blamed the local leadership of the Congress for their debacle.

While contesting the second Assembly election soon after the Opinion Poll, Bhau refused to continue the MGP’s alliance with the PSP. “The PSP got elected in Goa with our support and their MP Peter Alvares criticised the Congress government at the centre in the Lok Sabha. Being a Union Territory (UT), Goa cannot afford to oppose the central government at the Centre,” said Bandodkar.^3 The PSP lost all the eight seats it contested independently in 1967. The Socialists polled hardly five per cent votes, 3033 to be precise. Seven of them lost their deposits. Even the sitting MLAs like Jaisingrao Rane (6%) and Gajanan Raikar (2%) could not make any impact.^4

The Gold Mine of Congress

It was not Shashikala Kakodkar who made the first move to merge the MGP into the Congress. It was Dayanand Bandodkar. A little before his sudden demise in 1973, Bhau had almost finalised the plan to merge his party into the Congress. Uma Shankar Dixit, the influential union minister in the Indira government, had succeeded in mediating the merger. He had agreed to all the three major conditions laid down by Bandodkar: 1) Elections of the Congress party should be held as per the advice of Bandodkar; 2) Maximum candidates of the Congress should come from the Bahujan Samaj; and 3) Christians should have representation in the cabinet.

However, 12 August 1973 turned out to be a calamitous day for Goa, due to Bhau’s sudden demise. Goa has never witnessed till date such a funeral. The queue of mourners on the day of the funeral extended from his Altinho bungalow near the Circuit House right up to the Panjim Church Square.^5 More than half of Goa, especially in the villages, did not cook their meals as usual that day. We, at school, had a holiday, not joyous but full of tears. The whole state was mourning. The Congress missed gaining a visionary leader and a statesman!

There was a valid reason why Bandodkar had laid down those three conditions. It was because the Purushottam Kakodkar-led Congress was following the unfair policy of favouring landlords over the Bahujan Samaj. Equally flawed was the policy of fielding freedom fighters who had no roots among the masses of those respective constituencies.

In 1967, at the Assembly poll held within a month of the Opinion Poll, Congress did not contest. The national party tried to strike a pact with the regional UGP, as a unification of antimergerist forces. However, the talks failed since Dr Jack de Sequeira remained adamant on not sparing UGP’s strongholds. Congress was also hesitant to give a firm assurance that Dr Sequeira would be made the chief minister. The national party then decided that some of the freedom fighter party men would try their luck as independents. But this experiment flopped even more miserably than the previous one. Madhav Bir in Tivim (polled 869 votes), Pandurang Mulgaonkar in Panaji (1051), Jaikrishna Shirodkar in Shiroda (857) and Ligorio Cota Carvalho in Cortalim (1667) fared quite poorly. Former MGP leader and ex-Speaker P P Shirodkar, who was tipped to be the CM, also lost badly in Siolim (354) as an independent candidate.

But the Congress was still bent upon its 1963 policy when it contested the 1972 election, once again to lose all the seats, except Daman. The freedom fighters who lost were Gopal Apa Kamat in Sattari (1170), Vishwanath Lawande in St Andre (1205), Prafull Priolkar in St Estevam (934), Telo Mascarenhas in Cortalim (1018), and Anthony D’Souza in Mormugao (2816).^6

And once again, a prominent landlord and another mighty mine owner were given Congress tickets. This time from Pernem, Raghuraje Deshprabhu was fielded, but could not poll more than one third of the votes. MGP candidate Jaisingrao Abasaheb Rane, not from Pernem, defeated him by polling 62 per cent votes. Mine owner Modu Timblo in Margao fared even worse. He lost his deposit by polling hardly 17 per cent of the votes, finishing in third position. Anant alias Babu Naik made his debut in the Assembly on the UGP ticket by polling more than half the votes, 54 per cent.^7

But this policy changed with the UGP and the MGP leaders taking over the Congress during Indira Gandhi’s regime. The UT mentality obviously helped the Congress to get firmly rooted in Goa as the national party ruled India for 52 long years, from Nehru in 1947 to Manmohan Singh in the first decade of the 21st century, till the Narendra Modi-led BJP took over in 2014. The major break in between was the BJP rule for six years under Atal Bihari Vajpayee from 1998 to 2004, when BJP’s Manohar Parrikar formed two consecutive governments in Goa. Otherwise, India had witnessed minor stints like the post-Emergency Janata rule in 1977, with V P Singh and Chandrashekhar in the ‘90s, and Atal Bihari Vajpayee (BJP) for six days, as well as H D Deve Gouda and I K Gujral in the late ‘90s. These phases did not have any impact on Goan politics.

The national scenario certainly had an impact on Goa politics in terms of the Congress being the most powerful party in the country, with its blessings and financial support as the central government. Despite facing a series of rebellions as well as defections and changes in their governments, the Congress continued to wield significant power. Even after Goa attained Statehood in 1987, it remained dependent on the Centre till the 10th Finance Commission of 1992, when the Centre cut down financial assistance drastically, in accordance with the Gadgil- Mukherjee formula. In fact, the BJP Chief Minister Manohar Parrikar was the first politician of Goa to prove with his expertise in financial management that Goa could be economically self-sufficient. The Congress till then had not come out of the ‘UT Mentality’, Even today, Goan politicians are demanding a Special Status for Goa on the lines of the North-Eastern states for financial privileges.

The Era of Defections

Defections in Goa did not begin in 1990, when Pratapsingh Rane’s Congress government was toppled within 77 days. The first defection was engineered by Bhausaheb Bandodkar in July 1970 when his government was pushed into a minority due to a revolt by seven MGP men including two ministers and the deputy speaker. He sailed through the vote of confidence by splitting five UGP men from their party and getting them on his side. None of the rebels and defectors from the two parties won in the next election held in 1972.

The second revolt was faced by Shashikala Kakodkar in 1979, following the violent students’ agitation for 50 per cent bus concession. Two young MGP legislators, Dayanand Narvekar and Dilkhush Desai, moved out first, reducing the MGP strength to 13. The Congress had 10 MLAs, but Shripad Kunkolienkar had no voting right as his election petition was pending before the Supreme Court. The Janata Party had three legislators. An independent candidate from Daman was supporting the MGP and another independent Narayan Fugro from Diu was the Speaker. Fugro saved Shashikala-tai by casting his veto in support of the government when there was a tie during the voting on the budget. But then the Law Minister Shankar Laad also joined the rebels and pushed the Tai government into a clear minority. Then Tai managed to convince Prime Minister Morarji Desai, and got President’s rule imposed on 27 April 1979. She did not allow the rebels to form an alternate government. But the next election of 1980 ended the MGP rule. The rebels joined the Congress and that party came to power.

The Congress then ruled Goa for the entire decade uninterrupted. The party did face a major revolt led by Dr Wilfred de Souza in September 1983. He split the party with eight MLAs in protest, as his demand for change in the leadership of CM Pratapsingh Rane was not heeded. Dr Willy, who was then the PWD minister in the Rane government, went ahead and formed the Goa Congress party. This was in the background of the threeday retreat in Goa of the CHOGM (Commonwealth Heads of Governments’ Meet) hosted by India from 23 to 29 November 1983. To facilitate the hosting of the retreat of 39 heads of governments from all over the world, the Central Government gifted Goa a bouquet of infrastructural projects worth Rs 430 million, including the Zuari bridge as well as the CHOGM road from Porvorim to Sinquerim via Saligao and Calangute, and other facilities.^8

Despite Dr Willy’s clout with a powerful contractors’ lobby, the Goa Congress lost the 1984 Assembly election, except for Luizinho Faleiro, who made his debut in the Goa Assembly from Navelim. Though Dr Willy also lost the election, he along with the support of the MGP and frustrated Madgavkars succeeded in defeating his arch rival in the Congress, Babu Naik. Adv Uday Bhembre, standing as an independent, defeated him in one of the most exciting elections Goa has ever witnessed till date. The Congress was also weakened with Shashikala Kakodkar quitting the Congress and staging a homecoming to the MGP on 20 October and later also quitting the MGP to form her own party, the Bhausaheb Bandodkar Gomantak Party (BBGP). Her fate too was no different from the Goa Congress.^9

The Congress once again swept the 1984 election by winning 18 out of 30 seats and gaining 1.60 lakh votes out of 1.71 lakhs polled by five national parties including the BJP (contesting 16 seats), CPI (5 seats), CPM (4 seats) and Janata Party (3 seats), which they all lost). MGP established itself as the opposition, winning eight seats, besides four independents. The Assembly election was held alongside the national Lok Sabha poll, which was held in the background of the assassination of Prime Minister Indira Gandhi. Riding on a nationwide sympathy wave, the Congress won 404 seats in the 514-seat Lok Sabha. In Goa too the party won both the seats (North: Shantaram Naik, South: Eduardo Faleiro).^10

However, anti-Rane sentiment began brewing within the Congress even as the mighty Pratapsingh faced a violent agitation for the official language in 1986. This eventually resulted in Dr Willy coming back to his party, and Goa attaining statehood, with 40 Assembly seats. Meanwhile, the Parliament passed the Anti-Defection Act, making it mandatory for a defecting group to be at least one-third of the parent party’s strength in the legislature to split from the party. This development came a little before the 1989 election. There was yet again a state-wide month-long protest in 1988 against the alleged molestation of a teenage employee by the then Speaker Dayanand Narvekar. This agitation brought all the opposition parties together as a front to fight the 1989 election.

What was its outcome? The Congress reached the edge of a majority by winning 20 seats, while the MGP rose to 18. Rane was in the saddle once again, but only for 77 days. The toppling of Rane by a group of seven MLAs began Goa’s most shameful defection era. The most embarrassing part of this ‘legal defection’ was that the Tenth Schedule of the Constitution (Anti- Defection Act) had authorised the Speaker of the Assembly to sit in a neutral position and judge the legality of defections. But here, the Speaker Dr Luis Proto Barbosa himself led the first legal defection to seize the CM’s chair. The Goa Assembly had to appoint another ‘member of the House’ to decide about the Speaker’s defection. Dr Kashinath Jalmi, who judged this shameful act, ruled that the Speaker could not defect. His judgement was also upheld by the Supreme Court.

However, this new legal weapon of ‘one-third’ provoked a series of shameless toppling games and rampant defections during the entire term, primarily sponsored by various groups of builders and real estate agents. Goa witnessed seven chief ministers in those five years. Despite this, in the next Assembly election of 1994, the Congress still managed to emerge as the single largest party by winning 18 seats in a hung Assembly. Rane became the CM once again. But after ruling for three years and seven months, he was felled again. This time the Congress rebels were also supported by a four-member BJP group from outside.

In order to control these defections, the Anti-Defection Act was amended further in 2003, raising the limit of strength from one-third to two-thirds, or to resign and face a by-election. The professional defectors, mainly from the Congress, as well as from other parties, even faced the electorate after seizing the ministerial seat. The helpless voter finally gave up, but rose once again determinedly in 2012 to send the corrupt, opportunist, selfish, and ‘poor’ Congress of ‘rich’ leaders home. The national party, for the first time since 1980, dipped down to a single digit of nine MLAs. The only viable alternative then was Manohar Parrikar, whose BJP finally reached the magic figure of 21 and ruled Goa for five years.

By 2017, the Narendra-Modi led BJP had established an unbeatable majority in the Parliament in the Lok Sabha poll of 2014, Parrikar had become the defence minister of India, the BJP had showered social schemes with freebies on all sections of the Goan society and had built a well-knit infrastructure of roads, bridges etc.

Still, in the surprise poll of 2017, Congress once again rose from nine to 17 seats, pushing the BJP from 21 down to a mere 13, in a hung Assembly including three each of the MGP, Goa Forward Party, and independents. Churchill Alemao was the sole NCP man elected. Parrikar was surely stunned by this Ajeeb behaviour of the Goan voter.

Sitting in a dejected mood with his journalist friend, Parrikar said: “There is no other option other than sitting in the opposition now.” Suddenly his mobile rang, he looked at it, requested his friend to excuse him and went inside his room. Emerging after ten minutes in an upbeat mood, he told the journalist: “We are forming the government.” Now it was the turn of his friend to be stunned. The impossible had turned possible. Amit Shah moved into action, Nitin Gadkari flew down, a couple of helicopters landed in Goa, and Manohar Parrikar became the Chief Minister once again.

The national leaders had managed to persuade Vijai Sardesai of the GFP as well as Sudin Dhavalikar of the MGP, and the independents, to support the Hindutva party, which they had earlier sworn not to support. Both, Sudin and Vijai, became the deputy chief ministers while their four colleagues became ministers. Independents Rohan Khaunte and Govind Gaude also joined the cabinet.

The first one to jump out and seize a ministerial berth was ‘loyal Congressman’ Vishwajeet Rane. He quit minutes after taking oath as the MLA, a historic record he created on 16 March 2017. In this episode, Parrikar as well as his successor Dr Pramod Sawant engineered further defections; not to form the government, but to weaken the opposition. By October, two more Congress MLAs, Subhash Shirodkar and Dayanad Sopte, resigned and got re-elected on BJP tickets.

After Parrikar’s sad demise two years later, when Sawant took over on 27 March 2019, two of the three MGP legislators: Babu Azgaonkar and Dipak Prabhu Pauskar merged their twothird group into the BJP. Coalition partner Sudin Dhavalikar was dropped. By July 2019, 10 more Congress legislators formed a group of two-thirds and joined the BJP. As a result, all the three ministers of the Goa Forward Party and independent minister Rohan Khaunte were dropped. The coalition partners were dumped, probably because they had started acting ‘over smart’. The BJP rose from 13 to 27 while the Congress was reduced from 17 to five and MGP from three to one. Yet another unique kind of defection episode in India’s political history!

TOPPLINGS & CMS OF GOA: 1963 TO 2021

As of the time this book was being penned, a total number of 15 legislators from the Congress and the MGP have quit their parties in order to ‘strengthen’ the hands of Modi-ji. And still, the Congress continues to be in the prime position and the main opposition in the state as Goa goes for a fresh poll in 2022.

The following table shows how many chief ministers have become victims of rebellions and who ditched their own parties to become chief ministers. However, this list only gives indications of what must have happened during these toppling games. Not only the Congress, but BJP leaders like Manohar Parrikar also became CM for the first time by engineering defections in the Congress camp.

The history of defections in Goa is so ‘rich’ that I may have to write a special book on it. Just as the tip of the iceberg, here are some random facts and figures. The ninth Assembly of 1999 had 25 professional and habitual defectors out of 40. From 1990 to 2002, after which started the BJP era, Goa had 13 chief ministers in three Assemblies. In these 12 years, defections took place 21 times and the number of detectors was 80. That does not mean 80 MLAs defected. A large chunk among them had defected at least twice in these 12 years. The BJP, for example in 1999, had 10 MLAs in the beginning. When the then CM Manohar Parrikar had suddenly dissolved the Assembly prematurely, the saffron party had 11 defectors with them, more than their own party men. Similarly, in 2017, people had elected only 13 saffronites. Today, as this book goes to print and Goa goes for elections, the BJP has 27 MLAs. More than double!^11

Christians ‘Love’ BJP

The Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh (RSS) is the umbrella organisation of the Sangh Parivar. The BJP is its political wing, which is supposedly expected to work on the lines of the RSS ideology. Vimarsh Prakashan of New Delhi has recently published a book ‘Future Bharat: An RSS Perspective’. It is a compilation of lectures delivered by RSS Sarsanghchalak Mohan Bhagwat in New Delhi from 17 to 19 September 2018. During these lectures, he was asked a question: “In the ‘Bunch of Thoughts’, the Muslim community has been addressed as enemies. Does the Sangh accept these views?”

Bhagwat gave a lengthy reply as to why Muslims need not fear but must love their motherland, the culture, and our common ancestors, who were all Hindus etc. With regard to the ‘Bunch of Thoughts’ written by M S Golwalkar in 1960, Bhagwat said:

“.... In that book, we have given only his thoughts that were contemporary in nature. You read that book in which you will never find such things… Times are changing; the condition of the organisation also changes; so also, the manner of articulation changes. We have already got permission from Dr Hedgewar to bring about necessary changes…”^12

In the ‘Bunch of Thoughts’, there are three different chapters on ‘Internal Threats to India’, titled ‘The Muslims’, ‘The Christians’, and ‘The Communists’. In one of the paragraphs on ‘The Christians as the Internal Threat’, the book states:

“.... Such is the role of Christian gentlemen residing in our land today, out to demolish not only the religious and social fabric of our life but also to establish political domination in various pockets and if possible all over the land … Jesus had called upon his followers to give their all to the poor, the ignorant and the downtrodden. But what have his followers done in practice?.... Are we not aware of the atrocious history of Christian missionaries in our own country, of how they carried sword and fire in Goa and elsewhere? There is the story of ‘Saint’ Xavier, who used to experience the highest joy of his life when he used to see the new converts trampling upon their former gods and goddesses, razing their temples to the ground and insulting their own parents and elders who remained Hindus.

So long as the Christians here indulge in such activities and consider themselves as agents of the international movement for the spread of Christianity, and refuse to offer their first loyalty to the land of their birth and behave as true children of the heritage and culture of their ancestors, they will remain here as hostiles and will have to be treated as such.”^13

Did the BJP manage to come to power by remaining hostile towards the Christians in a Hindu-majority Goa?

BJP leader Manohar Parrikar always called himself a proud Swayamsevak of the RSS and started building the BJP in Goa in the background of the Babri Masjid-Ram Janmabhoomi issue. Before that, the Jan Sangh and the BJP had made three attempts since 1972 (excluding the combined effort with the Janata Party), but could not garner more than two per cent votes in any of these elections. The saffron party also did not gain more than two per cent votes in the seven seats it contested in the 1989 Assembly election. But in the 1991 Lok Sabha election, Parrikar polled 18 per cent votes in North Goa and rose up to the third position, just two per cent less than the runners-up MGP. Similarly, in South Goa, Shripad Naik polled 14 per cent votes to get to the third position.

In the 1994 Assembly election, by aligning with the MGP, the BJP made a debut in the eighth Assembly by winning four seats: Manohar Parrikar (Panaji), Shripad Naik (Madkai), Digambar Kamat (Margao) and Narhari Haldankar (Valpoi). It then rose to 10 seats in 1999, 17 seats in 2002 and dropping to 14 in 2007. But the Hindutva party could acquire majority seats of 21 in the 40-member House only when the so-called ‘enemies’ of the RSS were made the friends of the BJP, especially the Christian community and the Muslim minorities. Till then, the saffronites were either leading the governments with the help of the Congress defectors or with the help of small parties available for political auction like the MGP, UGDP etc.

In 1994, the BJP emerged with a bang, filling the toothless opposition space occupied by the MGP. Parrikar exposed a multi-crore power scam by the then Power Minister Mauvin Godinho in the Rane-led Congress government. (That alleged scamster Mauvin Godinho is now a senior minister in the BJP government!) With a mere one-tenth of the strength of the 40-member Assembly, the BJP also supported from outside the Dr Wilfred de Souza’s defector-government, formed in 1998. The Hindutva party’s first love in the defection game was Dr Willy, the Goan politician known for his ‘Christian politics’.

His 10-member splinter group – the Goa Rajiv Congress – also included two other Christians MLAs, Carmo Pegado and Fatima D’Sa, besides Dayanand Narvekar, Subhash Shirodkar, Chandrakant Chodankar, Deu Mandrekar, Pandurang Bhatale, Pandu Vasu Naik and Jagdish Acharya. It lasted for only four months. His three ministers – Dayanand Narvekar, Subhash Shirodkar and Pandu Vasu Naik – along with deputy speaker Deu Mandrekar split from the government that was supported by the MGP from inside and by the BJP from outside. The BJP was then quick to demand President’s Rule.

With this second defection of ‘homecoming’, Luizinho Faleiro became the new Chief Minister of the Congress, but for not more than two-and-a-half months. Within 68 days, two of his ministers, 76-year old Deu Mandrekar (MLA for the third time), along with independent John Manuel Vaz withdrew their support, pushing the Faleiro government into a minority. Dr Willy once again staked his claim with the support of the MGP and the BJP. But suddenly the BJP made a volte face, changed its strategy, and refused to support the Willy government. President’s Rule was imposed on 12 February 1999.^14

For four months till the next Assembly election, Goa witnessed one of the best administrations, run by Governor Lt Gen (Retd) J F R Jacob with only two advisors: Goa-born senior bureaucrat in Delhi Albano Couto and M N Buch.

After pulling the rug from under Dr Willy’s feet, a similar strategy was played by BJP’s master strategists late Pramod Mahajan and Goa’s Manohar Parrikar, when a fresh Assembly election was announced in 1999. They responded positively to the initiative taken by mine owner Auduth Timblo of Fomento and prolonged the alliance talks with the MGP till the last minute. Then, just a couple of days before the last day of nominations, they broke off the alliance talks on flimsy grounds, throwing the MGP completely off guard. The most powerful opposition party till yesterday had to literally hunt for candidates. The last-minute-ditching strategy worked once again as the BJP turned the tables. The saffron brigade rose from four to 10 while the MGP reduced from 10 to four. Parrikar announced proudly: “Though Lord Rama is our national hero, my idol in politics is Lord Krishna”, obviously referring to Krishna Niti described in Hindu mythology.

Despite these serial defections, especially by the Congressmen, the Congress still rose to 21 seats, with Luizinho Faleiro once again becoming the Chief Minister. This was the first time the Congress had achieved the magic figure of 21 in the 40-member House. But Faleiro was not confident about his own party colleagues. He engineered defections in all the three smaller parties in order to ‘strengthen’ the Congress. Both UGDP MLAs Suresh Parulekar and Jose Philip D’Souza; Ramakant Khalap and Prakash Velip out of four from the MGP, and Francis D’Souza from the GRC, leaving its leader Dr Willy all alone, joined the Congress. But even the strength of 26 could not sustain Faleiro for more than six months. His archrival Francisco Sardinha split from the Congress with 10 more members, to seize the throne on 24 November 1999.

The BJP this time participated in the coalition government of defectors, except that Manohar Parrikar did not join the cabinet. Sardinha’s Goa People’s Congress had seven Christian defectors: Sardinha, Alex Sequreira, Victoria Fernandes, Arecio D’Souza, Francis Silveira, Francis D’Souza, and Mauvin Godinho, whose power scam the BJP had exposed just two years earlier. But Sardinha’s defector government buckled within nine months due to Parrikar’s Krishna Niti. In October 2000, Parrikar engineered defections in Sardinha’s GPC as well as more defections in the ‘original’ Congress. Khalap and Velip defected for the second time within nine months from the GPC while Ravi Naik, Shaikh Hassan Haroon, Babu Azgaonkar, and Sanjay Bandekar split from the Congress to join the BJP.

Parrikar’s 14-member cabinet included two Christians and one Muslim: Filipe Neri Rodrigues, Jose Philip D’Souza and Shaikh Hassan Haroon. But the defection activity had not stopped. Sensing trouble from within his cabinet to topple his one-and-a-half-year old government, Parrikar surprised the whole opportunistic political world of Goa. He suddenly moved into action on 27 February 2002 by convening an emergency cabinet meeting at the International Centre Goa (much closer to the Raj Bhavan than the Panaji Secretariat) and rushed to the Governor at Cabo, recommending dissolution of the two-anda- half-year old Assembly.

Though his letter claimed that the premature dissolution was recommended by the cabinet, the cabinet members were totally in the dark. They heard about it from us: the media. Opposition Leader Luizinho Faleiro alleged that the dissolution was not on the official agenda of the cabinet. But it simply didn’t matter to the Governor since who mattered as per the Constitution was the Chief Minister, not his council of ministers. The Governor was bound to implement the cabinet recommendation. Atal Bihari Vajpayee was heading the BJP government at the Centre at this moment and Mohammed Fazal, a BJP loyalist, was the Goa Governor. With the Centre’s blessings, Parrikar managed to continue as a Caretaker Government with his entire cabinet, until a fresh election was held on 30 May 2002, coincidentally on Goa Statehood Day!^15

After that the BJP changed its entire political strategy. It had realised that the Hindutva religious card didn’t work in Goa. Parrikar, during his short stint, had performed very well, especially in financial management by presenting some brilliant budgets and raising revenue locally by filling the loopholes. He had also filled the public treasury through non-tax revenue, which had not been revised by his Congress predecessors for two to three decades. Parrikar thus made Good Governance his main plank and pushed his Soft Hindutva strategy under the carpet. This proud RSS Swayamsevak had skilfully revamped his image as a minority-friendly political leader. In 1999, the BJP had fielded only four candidates from the minorities, in the Christian-dominated constituencies of Old Conquests, especially in Tiswadi, Mormugao, and Salcete talukas: Socorro Fernandes (St Cruz), Anthony Fernandes (Cortalim), Julio D’Silva (Cuncolim) and Shaikh Jina (Navelim). Among them, only two candidates rose up to runner-up position: D’Silva in Cuncolim by polling 26 per cent votes and Jina in Navelim with 14 per cent votes against Luizinho Faleiro who polled 75 per cent votes.

However, in the 2002 Assembly poll, the BJP fielded eight minority candidates (out of 39) in the four talukas of the Old Conquests: Francis D’Souza (Mapusa), Tony Rodrigues (Taleigao), Shaikh Hassan Haroon (Mormugao), Anthony Vaz (Cortalim), Jose Pinheiro (Loutolim), Laxmi Gonsalves (Benaulim), Julio D’Silva (Cuncolim) and Shaikh Jina (Navelim). Out of these, Francis D’Souza not only got elected, but remained as the BJP MLA for four consecutive terms till 2017. After his sad demise, his son Joshua is now a BJP legislator. Rodrigues (25%) and Shaikh Hassan (28%) stood at second position while Vaz (27%) and D’Silva (20%) held the third position.^16

Parrikar became the CM once again on 3 June 2002, with the BJP rising to 17 seats in a hung Assembly. It was one seat more than the 16-member Congress. With the BJP still ruling at the Centre, he formed the government with the support of the three-member UGDP, two-member MGP and Independent Filipe Neri Rodrigues. He had four Christian ministers: Francisco D’Souza from the BJP, Babush Monserrate and Mickky Pacheco from the UGDP and Filipe Neri, the independent. After Mickky was dropped from the cabinet in June 2004, Matanhy Saldanha from the UGDP was accommodated. To strengthen his government, Parrikar engineered defections once again, with Madkaikar quitting the MGP, Babush quitting the UGDP and Isidore Fernandes from the Congress. They were made ministers, increasing the strength of the Christian ministers by two more.^17

Then in some dramatic incidents witnessed in the Assembly, including the physical eviction of Filipe Neri by the police from the House, the Parrikar government was reduced to a minority within two years and eight months. It began with Parrikar dropping Babush from the ministry. That led to Madkaikar and Isidore quitting the BJP. Then Mickky joined the BJP and quit it in one day, claiming that he believed in front-stabbing, not back-stabbing. The coalition partners − the MGP and Filipe Neri Rodrigues − withdrew support to the government. While the newly sworn in Congress government led by Pratapsingh Rane was in trouble due to disqualifications and other vexing issues, the three-time BJP MLA Digambar Kamat came to his rescue. Claiming that he had been suffocating in the Hindutva party all those years, he quit the BJP. It is known as the Ghusmat episode in the history of Goan politics!

This was the time when China had emerged as the major client for Goan iron ore, including the low quality rejects. Illegal mining had slowly started rising in Goa while three-time BJP MLA Digambar Kamat was the Minister for Mines. Auduth Timblo of Fomento Mines moved into action, took his ‘political revenge’ on the BJP for breaking its alliance with the MGP in 1999 and put a stop to the uncertainty over the survival of the Rane government. Digambar continued as the Mines Minister.

The government also faced a historic agitation in 2006 against the disastrous Regional Plan framed by the Town and Country Planning Minister Babush Monserrate. The construction lobby of land grabbers had gone on a rampage, and people across Goa were up in arms. Bowing before the public outcry, Babush was dropped and the disastrous Regional Plan was scrapped. The Rane government survived till the next Assembly election.

In the 2007 election, the BJP slipped down to 14, the Congress rose to 16 in a hung Assembly once again. With illegal mining booming, mines minister Digambar Kamat rose to become CM and Parrikar became the Opposition Leader for five long years, without any toppling or defection taking place despite a hung Assembly. The BJP fielded only four Christian candidates, of which only Francis D’Souza won. Agnelo Silveira (Taleigao), Antonio Caído (St André) and Milagres Gonsalves (Cuncolim) lost.

Riding over the rampant illegal mining, which was later estimated by Justice Shah Commission to be to the tune of Rs 35,000 crore rupees, Kamat impressed the Goan populace by presenting an alternate environment-friendly Regional Plan prepared by a Task Force led by Goa-born internationally famed architect Charles Correa. Kamat also scrapped the five Special Economic Zones, which were exposed as a real estate land scam. However, on the other hand, the unabated destruction of the hinterland and even the Sahyadri Ghat continued, until the Supreme Court banned Goa’s mining activity in 2012. Parrikar, as the chairman of the Public Accounts Committee, had exposed the illegal mining steered by Kamat.

The opposition leader also led the agitation against Medium of Instruction when Kamat continued government grants to the 127 English medium primary schools run by the Church. It was directly in contravention of the government policy of 1992 not to give government grants to English medium schools. Accordingly all the Church schools had switched over to Konkani medium. But no government had followed its preventive clause not to permit new English medium private primary schools. Private English schools kept mushrooming with the blessings of the double-standard politicians. This duplicity resulted in the increasing trend of parents sending their children to English medium primary schools. This exodus drastically affected the strength of the Konkani schools run by the Church. After running Konkani schools for two long decades, the Church-run Diocesan Society of Education finally decided to switch back to the English medium. Digambar Kamat assured to continue their salary grants. A state-wide agitation began against this, led by Konkani leaders, who joined hands with the Sangh Parivar. Parrikar also joined the agitation of the Bharatiya Bhasha Suraksha Manch (BBSM) to oppose the Church.

In spite of this, the Church came in support of Parrikar and his BJP in the 2012 Assembly election, in order to teach a lesson to the corrupt and defector-driven Congress, which was taking the Christian community for granted.

In the 2012 election, the BJP strategically contested only 28 seats, by supporting the Mickky-led Goa Vikas Party in Salcete, as well as three independents. In addition, the Hindutva party fielded six Christian candidates. All of them won: Francis D’Souza (Mapusa), Michael Lobo (Calangute), Glenn Ticlo (Aldona), Carlos Almeida (Vasco), Matanhy Saldanha (Cortalim) and Nilesh Cabral (Curchorem). The BJP won 21 seats, besides the two GVP MLAs, Mickky Pacheco (Nuvem) and Caitu Silva (Benaulim) as well as the two independents it had supported: Avertano Furtado (Navelim) and Benjamin Silva (Velim). The Hindu-Christian ‘Bahujan formula’ of Bhau Bandodkar worked well for the BJP too!

Since then, the BJP in Goa has been holding its fort with the help of Christians. In the last election held in 2017, the BJP slipped down to 13 while the Congress rose from nine to 17, once again in a hung Assembly. Out of these 13, seven MLAs were Christians. Perhaps it is a record that the saffron party has created in India, where the majority of its legislators belonged to the minority community. Both the BJP and the Church were soft to each other. Due to this and the BJP being in power at the centre, Parrikar managed to fly the tricolour flag on the banks of river Mandovi on the Independence Day, once again by using the crutches of the power-hungry regional outfits. He moved down to Goa, leaving the influential defence ministry of the country, to hold the reins of power

After Parrikar’s sudden demise in March 2019 due to pancreatic cancer, Dr Pramod Sawant, the only BJP cadre politician left in the legislative party, succeeded him. In order to strengthen its position in the Assembly, the BJP continued to engineer defections in the Congress as well as the MGP. While the saffron party is 27-member strong today, 15 among them are Christians.

Since 2002, the Hindutva party has succeeded in electing almost 12 Christian legislators. From time to time, nine more Christian MLAs have defected and held the saffron lotus on their shoulders with pride. In addition, almost 10 more Christian MLAs have split from the Congress and ruled hand-in-hand with the Hindutva party.

Due to this, the BJP in Goa had to also face the wrath of its parent organisation, the RSS. Goa witnessed a state-wide revolt by the RSS cadres, led by its state-level Sanghchalak Principal Subhash Velingkar, on the eve of the 2017 Assembly election. To avoid displeasing the Church and the Christian community, Parrikar followed his predecessor Digambar Kamat in continuing salary grants to the Church-run English schools. The agitation started once again. Velingkar converted the BBSM into a political outfit − the Goa Suraksha Manch (GSM). He vowed to finish the “anti-national” BJP!

The GSM lost all the five seats it contested, securing barely 10 per cent of the votes. But the RSS cadres certainly succeeded in defeating many BJP candidates by diverting their votes to the winning candidates, no matter which party they belonged to. It even included Babush Monserrate in Panaji and Vijay Sardesai in Fatorda. The GSM was created only for those hardcore BJP sympathisers, who would never vote for the Congress or other anti-BJP outfits. It had a huge impact. A total of 12 BJP bigwigs lost their elections. It included the sitting chief minister Laxmikant Parsekar, ministers Rajendra Arlekar, Dyanand Mandrekar, Dilip Parulekar, and Mahadev Naik, sitting MLAs Kiran Kandolkar, Subhash Naik, Ganesh Gaonkar and Subhash Phaldesai as well as former MLAs Damu Naik, Prakash Velip, and Vijay Pai Khot.

Velingkar later on admitted in a ‘Straightforward’ interview with me that “our priority in the 2017 election was to defeat the BJP, not to get the GSM elected. We did not give a public call to divert our votes to the winning candidate. Our RSS cadres are intelligent enough to know what is the priority and act accordingly.”^18

As a result, the BJP was left with only four from the original cadres of the party including Dr Pramod Sawant, Sidharth Kuncolienker, Rajesh Patnekar, and Milind Naik. Pandurang Madkaikar and Pravin Zantye were lifted from the Congress. On the other hand, all the seven Christian MLAs of the BJP were re-elected. Only Arthur D’Silva in Curtorim lost to Alex Reginald Lourenco of the Congress. And in most of the seats where the BJP did not have Christian candidates, the Congress won. It looked like the Church had played the Krishna Niti of Parrikar. It worked, as the BJP eventually came to power and the continuation of salary grants to the Church-run English medium schools is now no longer an issue.

Velingkar, the political Guru of Parrikar, decided to take ahead his task even after his disciple had died and a fresh bye-election was announced for Parrikar’s vacant Panaji seat on 19 May 2019. Velingkar himself entered the fray against BJP’s Siddharth Kuncolienker. His defeat was really pathetic. The RSS rebel leader could garner hardly three per cent votes; 516 to be precise. He lost to the BJP as well as the Congress and announced his retirement from election politics. Babush Monserrate, the victorious Congress MLA, is now in the BJP while his wife Jennifer is a minister!

This is the way the BJP is surviving today in Goa. By having almost 16 old and new Congressmen as their MLAs from among its 27, it has become the Bharatiya Janata Party of the Congress. And with 15 Christian MLAs, the Hindutva party has also become the party of majority Christians. The enemies described in the ‘Bunch of Thoughts’ have become friends of the Hindutva party and the friends like the RSS rebels have become the arch enemies of the BJP.

These are the dynamics of the Ajeeb politics of Goa!!!

The Regional ‘Rejects’

The Opinion Poll proved that when Goans want to protect their language, culture, ecology or identity, they think beyond politics. But when they think about politics, they don’t support the regional parties espousing the regional sentiments. For that matter, not a single regional party could come to power or even strengthen its roots in Goa’s political soil in the last 60 years. On the contrary, they were uprooted by the Goan voters. All such experiments have failed miserably.

The only regional party that could come to power and rule Goa for 16 long years uninterruptedly was the Maharashtrawadi Gomantak Party. But was it a regional party in its true sense? In fact, the MGP was formed to eliminate Goa’s regional Konkani identity by merging it into a Marathi state.

On the other hand, the United Goans Party, which fought for a separate state, could never cross 12 seats in the 28-seat Goa (Daman and Diu were one seat each). In fact, in the third election held in 1972, the UGP slipped down to 10 seats while the MGP rose to 18. That was the last election for the United Goans Party. The UGP then simply disappeared from Goa’s political scenario as its tall regional leaders like Dr Jack Sequeira and Anant alias Babu Naik preferred to join the national parties like the Janata Party and the Congress respectively.

The MGP continues. But after losing the battle of making Marathi the official language in 1986-87, the party became a ‘workshop’ for the Congress, supplying candidates to them as and when required. Its prominent leaders kept on jumping out of the sinking ship to try their luck with the national parties. The BJP, in the meanwhile, captured MGP’s dedicated vote bank, making the Lion completely powerless. And now Sudin Dhavalikar, its new supremo, has turned the roaring Lion into a begging Lion. The ‘party of individuals’ shamelessly negotiates power-sharing in the hung Assemblies. We can unhesitantly call it a ‘stepney’ for Congress as well as the BJP, with no ideology of any sort except greed for power.

Nationally, Goa has been at the forefront, fighting issues of regional identity and protecting its ecology for the last 50 years. It began with pollution at Zuari Agro Industries and protecting interests of traditional workmen like Render (toddy tappers) and Ramponkar (traditional fishermen) in the 70s, a militant students’ movement and violent Konkani movement in the 80s, opposing allegedly polluting projects like Nylon 6,6, alignment of Konkan railway, and destruction of the coastal belt due to five-star tourism in the 90s and state-wide agitation against the destructive Regional Plan as well as diversion of Mhadei river in the first decade of the 21st century. And now, it is fighting illegal mining and casino-drugs-driven tourism as well as opposing three linear projects – double-tracking of a rail line from Karnataka’s Hospet to Vasco, laying down a 400-kV power transmission line through the Sahyadri range in Mollem and four-laning of the existing NH 4A.

THE FATE OF REGIONAL PARTIES

No | Party | Polls | Contested | Candidates | Won | %
1 | United Goans Party | 4 | 102 | 35 | 34% |
2 | Gomant Lok Pokx | 3 | 16 | 00 | 00 |
3 | United Goans Democratic Party | 5 | 65 | 9 | 14% |
4 | Goa Vikas Party | 4 | 18 | 2 | 11% |
5 | Goa Suraj Party | 3 | 11 | 00 | 00 |
6 | Save Goa Front | 1 | 17 | 2 | 12% |
7 | Goa Forward Party | 1 | 4 | 3 | 35% |
| TOTAL | 21 | 233 | 51 | 22% |

But none of these regional sentiments, except the anti-merger movement, translated into a robust regional party that would challenge the mighty national parties like the Congress and the BJP. On the contrary, the following table clearly shows the pathetic condition of the regional parties in Goa, from 1963 till 2017 elections:

The table does not include the MGP since it is not a regional party in its true sense of regionalism. It also does not include the parties formed due to rebellions in the parent parties. And, of course, the question simply doesn’t arise to include the parties (or the groups) formed by defectors to topple the governments of the parent parties, to seize power. The table has listed only those regional parties which were formed much before elections, independently, with regional aspirations, as an alternative to the national parties.

UGP: The only regional party that was overwhelmingly supported by the people of Goa was the Dr Jack Sequeira-led United Goans Party. It actually contested only the first three elections, from 1963 to 1972, displaying an impressive voting percentage between 30 to 38 per cent. Babush Monserrate, in 2017, revived the party and contested two seats. He won from Panaji, but his so-called associate Ramakant Borkar was in the sixth position with a mere seven per cent of the votes.

None of the other regional outfits could cross 21 per cent votes (UGDP in 2002 election with ten candidates won three seats). The only exception is the Goa Forward Party, which polled 35 per cent of votes in 2017. But it had fielded only four candidates, and three of them emerged victorious.

In fact, except for the UGP, none of these regional parties had aimed at coming to power on their own. While the magic figure to form the government is 21 in the 40-member Assembly, no regional party, since 1989, even contested more than half of the seats. Most of the time, they contested less than ten seats, sometimes just one or two seats. This itself is ample proof that these regional parties were not formed to lead the regional aspirations of the Goans and rule Goa. The sole and whole intention was to share power with the big national parties.

Precisely this is the reason they could win hardly 51 seats out of 233 seats all these parties contested from time to time. And if we exclude the UGP era, we realise that the rest of the six parties won only 16 seats out of 131 seats they contested in 17 different elections in nearly three decades. That’s pathetic.

GLP: Gomant Lok Pokx was one regional party that had evolved through people’s struggles like Render (toddy tappers), Ramponkar (traditional fishermen), factory and mining workers, motorcycle pilots etc. It was demanding the continued implementation of the Tenancy Act. It was also espousing the cause of ‘Sons of the Soil’, which had migrants as its target. The party was led by two former MPs, Adv Amrut Kansar and Erasmo Sequeira as well social activists like Victoria Fernandes, Matanhy Saldanha, Celso Dias, Antonio Fernandes, etc.

The party contested two Lok Sabha elections of 1984 and 1991, but polled around three-four per cent votes which came down to less than one per cent in the second contest. In the 1989 Assembly election, the GLP contested only 11 seats, that too in the Old Conquests, like Tivim, Calangute, Saligao, Panaji, Taleigao, St Cruz, St Andre, Loutolim and Cortalim. Prashant Naik among them had withdrawn from Canacona at the last minute. The overall percentage was not more than 12 per cent in 11 places. Only Victoria could garner around 4500 votes and lost to Congress MLA Victor Gonsalves. All others lost miserably. In 1994, they once again contested only four seats including Erasmo Sequeira and Matanhy Saldanha, but could not poll more than three per cent votes.

UGDP: While the GLP experiment had failed, in 1994, another regional experiment emerged across Goa: the United Goans Democratic Party. It was originally formed at the behest of Dr Wilfred de Souza to embarrass his rival, the then chief minister Ravi Naik. Raghurai Tamba, a Panaji-based businessman, had taken Ravi head-on some gelatine-related issue. He was the founder president of the party. Churchill Alemao, as he claims, did not found the UGDP. In fact, after quitting the Congress to topple Rane, this ‘18-day chief minister’ was hunting for a party to contest from.^19

The UGDP accommodated him, while fielding 20 candidates in the 1994 poll. It had two former MLAs as the candidates: Luis Proto Barbosa (19%) and Radharao Gracias (41%). Both of them lost to the Congress, in Cortalim and Loutolim respectively. But in the first attempt itself, three MLAs were elected by defeating Congress bigwigs: Churchill Alemao beat Monte Cruz in Benaulim, Antonio Gaonkar grounded Francisco Sardinha in Curtorim, and Arecio D’Souza defeated the then GPCC president Shantaram Naik in Cuncolim.

The party however was found to be more effective in the Christian-dominated constituencies of the Old Conquests. Four more candidates faired quite well: Nazario Pinto (34%) against Luizinho Faleiro in Navelim, Simon Caido (19%) against Carmo Pegado in St Andre, Filipe Neri Rodrigues (19%) against Manu Fernandes in Velim and Shaikh Muhammad Akbar (12%) against Digambar Kamat of BJP in Madgao. Also in Curchorem, Luis Diniz polled 17% votes against Domnic Fernandes. But Tamba, the president, could not even mobilise one per cent votes in Panaji. Similar was the really pathetic condition of other candidates in Pernem, Dhargalim, Pale, Shiroda, Sanguem, Quepem and Canacona in the New Conquests as well as Vasco and Fatorda in the Old Conquests.

The UGDP then decided to take five-term Congress MP Eduardo Faleiro head-on in the 1996 Lok Sabha poll. Churchill Alemao on the UGDP ticket defeated him, after which he resigned as the Benaulim MLA. In a bye-election held on 11 October 1996, his brother Joaquim Alemao was elected from Benaulim. This victory made Churchill popular throughout Goa, including in the New Conquests. He was pulling crowds of Hindus as well as Christians and Muslims in the Old as well as New Conquests, even in the interiors of Sattari. For the people, he was a long-awaited messiah.

But the non-Congress governments of H D Deve Gowda and I K Gujral at the centre could not last for long and fresh general elections were announced in 1998. UGDP MP Churchill lost this election to the Congress as well as the BJP candidates. The dejected Churchill struck a deal and joined the Congress along with his brother Joaquim and Arecio D’Souza. He and Arecio also got elected in Benaulim and Cuncolim in the 1999 Assembly election.

By this time, two activist lawyers of Salcete, Anacleto Viegas and Radharao Gracias, had taken over the control of the UGDP. The party fielded 15 candidates, polled 15 per cent votes and also got two MLAs elected: former MLA Suresh Parulekar from Calangute and Jose Philip D’Souza from Vasco. Radharao contested from Benaulim but lost the battle to his former colleague Churchill. Similarly, another lawyer friend and former MLA Herculano Dourado also lost to Congress MLA Mauvin Godinho in Cortalim. The party candidates could not even save deposits in 12 of the remaining 13 seats.

After that the UGDP became a party to strike deals with some wealthy ambitious politicians to raise funds, with which serious candidates of the party were trying their luck. It worked well in the 2002 Assembly poll. Out of 10 candidates it fielded, two wealthy and ambitious politicians got elected: Babush Monseratte from Taleigao and Mickky Pacheco from Benaulim, who defeated Churchill. In the bargain, Matanhy Saldanha from the party cadre also got elected from Cortalim. Radharao however once again lost the battle against Congress MLA Alexio Sequeira in Loutolim. Some former MLAs also tried their luck with the UGDP, but lost, like veteran UGP MLA Teotonio Pereira in St Andre, ex-minister Monte Cruz in Fatorda, and ex- MLA Victor Gonsalves in St Cruz.

By the end of the term, Babush had travelled to the BJP and then Congress to grab ministerial positions in both the governments. Mickky had formed his own UGDP (Secular) while staunch anti-Congressman Matanhy had joined hands with BJP’s Manohar Parrikar while remaining in the party.

In the 2007 election, the UGDP lawyer-duo struck new deals with Congress rejects including Babush Monserrate, who won in Taleigao. His wife Jennifer also entered the election arena from St Cruz to score in the third position. Matanhy Saldanha lost to Mauvin Godinho once again while ex-MLA Prakash Phadte lost in Mayem. Joseph Sequeira in Calangute and Dr Jorson Fernandes in Cuncolim lost too. The others were simply negligible in their performance.

The 2012 election was so pathetic for the UGDP that none of their seven candidates were known politicians and none of them could score well. The total percentage was hardly six per cent. In fact, their Pernem candidate Santosh Mandrekar set a new record of gaining the lowest number of votes: 50. The party did not contest the 2017 election. Now for the forthcoming 2022 election, its president Dr Jorson Fernandes has joined the Trinamool Congress, with due ‘permission’ from the UGDP supremos: Radharao Gracias and Anacleto Viegas.

GOA FORWARD: On the eve of the Assembly election 2017 and on the eve of India’s Republic Day, on 25 January 2016, a new regional party came into being: the Goa Forward Party. The core slogan was Goem, Goenkar, Goenkarponn (Goa, Goan, Goan Ethos). It was floated by Vijai Sardesai, an independent MLA from Fatorda who was denied Congress ticket in 2012. He mobilised the best political brains of South Goa, made eminent educationist and political analyst Prabhakar Timble the President and entered the fray on an anti-BJP plank. After a series of alliance talks with the Congress failed, the GFP fielded four candidates. Barring Velim, GFP won three seats: Vijai Sardesai (Fatorda), Jayesh Salgaoankar (Saligao) and Vinod Palienkar (Siolim).

However, when the time came to form the coalition government, GFP leader Vijai Sardesai made a 360 degree turnaround and surrendered to the mighty central leaders of the BJP, who were running the government at the Centre.

‘Professional negotiator’ MGP also joined the cabinet besides two more independents. In protest, GFP President Prabhakar Timble resigned from the party. Other social activists like Mohandas Lolienkar, Prashant Naik, Dilip Prabhudesai, Saiesh Palondikar etc. however stood behind Vijai. The GFP also became a partner in the BJP-led National Democratic Alliance (NDA) at the national level.

As has been narrated in the earlier section on defections, the GFP was finally dropped from the government in July 2019. Since then, Vijai Sardesai claims to be hard-core anti-BJP once again. He has tried repeatedly to have a pre-poll alliance to defeat the BJP ‘unitedly’, after which he also tried to align with Mamata Banerjee’s Trinamool Congress. He initially agreed and then backed out from the offer of merging the GFP into the TMC and began fresh talks with the Congress. Meantime party MLA Jayesh Salgaokar resigned and joined the BJP, while the working president Kiran Khandolkar, a former BJP MLA, crossed over to the TMC. However, in the bargain, the five-year old regional outfit has faded out its shining colours of Goem, Goenkar, Goenkarponn. The party supposedly of regional aspirations has proved to be yet another ‘negotiator party’ of personal aspirations!

REVOLUTIONARY GOANS: Calling itself Uzzo (Fire), a section of youth of Goa have started gathering around a new political outfit − the Revolutionary Goans (RG), which began as a social organisation five years ago. Its fiery speaker Manoj Parab has been pulling large crowds, especially in the Old Conquests and the tourism belt. Utilising social media effectively, the RG has now entered the electoral fray under the banner of the Goa Suraj Party. It has introduced a Person Of Goan Origin (POGO) bill, which they want to be passed by the Goa Assembly. They are primarily targeting the influx of migrants and want all the government facilities, schemes, policies, and programmes limited to the people of Goan origin. They also demand the scrapping of the 15-year domicile clause.

The POGO bill defines a person of Goan Origin as

“a person who is or whose either parent or grandparent were born in Goa prior to 20 December 1961 or who had a permanent habitation in Goa prior to 20 December 1961 and who were citizens of India post-liberation irrespective of nationality or passport they hold currently.”

The RG wants cent per cent jobs in government and private establishments, possession of Communidade land, EDC loans and subsidies, as well as shops and properties in government establishments only for the persons of Goan origin.

“RG will fight tooth and nail any sort of discrimination against Goans, which is already being witnessed. This is aimed at promoting and encouraging vote bank politics and making Goans irrelevant. Such discrimination against us in issuance of ration cards, aadhar cards, voting cards, giving them spaces to do business as well as residences, also jobs, has resulted in such frustration among the son of the soil that there has been a virtual exodus of Goans from Goa, thus leaving greater scope for an increased influx of migrants into Goa.”

RG also opposes migrants encroaching on government and Communidade lands while also blaming migrants for spreading various types of diseases, and their involvement in criminal activities. Their official pamphlet does not denounce Goans who are also involved in such illegal, unhealthy, or criminal activities.

Also another distinct feature of the RG is that the party has evolved through a social organisation they set up five years ago and has also encouraged Goan youth to take up different opportunities being made available due to the changing socioeconomic conditions of Goa.

These two chapters have tried to highlight the unique aspects of Goan politics from 1963 till date, with the Ajeeb character of the Goan voter, the politician, as well as the Goan polity. The rest of the book will try to explore the root causes behind this kind of politics, which seems stranger or Ajeeb than the rest of India. With the BJP government trying to enforce the Bhumiputra Adhikarini Bill and the brand new political outfit the Revolutionary Goans pursuing an ethnic movement for the “Sons of the Soil Only”, this book will also try and dig into history to perceive who is the Bhumiputra of Goa, the Goan who has migrated, or the migrant who is settled in Goa. It will also try to show how Goan politics, since the ancient times of its first settlements till date, has been moving around just one distinct component of Goa – ITS LAND!

गोमंतक; हा कौल जनतेचा आहे, 13 डि सेंबर 1963↩︎

गोमंतक; श्री दयानंद बांदोडकर यांचे पं नेहरूं ना उत्तर, 17 डि सेंबर 1963↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्ति नंतरचा गोवा, पान 46↩︎

Election Commission of India↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्ति नंतरचा गोवा, पान 75-76↩︎

Shirodkar Dr P P; Who’s Who of Freedom Fighters↩︎

Election Commission of India↩︎

itsgoa.com and pamphlet of Sangharsh Natya Manch, cultural wing of Progressive Students’↩︎

बेळेकर सुहास; गोव्या तील नि वडणुका, विधानसभा व लोकसभा 1963 ते 2014↩︎

Election Commission of Indoa↩︎

Goanews.com; Defector is most powerful, 20 April 2002↩︎

Bhagwat Dr Mohan; Future Bharat- An RSS Perspective, P 87-89↩︎

गोळवलकर मा स; विचारधन (पाचवी आवृत्तीः डि सेंबर 2001), पान 177↩︎

goanews.com↩︎

rediff.com; Goa Assembly dissolved, Parrikar to continue as↩︎

Election Commission of India↩︎

goanews.com↩︎

goa365.tv; ‘Straightforward’ with Subhash Velingkar, 28 January 2018↩︎

Interview with Adv Radharao Gracias↩︎

Chapter 7

'Old' is Gold

The tiny state of Goa on the western coast of India is divided into three geographical divisions: the coastland, the midland, and the hinterland. All three are equally beautiful, pristine, peaceful, and soothing with their unique characteristics. The coastland primarily consists of beaches and low-lying river basins strewn with coconut plantations. The midland is made up of plateaus and small hillocks planted with cashew, rivulets flowing in the valleys, some islands, refreshing green paddy fields and other vegetation including Kullagar (orchards of coconut, betel nut and all kinds of fruit-bearing trees). The hinterland comprises mountainous regions of the Sahyadri Ghats with thick forests, consisting of rich flora and fauna, boasting a rich biodiversity, and replete with waterfalls.

The coastland, which was earlier predominantly dependent on fishing, toddy tapping and some agriculture, is now the economic hotspot of Goa due to tourism. The hinterland, where cashew plantation, shifting cultivation and terrace farming were the primary economic activities, has been hijacked by the mining industry operating open-pit mines for manganese and iron ore, and laterite and other stone quarries, effectively bulldozing its agricultural economy. Though industrial estates have come up on the plateaus, the midland, however, is still dominated by agriculture and horticulture. The politics of economics, accordingly, differs in all these three ‘lands’.

With agriculture coming to a grinding halt in the hinterland, tourism booming in the coastland, and manufacturing as well as the services sector growing slowly in the midland, urbanisation has increased in leaps and bounds in the last four to five decades. More in number than municipal towns are the census towns, which are spread in the villages, especially of the coastal belt. In fact, the entire coastal stretch from Pernem to Canacona is now urbanised. The locals tend to blame migrants from outside Goa for this trend, but in reality there are more locals who have migrated to the towns than the Bhaile (outsiders).

In 1960, Goa was 85 per cent rural and only 15 per cent urban. Today, it is 62 per cent urban and only 38 per cent rural. This is the opposite of the rest of India: 35 per cent urban and 65 per cent rural. In the last 50 years (till the 2011 Census), the urban population has increased by 8.19 lakhs. The migrants from other states among these would not exceed 3.5 lakhs, or at the most four lakhs. This means that the same number of Goans (or more) have either shifted their base from the village to a city managed by a municipality, or that the village itself has turned into a small township administered by a village panchayat. In addition, there are new townships like Porvorim that come under several panchayats. This has not only impacted the socioeconomic structure of Goa, but also the politics of land.

Old Conquests Rule Goa

Old and New Conquests are not merely historical terms, or geographical territories. They are more significant today politically. The Old Conquests form one-fifth of Goa’s geographical spread, consisting of only four talukas − Bardez, Tiswadi, Mormugao, and Salcete. But they include the port town of Vasco, the commercial towns of Mapusa and Margao, and the capital city of Panaji. In addition, Goa’s prime tourist belt is spread out in the Old Conquests. In contrast, in the New Conquests it is only Pernem and Canacona talukas that have some beaches, and do not have tourism spread into the interior villages. The Old Conquests are thus thickly populated, and their population is swelling by the day.

Goa has a total of 40 Assembly constituencies. Out of these, the Old Conquests comprise 24 constituencies, more than half of this total − four in Mormugao, five in Tiswadi, seven in Bardez and eight in Salcete. Even during the time when Goa was a Union Territory, when six Assemblies were constituted from 1963 to 1984 out of 28 constituencies, the Old Conquests had 16 constituencies, again more than half. And historically, we know that the Old Conquests were dominated by Christians, since no significant religious conversions took place in the New Conquests.

Constituencies In Old Conquests: Union Territory & State

TALUKAS | UT | CONSTITUENCIES | STATE | CONSTITUENCIES
Bardez | 5 | Siolim, Calangute, Mapusa,Tivim, Aldona | 7 | Siolim, Calangute, Mapusa, Tivim, Aldona, Saligao, Porvorim
Tiswadi | 4 | Panaji, St Cruz, Cumbarjuve, St Andre | 5 | Panaji, St Cruz, Cumbarjuve, St Andre, Taleigao
Mormugao | 2 | Cortalim, Dabolim | 4 | Cortalim, Dabolim, Mormugao, Vasco
Salcete | 5 | Cuncolim, Benaulim, Navelim, Margao, Curtorim | 8 | Cuncolim, Benaulim, Navelim, Margao, Curtorim, Velim, Fatorda, Nuvem
TOTAL | 16 | | 24 |

Source: Election Commission of India

Until the 2007 Assembly election, the Old Conquests had 22 constituencies. However, after delimitation, from the 2009 Lok Sabha elections, Porvorim was added to Bardez taluka and Dabolim was added to Mormugao taluka. On the other hand, in the New Conquests, Dhargalim in Pernem taluka and Poinguinim in Canacona taluka were dropped as Assembly segments. Also, old components of the other Assembly segments were exchanged, with additions and deletions. The whole exercise was conducted in response to the increasing or decreasing number of voters, as a result of in-migration from other states and local migration of Goans to urban areas.

It is therefore important to understand these trends of urbanisation that are leading to the Old Conquests becoming politically and economically dominant day by day. It is equally important to analyse the influence of the minority Christian community, which is concentrated in the Old Conquests. Are they losing their political hegemony in Goa’s politics? Is that the reason for the inhabitants of the Old Conquests to be up in arms against the housing projects coming up in their areas? Has Goa’s politics started moving around land with a demographic perspective?

Goans - Not Migrants - Congesting The Cities!

In 1977, the veteran freedom fighter Madhav Bir was elected as the Panaji MLA to the fifth assembly. During an assembly debate on Housing, he demanded that the newly formed Goa Housing Board (1969) should start developing the plateau of Alto-Betim, through which passed a road going to Mapusa from Panaji via the Mandovi bridge which was built in 1971. It was then an open space except for a few prominent bungalows, like the one owned by the then chief minister, Shashikala Kakodkar.

With Panaji seeing rapid development as the capital of Goa, pressure for housing had started mounting. Taking up the suggestion made by Bir, a new Housing Board colony came up there, followed by other colonies, such as the Journalists’ Colony, Defence Colony, etc. The ‘development’ of the plateau got a boost, and within four decades Porvorim became the largest township of Goa with a population of over 60,000 in a small area of 8.12 square kilometres.^1 Since 2009, it has been a separate assembly constituency with over 25,000 voters.

The Mandovi bridge collapsed in 1986, and within two years a second bridge was built. Later, the old bridge was repaired and returned into operation as a parallel bridge. In 2019, to regulate the heavy volume of traffic from Porvorim, as well as the other townships of Bardez taluka, a third bridge, the Atal Setu, has been built above the existing two bridges.

Porvorim once used to be a plateau that served as a grazing pasture for cattle. It was, in fact, a small vaddo of the Socorro village, down the plateau, at the crossroads where the Panaji- Mapusa national highway cuts through the road from Socorro to Sangolda. People living on the Porvorim plateau don’t even know that the name belonged to a small marketplace (tintto) on the crossroads down the hill. The politics of this township and the constituency revolves around land, and only the land. This plateau is shared between the six village panchayats of Socorro, Salvador de Mundo, Penha da Franca, Reis Magos, Pilerne and Sangolda. And more importantly, the land is owned by four Communidades of Serula, Pilerne, Sangolda, and Nerul. It is exclusively used for housing.

During his first tenure as the chief minister, Manohar Parrikar had proposed to incorporate this whole township, as well as the extended city of Panaji in Taleigao panchayat into the Panaji municipality, for which he had constituted Goa’s first municipal corporation, the City Corporation of Panaji (CCP). But Parrikar had to surrender to the mighty power of landpoliticians who dominated the local panchayats and the plan was shelved. Today, the CCP is a corporation only in name, while Porvorim continues to be administered by the six panchayats and the three Communidades. Hardly any person living on this plateau belongs to these villages. They are either Goans who have migrated from other villages, from Pernem to Canacona, or wealthy migrants from other states. The government has also shifted the Secretariat, the Assembly, and even the High Court to Porvorim, along with some other establishments.

Porvorim is not the only township of Goa. Panaji itself has expanded to Taleigao, Bambolim, Merces, Chimbel, Kadamba Plateau of Bainguinim, right up to Old Goa. Other towns in the Old Conquests are no exception. The port town of Vasco has expanded to cover almost all the hillocks around it, such as Sada, New Vaddem, Driver Hill, Uttor Dongor, Chichalim, Dabolim, as well as the plateau of Zuarinagar; Margao now includes Vidyanagar (Housing Board colony), Fatorda, Navelim, and Davorlim; and Mapusa covers Khorlim, Ganeshpuri, Duler, etc, making them thickly populated extended towns of Goa.

The biggest new settlement in the New Conquests is found in Ponda city that has expanded to Shantinagar, Curti, Bethora, up to Borim and Usgao. Besides this, a central vaddo like Marcela of Tivrem-Vargao panchayat, Housing Board Colonies of Sankhli, as well as Bicholim, and several other places have developed into small or large townships settled by urbanised middle and upper-class Goans. Compared to other states, Goa has very few slum areas: Baina and Zuarinagar of Vasco; Moti Dongor of Margao; Indiranagar of Chimbel; Ganganagar and Ekta Nagar of Mapusa, etc.

The Census of India defines a town as:

All places with a municipality, corporation, cantonment board or notified town area committee etc.
All other places which satisfy the following criteria:

a minimum population of 5000;
at least 75 per cent of the male working population engaged in non-agricultural pursuits; and
a density of population of at least 400 per sq. km.^2

Based on these criteria, Goa had only five towns in 1950, to which six were added after liberation in 1961. In spite of urbanisation and an influx of migrants into city areas, by 1981, the number of towns had increased from 11 to 15, including the municipal towns. But the number doubled to 31 by 1991. By 2001 Goa had 44 towns and the figure reached 70 in 2011. This includes 14 municipalities and 56 other townships. Now, the urban agglomerations are not limited to suburbs of municipal towns, but cover practically the entire coastal belt, from Pernem in the north to Canacona in the south. The majority of these fall in the Old Conquests. For all practical purposes, the Goa of today is a City State!

Following a state-wide agitation against the conspiracy of Goa’s politicians to concretise large parts of the state, the destructive Regional Plan of Goa was finally scrapped in 2006. But the struggle continues even today. The focus has shifted to mega housing projects that are coming up in the coastal villages of the Old Conquests without first building the required infrastructure to support them. A prime example is the mega housing project of the Rahejas proposed in the sleepy village of Carmona in Salcete. The Rahejas had planned for constructing 750 dwellings in an area of 80,000 square metres, adding not less than two to three thousand people to the village population of just four thousand, living in about a thousand houses. The project, meant for people from outside Goa, was finally scrapped in spite of the support of local politicians. The urbanisation of Goa however continues unabated.

The villages of Goa are shrinking as it slowly turns into a City State. The graph clearly shows that the rate of population growth in rural parts of Goa is not only declining but has reached a negative mode for the last three decades. From minus two per cent in 2001, it has declined dramatically to minus eighteen per cent in just ten years. That’s alarming. The figures of 2021 are yet to be released.

What it means in terms of number is that though Goa had a population of five lakhs living in its villages in 1960, in 2011, despite population growth it has reached only 5.51 lakhs. That’s a negligible increase of 10 per cent over 50 years. This is because either most villagers have migrated to the cities, or their villages have been converted into urban agglomerations. In contrast, the towns of Goa had a marginal population of 87,000 at the time of liberation. Today, it has zoomed to nine lakhs. A growth of 934 per cent in five decades!

The Christian Factor In The Old Conquests

Since people from the New Conquests are migrating to the Old Conquests, it stands to reason that the numbers will be dominated by Hindus. This does not mean that Christians from the New Conquests are not migrating. For employment opportunities and better educational prospects, many Christians from the New Conquests prefer buying a flat in a city, rather than buying land in the village and building a house. Overall, the Hindu population is rising constantly in the Old Conquests and declining in the New Conquests.

However, this does not imply that Christians are a minority as far as Goa’s electoral politics is concerned. Rather, in some of the constituencies of the Old Conquests, it’s a brutal majority. Unlike in the ‘60s and ‘70s, many village-based constituencies of the Old Conquests have been swelling with urbanised Goans and migrants from outside Goa. Most of them are non- Christians. But this does not affect the Christian domination in their constituencies. The table is a testimony.

Rural Goa: 1961-2011 (%)

| HINDU | | CHRISTIAN | | MUSLIM |
| 1961 | 2001 | 1961 | 2001 | 1961 | 2001
| | | | | |
Bardez | 57 | 70 | 43 | 24 | 0 | 5
Tiswadi | 55 | 68 | 45 | 28 | 0 | 4
Mormugao | 41 | 38 | 54 | 54 | 5 | 7
Salcete | 18 | 19 | 80 | 75 | 2 | 5
OLD-CONQUESTS | 40 | 47 | 59 | 47 | 1 | 5
Pernem | 87 | 92 | 13 | 7 | 0 | 1
Bicholim | 94 | 96 | 5 | 1 | 1 | 3
Satari | 97 | 96 | 2 | 1 | 1 | 3
Ponda | 90 | 84 | 9 | 11 | 1 | 5
Quepem | 62 | 72 | 37 | 26 | 1 | 2
Sanguem | 76 | 83 | 23 | 11 | 1 | 5
Canacona | 76 | 81 | 23 | 18 | 0 | 1
NEW-CONQUESTS | 84 | 87 | 15 | 10 | 1 | 3

Source: Census of India

When Goa went for its first poll in 1963, the Christians constituted nearly 60 per cent of the electorate in the then 16 constituencies of the Old Conquests. Since then, the number of constituencies has risen to 24, new townships have come up, people from outside Goa and from the New Conquests have migrated in, but still nearly half of the population remains Christian. The Hindu population, in the last 50 years, has increased marginally, from 40 to 47 per cent. And the rise in the Muslim population is still at a single digit, from one to five per cent.

In terms of talukas, Bardez always had Hindu-majority constituencies, such as Mapusa, Siolim and Tivim. They always remained bastions of the Maharashtra Gomantak Party (MGP). In 1977, the MGP had won even the Calangute seat. Their Christian MLA, Raul Fernandes, was the education minister in Shashikala Kakodkar’s government.

The Christian population of Tiswadi has also reduced drastically in the last five decades, from 45 to 28 per cent. Even one-time Christian-majority constituencies, such as St Cruz and St Andre are dominated by the Hindus today. But, except for Shripad Kunkalienkar, who won the seat twice in 1977 and 1984 on a Congress ticket, and Vishnu Wagh who took the seat in 2012 on a BJP ticket, St Andre has always elected a Christian candidate. Dr Jack de Sequeira, known in Goan politics as the leader of the Christian community, was elected from St Cruz three times, from 1967 to 1977 on UGP and Janata Party tickets. Till today, St Cruz has not elected a Hindu MLA.

Cortalim is the only constituency in Mormugao which was dominated by Christians right from the beginning, having always had Christian MLAs. In spite of the influx of migrant outsiders and local Goans, other constituencies in and around the port town of Vasco were also held by Christian candidates several times. Momugao was in fact a Hindu-majority constituency right from the beginning and yet held by Christian legislators. Prominent among them are Urminda Lima Leitao (UGP) in 1963, John Manuel Vaz (Ind) in 1994, and his son Karl Vaz (Congress) in 2002.

Even after continuous migrations, and new townships coming up every five years, Salcete is still held by the Christian community. It has eight constituencies. The whole picture of election results in Goa changes when counting begins in Salcete. During the Union Territory days when it had five constituencies, only Margao was consistently held by a Hindu, like Vasudev Sarmalkar and Anant alias Babu Naik till he was defeated by Adv Uday Behmbre in a historic election held in 1984. All three of them were in total harmony with the Christians. The rest of the four constituencies till 1984 and seven seats till date have always been held by Christian MLAs.

The only exception is Fatorda, which came into existence as an assembly seat in 1989. Luis Alex alias Mama Cardoz, a tribal leader, won the seat thrice, from 1989 to 1999, and lost it to BJP’s Damu Naik in 2002 by a slim margin of just 588 votes, that too because Monte Cruz (UGDP) split his Congress votes by polling around 4000 votes. But Damu Naik could not hold on beyond two elections. Vijai Sardesai, either as an Independent or as a candidate of the Goa Forward Party, has been defeating the BJP candidate in Fatorda, with full support of the Christian community. He is now in trouble for the 2022 poll because the Christians are condemning him for joining hands with the BJP government.

The Election Commission of India neither maintains its records on the basis of religion, nor promotes elections on religious lines. A similar spirit is shown by Goan voters, though political parties do count the number of voters based on religion. One such break-up, though not fully authentic, was created by Vivek Mordekar, one of Goa’s leading IT professionals, on the basis of surnames. This provides a clear picture of how religion counts in Goan politics in terms of choosing popular candidates, but does not matter when it comes to voting.

Religions 2017: Old Conquests

NO | CONSTITUENCY | HINDU | CHRISTIAN | MUSLIM
1 | Nuvem | 11 | 87 | 1
2 | Benaulim | 11 | 86 | 2
3 | Velim | 18 | 78 | 4
4 | Curtorim | 27 | 64 | 8
5 | Cuncolim | 40 | 54 | 6
6 | Calangute | 48 | 49 | 3
7 | St. Andre | 52 | 46 | 2
8 | Cortalim | 48 | 44 | 8
9 | Fatorda | 48 | 42 | 10
10 | Navelim | 39 | 40 | 21
11 | Aldona | 59 | 37 | 4
12 | St.Cruz | 55 | 31 | 14
13 | Cumbarjua | 67 | 29 | 4
14 | Siolim | 69 | 29 | 3
15 | Saligao | 66 | 28 | 6
16 | Panaji | 64 | 28 | 8
17 | Taleigao | 63 | 27 | 10
18 | Margao | 56 | 23 | 21
19 | Porvorim | 70 | 23 | 7
20 | Dabolim | 67 | 22 | 11
21 | Tivim | 77 | 20 | 3
22 | Mapusa | 70 | 18 | 12
23 | Vasco-Da-Gama | 66 | 15 | 19
24 | Mormugao | 73 | 11 | 16
| AVERAGE | 53 | 39 | 9

Source: Vivek Mordekar, IT Professional, Margao

Even after an in-migration in large numbers and the influx of local Hindus (also a few Muslims), five constituencies in Salcete continue to be dominated by Christians: Nuvem, Benaulim, Velim, Curtorim and Cuncolim.

The second category shown in the table is of five constituencies where the population of Hindu and Christian- Muslim minorities is almost equal: Calangute, St Andre, Cortalim, Fatorda, and Navelim. These were the Christianmajority seats in the first two decades, but the demography has changed continually since the 1980s. Cortalim consists of a large number of migrant labourers settled in Zuarinagar, while Navelim consists of in-migrant Hindus and Christians and equally large numbers of local Hindus who have migrated from the New Conquests. In spite of this, religion never became a deciding factor in electing the MLA. Neither the MGP nor the BJP could find roots here, and neither could a candidate belonging to the Hindu community ever succeed.

The third category consists of 14 seats out of a total of 24, more than half. It also consists of major commercial or port towns in the Old Conquests, such as Mapusa, Panaji, Margao, Vasco, and Mormugao, which have always remained dominated by Hindus. But even these towns have been electing Christian candidates so far, such as Francisco D’Souza and his son Joshua in Mapusa from 1999 to 2017, once on the Goa Rajiv Congress ticket and then under the BJP banner.

With the port town getting congested, Dabolim constituency was carved out of Mormugao constituency, which included more than half of the port town and Zuarinagar too. It was then renamed as Vasco after Goa became a State. From the 2009 Lok Sabha election and 2012 of the Assembly, Vasco was separated from Dabolim, limiting it to the main town. This segment with Hindu majority but sizeable Christians, has elected Christian MLAs like Adv Herculano Dourado (1980) and Simon D’Souza (1984 &1989) of the Congress, Dr Wilfred Mesquita (1994) of the MGP, Jose Philip D’Souza (1999/2007) of UGDP and NCP, and Carlos Almeida (2012/2017) of the BJP. Even today, it has a Christian population of hardly 15 per cent. (We have already discussed Mormugao earlier).

But at the same time, the Christian domination is so strong that the Congress Chief Minister, Digambar Kamat, during his single five-year tenure from 2007-12, had to accommodate seven Christian MLAs in his 12-member cabinet. Most of them were from Salcete taluka. Even today, the Pramod Sawantled BJP government has five Christian ministers and a Deputy Speaker.

In spite of being such a dominant force, Goa could never get a Christian chief minister through a public mandate, other than Luizinho Faleiro, the sole exception. In 1999, the Congress achieved the magic figure of 21 which led to Faleiro becoming the chief minister. Otherwise, all other Christian chief ministers have seized power by toppling the ‘popular’ governments through defections and horse trading. They include Churchill Alemao (1990), Dr Luis Proto Barbosa (1990), Dr Wilfred de Souza (1993 & 1998) and Francisco Sardinha (1999).

Realising the non-religious attitude of the Goan voter, the BJP master-strategist, Manohar Parrikar, had to change his electoral tactics by going soft, even on Soft Hindutva, and follow the Congress line of ‘appeasement of the minorities’. Parrikar never succeeded in ‘Mission Salcete’ but could reach the magic figure of 21 in 2012 by winning 12 seats in the Old Conquests, by fielding Christian candidates in those constituencies.

It is perhaps for the first time in the history of Goan politics that the AAP leader, Arvind Kejriwal, has made an open statement that his deputy chief minister would be a Christian. The same AAP, had side-lined Elvis Gomes after promoting him as the CM face, claiming that his Christian face was becoming a liability. And now the ‘over smart’ party is also receiving flak from the common Goan for encouraging Bhandari and Christian politics. Not only the Delhi-based AAP, but none of the so-called ‘outsider’ parties have been able to comprehend the dynamics and spirit of Bahujan politics of Goa.

Unlike the rest of India, Goa has a different history due to the brutal policy of religious conversions that the Portuguese adopted. Goans were undoubtedly victims of the conversions as well as the Inquisition against the neo-converts. But this coin has another side. Due to the conversion policy, which the Portuguese did not implement while winning over the New Conquests, we have a mix of two major religions in Goa, divided into two Conquests. Due to this, religion-based political parties cannot play their fanatic politics in Goa. In that sense (not otherwise) the religious conversions have been a blessing in disguise for this tiny state on the western coast of India!

Wikipedia; Porvorim↩︎

Census of India↩︎

Chapter 12

Opinion (Poll) Matters, Not The ...

The initial plan of the MGP and PSP was to embarrass the Centre. The MGP would win the first election, then resign en masse within six months, face a new election, and once again resign en masse. This was meant to use the Assembly election as a pressure tactic to merge Goa into Maharashtra.[^1] But things changed dramatically once the MGP came to power. Bhausaheb Bandodkar himself, along with the MGP and the PSP leaders, postponed the agenda of the merger. Instead he concentrated on their core agenda of Land to the Tiller and overall development of Goa in the fields of education, health, agriculture, fishing, industry, cooperation, and even the development of the Mormugao port.

With the elected government coming to power, the Planning Commission of India increased the plan outlay for Goa from Rs 95 lakh to Rs 250 lakh. It also sanctioned grants of Rs seven crore for core areas like agriculture, industry, electricity, education, and health. The number of primary schools shot up from 292 in 1961 to 840 in 1964 with new school buildings coming up in the rural areas. Private primary and secondary schools as well as colleges in the cities were encouraged. Goa’s health infrastructure at the rural level was strengthened with six cottage hospitals equipped with 330 beds, 12 rural health centres, and three mobile health vehicles. Potable water was provided to the interior areas of the New Conquests like Ponda, Sanguem, Quepem etc., besides the cities. Panchayats brought 1400 acres of fallow land under cultivation, roads were built, bandhs and buildings were repaired, new wells were dug, irrigation facilities were provided, three industrial estates were set up, welfare centres were started for pregnant women, and 58 fair price shops were opened for ration. Bandodkar also requested the Centre to enhance the plan to build infrastructure like roads and bridges.[^2]

This did not mean that the crucial issue of the merger was forgotten. But Bhau was apparently convinced that it was not possible without the Centre’s blessings. Thus the issue remained in limbo for as long as Nehru was alive. Panditji left the world on 27 May 1964 and the ball of the merger began to roll once again.

Mid-Term To Plebiscite

On 9 June 1964, Lal Bahadur Shastri took over as the Prime Minister of India. With pressure from Maharashtra-based central leaders like Y B Chavan etc., the Centre began to toy with the idea of dissolving the Goa Assembly and holding fresh mid-term polls on the issue of the merger. The proposal started to gain ground with CM Bandodkar facing a rebellion within his own party to the extent of his own party men filing a no confidence motion against him with the help of the opposition UGP. However, in view of the India-Pakistan conflict that came centre stage, PM Shastri deferred the decision of mid-term polls. During his Bombay visit on 20 October, he reviewed the Goa situation, where he was also told that the rebellion was more ‘personal’ than issue-based.[^3] Shastri officially confirmed the decision to defer the Goa mid-term polls in the Lok Sabha when PSP MP Hari Vishnu Kamat raised the issue on 24 November 1964.[^4]

Meanwhile, the issue got a sudden twist with the visit of Railway Minister S K Patil to Goa in the last week of October 1964. He had come down to review the party organisation in the wake of the election debacle in the previous year. Replying to a media question on the merger during a press conference on 31 October, Patil said that the Central Parliamentary Board, at its meeting on 7 April, had decided that Goa would continue as a union territory for 10 years, after which Goans could decide their status through a ‘referendum’.[^5]

The very next day, on 1 November, Prime Minister Lal Bahadur Shastri was quizzed by the media in Bombay. He avoided a straightforward reply, claiming that he could not recollect what the Board had decided. He recalled a decision taken by the Parliamentary Board before the Goa election, when Nehru was alive. But with the Goa election result, he felt that the decision needed to be relooked into. He also admitted that there were serious differences within the Congress on this issue, making special mention of S K Patil.

The MGP instantly opposed Patil’s proposal of a plebiscite while CM Bandodkar rushed to Bombay to meet PM Shastri, pressing for an immediate merger. The Prime Minister invited him to Delhi to discuss the matter threadbare while requesting him to defer the MGP decision to move a resolution on the merger in the Goa Assembly. On 3 November, in Bombay, Patil contradicted the PM, stating that he had made the statement in Goa based on a decision at a joint meeting he had with the PM and Congress President Kamraj before leaving for Goa. “But the referendum is my personal opinion,” he clarified.[^6]

Surprisingly, the UGP took five days to react to Patil’s proposal of a plebiscite. Rather than having a press conference on the issue, Dr Jack de Sequeira preferred to issue a short press note, terming the decision of a referendum practical and sensible. This decision will put an end to the number of interpretations that were attempted, he stated.[^7] Gomantak, in its editorial, called it UGP’s volte face from its original demand of Statehood for Goa.[^8] PSP leader, S M Joshi termed Patil’s announcement as a ‘bomb explosion’ on the eve of Diwali, which would have serious repercussions. The Kannadigas in Karnataka, on the other hand, welcomed Patil’s announcement.[^9]

Actually, Patil had echoed the opinion PM Nehru had expressed earlier at an AICC session held in Jaipur on 7 June 1963. When a group of Maharashtra politicians asked him how the wishes of the people of Goa would be determined, Nehru had told them: “It will be done through a referendum.”[^10]

Patil’s game, however, drew flak from his own party colleagues. The front pages of the newspapers of 4 November were seen with contradictory statements of Maharashtra’s Congress leaders on the issue of Goa. The day Patil spoke to the media, his colleagues Defence Minister Y B Chavan and Maharashtra CM Vasantrao Naik publicly appealed to the Congress leadership to rethink the Board decision and immediately merge Goa into Maharashtra. The Goa cabinet met in Goa on 6 November and sent a memorandum to the PM urging the merger, and also planning a series of mass protests.

The weeklong controversy was put to rest temporarily when the Congress President Kamraj assured a delegation of Maharashtra Congressmen that the Parliamentary Board would reconsider its decision.[^11]

CM Bandodkar then organised a massive pro-merger rally in the state capital of Panaji, following which the state government passed a private member’s resolution in Goa Assembly on 22 January 1965 demanding Goa’s merger into Maharashtra. The minority UGP walked out in protest. Following this, the Maharashtra Legislature passed an official resolution on 10 March 1965. Maharashtra CM Vasantrao Naik himself moved the resolution, and assured to grant special status to Goa and protect its identity, religion, culture, language, education, and social fabric. Not to be outdone, the Mysore Assembly passed a resolution on 12 March, condemning the Maharashtra Assembly resolution. It cited the pre-Portuguese rule of South Indian dynasties over Goa as well as Konkani-speaking settlers in Mysore, besides geographical, cultural, and linguistic aspects.[^12]

Under immense pressure, the Shastri cabinet decided to hold a mid-term assembly poll in Goa on the issue of merger. The Goa Congress strongly opposed this decision. Goa Congress President Purushottam Kakodkar, a leading freedom fighter, tried to convince the party leadership to reconsider the cabinet decision. He didn’t succeed. Then Kakodkar suddenly disappeared. It made national news. Suspicion was rife that he may have been eliminated by the pro-merger camp. Three months later, however, he reappeared, claiming that he had been meditating at the Sivananda Ashram in Rishikesh. Meanwhile, PM Shastri suddenly died in Tashkent, Uzbekistan (in the then Soviet Union) on 11 January 1966, a day after signing a peace treaty to end the 1965 Indo-Pakistan War.

The powerful ‘syndicate’ of K Kamaraj of Madras, Atulya Ghosh of West Bengal, Neelam Sanjiva Reddy of Andhra Pradesh, S Nijalingappa of Mysore and S K Patil of Maharashtra, which had elevated Shastri to the PM’s post after Nehru’s death, backed Indira Gandhi for prime ministership over Morarji Desai. Indira Gandhi took over as the Prime Minister in late January. A UGP delegation led by Dr Jack de Sequeira met Mrs Gandhi on 6 May 1966. Goa Congress chief Kakodkar met her, as well as Congress President K Kamaraj, on 21 June. Both pitched Nehru and Patil’s proposal for a referendum instead of a mid-term poll, but Mrs Gandhi declined to reverse the decision of the Shastri cabinet.

Kakodkar then played some astute politics. Though Deputy Prime Minister Morarji Desai also declined his request, he managed to get an assurance from Desai that he would not oppose an alternative, if it was proposed in the Parliamentary Board. S K Patil, now a powerful member of the ‘syndicate’, moved the vital resolution at the Congress Parliamentary Board meeting on 3 September 1966. Patil proposed that instead of a mid-term poll, a ‘different kind of mechanism’ be evolved to resolve Goa’s merger issue. Neither Morarji Desai, Indira Gandhi, nor Kamraj opposed it. The Congress didn’t want to call it a ‘referendum’ or a ‘plebiscite’ because of the Kashmir issue. Consequently, Union Home Secretary L K Singh proposed that it be called an ‘Opinion Poll’.

The UGP demanded that the MGP government resign so that the referendum could be conducted in a free-andfair atmosphere. Goa Chief Minister Bhausaheb Bandodkar gracefully resigned on 28 November 1966, paving the way for a level-playing field. President’s Rule was imposed on 3 December.

Who Is A Goan?

Holding a referendum was not an easy exercise for the Centre. The Constitution of India had no provision to hold a referendum or a plebiscite. It was happening for the first time in the Indian Republic. There were referendums held earlier, while Free India was getting created. But they were held to decide whether people wanted to join Free India, may it be in the North-West Frontier Province (NWFP, in Pakistan) held on 6 July 1947, in Sylhet (then in Assam and now in Bangladesh) held on 7 July 1947 or in Junagadh (in Saurashtra, Gujarat) held on 20 February 1948. Nehru had even proposed a similar referendum for Goa, Daman and Diu, on 4 February 1949, in the United Nations Organisation (UNO). But Portuguese Prime Minister Antonio de Oliveira Salazar rejected it. Much later in 1975, a plebiscite was held for Sikkim, on 14 April 1975 after Indian troops occupied the North Eastern state in April 1975.

In tune with the same spirit, the Goa, Daman & Diu Opinion Poll Bill, 1966 was introduced on 21 November and then was moved on 30 November 1966 in the Parliament. Interestingly, it was moved by Deputy Minister for Home Affairs Vidya Charan Shukla. Union Home Minister Yashwantrao Chavan, the strongest proponent for Goa’s merger, avoided tabling the Bill signed in his name. After lengthy debates in both the Houses − the Rajya Sabha and the Lok Sabha − the bill was passed on 1 December 1966.

The most interesting part of the debate was ‘Who is a Goan?’ The Maharashtrians, Kannadigas and other migrant Indians living in Goa as well? Or those lakhs of Goans who had to migrate to Bombay and other states during the Portuguese regime but had their homes in Goa? Acharya Kripalani hit out directly at North Goa MP Peter Alvares, asking if he was a Goan when he had always lived in Bombay. “Living in Bombay, if Peter Alvares can contest from Goa, why can’t a Goan living in Bombay vote in the Opinion Poll?” he asked. Alvares admitted that the definition of a Goan was difficult, but also asserted that Goans living outside Goa and settled in other parts of India should not be considered as voters.

Deputy Home Minister Shukla finally clarified that Goans living outside Goa, who could prove they were ordinarily residents of Goa, could enrol themselves as voters. No minimum residential period was required to prove that a person was an ordinary resident of Goa. The House however rejected a series of other amendments including giving the right to participate in the Poll to all those who had declared themselves as Goans under the Goa, Daman and Diu Citizenship Order 1962. This option was given to Goans when the Portuguese era came to an end.[13]

On the forefront to get outside Goans enrolled as voters was the UGP. Dr Jack de Sequeira left no stone unturned to achieve this demand, as most of the Goans working or settled outside were Christians, who were dead against merging Goa’s identity. The UGP led delegations to Delhi to meet the MPs of different parties while Goans opposing the merger formed organisations in Bombay to convince the ‘Bombay voters of Goa’. The party wanted not only Goans settled in different parts of India but also those settled abroad to be given voting rights. The UGP also wanted the facility of postal ballots for Goans working overseas, including the seamen.

However, during his three-day visit to Goa, Chief Election Commissioner K V K Sundaram ruled out voting rights for ‘original’ Goans who were permanently settled outside Goa. Since this statement created further confusion, next day in Bombay he clarified that such Goans would be allowed to vote if they convinced the registrar that they were temporarily staying outside but were ordinarily permanent residents of Goa. He rapped these Goans asking why they had not enrolled themselves in the 1963 election. He also rejected the demand for a postal ballot for the Goan seamen.[^14]

Finally, Goa had 60,321 new voters; some from outside, especially those working in Bombay. From 3,28,071 in the 1963 election, the electorate had swollen to 3,88,392, a rise of 16 per cent.

Mobilising The “Opinion”

The President gave his assent to the Goa, Daman and Diu (Opinion Poll) Act on 11 December 1966, and the Election Commission of India (EC) was authorised to hold the Opinion Poll based on the electoral roll prepared for the Lok Sabha elections scheduled in 1967. The EC allotted two symbols: a Flower to opt for merger with Maharashtra, and Two Leaves to retain Goa as a Union Territory. The Opinion Poll, free India’s first referendum, was scheduled on 16 January 1967.

But the wheels of the Opinion Poll had started moving in Goa much earlier; soon after the Congress Parliamentary Board had decided to recommend a ‘different kind of mechanism’ to solve the merger issue. For the 38 per cent Christian population of Goa, it was a matter of sheer survival. The Christians stood to lose their demographic status of a ‘major minority’ forever; they would be marginalised to a mere 2 per cent minority in a 4-crore strong Maharashtra, which had just six lakh Christians. Goa would be Maharashtra’s 28th district and, with its sevenlakh population, one of the smallest. Each of the 270 Assembly constituencies in Maharashtra comprised 60,000 to 1 lakh voters. Each Goa assembly constituency had just 10,000 to 15,000 voters. Goa would have got a maximum of four to five assembly constituencies in Maharashtra. For Christians, having even one constituency of their own would be a far-fetched dream. For Goan Christians, the Opinion Poll was a do-or-die fight to the finish.

But politics in Goa was not a straightforward Hindu-vs- Christian equation. Rather, it was the Hindu non-Brahmin Bahujan Samaj versus the rest; the Hindu peasantry versus the Hindu landlords, and the latter aligning with the minority Christians. Neither was it a linguistic battle as is being projected, that is, Konkani versus Marathi.

I had the opportunity to interview Uday Bhembre, one of the stalwarts of the Opinion Poll, for three-and-a-half hours on behalf of the Konkani Bhasha Mandal. He categorically stated: “The Opinion Poll was not fought on linguistic grounds. Konkani-Marathi was just one of the arguments. It was purely a political battle for Goa’s socio-political identity.” He also said that Rashtramat, the Marathi daily the anti-mergerists had launched to reach out to the Hindu Bahujan Samaj, had the Konkaniwadis as well as Marathiwadis, who were opposed to the merger.

As the voice of the free media was suppressed during the Portuguese regime, post-liberation Goa witnessed varied kinds of media organisations: newspapers, weeklies, and even fortnightlies in Romi and Devanagari Konkani, Marathi and English besides pre-liberation Portuguese newspapers. Within three years of Independence, Goa was publishing 26 newsrelated periodicals.[^15] That number had increased further when the Opinion Poll was held.

The mainstream news media consisted of mine owner Vishwasrao Chowgule’s Gomantak, founded on 24 March 1962; followed by Dempo’s The Navhind Times on 18 February 1963; and Novem Goem (1962), a fortnightly in Konkani written in the Devanagari script. Sot (1962) and Uzvadd (1963) were weeklies in Romi Konkani. Pradip and Gomant Vani were dailies in Marathi. The two Marathi newspapers campaigned for merger. The other publications opposed merger tooth-and-nail. But their circulation was very limited, except for Gomantak and The Navhind Times.

To reach out to the Hindu Bahujan Samaj, a group of young Konkani writers came together to start Rashtramat, a Marathi daily, in 1964. Their initial effort of ‘crowdfunding’ did not work and they approached the mine owners. Seven mine owners from the three families of Salgaocar, Timblo and Gosalia together funded the venture. Rashtramat’s mission was to counter the pro-merger propaganda of Goa’s then sole Marathi daily Gomantak, which was run by the Chowgules. Their target readership was the Hindu Bahujan Samaj. Winning the Opinion Poll with 38 per cent Christians and two per cent Hindu Brahmins was next to impossible when all the Christians, due to heavy migration, were not available for voting.

The experiment of Rashtramat not only worked but played wonders. It succeeded in countering the pro-merger propaganda of not only Goa’s Marathi newspapers but also the newspapers from Maharashtra like Pudhari (Kolhapur), Sakal (Pune), Maharashtra Times (Bombay) and Maratha, a daily edited by Prahlad Keshav aka ‘Acharya’ Atre, a firebrand orator and writer. Udaybab’s daily column Brahmastra in Rashtramat became a matter of discussion in most of the households, especially in the New Conquests and among the Hindu Bahujan Samaj. Udaybab recalls that Rashtramat changed its strategy when it realised that people were in a mood to weigh the issue ahead of the poll. Rather than outright attacks on the mergerist viewpoint, the newspaper began logically explaining the issue, putting forth arguments designed to convince sceptics. The main thrust of the public awareness campaigns was around small group meetings, public meetings, distributing printed material like handbills and displaying banners as well as holding cultural programmes. The fever of the Opinion Poll had gripped Goa’s villages and the towns soon after the official announcement.

Tense moments were witnessed practically every day, with groups on both sides disrupting meetings, blocking roads and sometimes even throwing eggs and stones at speakers. Police stations were flooded with complaints and counter-complaints. Women complained about sexually coloured remarks. How much was true and how much was just an attempt to defame the other side is hard to tell. People from both sides were arrested. There were also occasional serious incidents like beatings and stabbings.

The really interesting battle was on the cultural front. Maharashtra’s popular Lal Bavtta Kala Pathak led by Shahir Amar Shaikh, as well as Shahir Sable, enthralled crowds with inspiring patriotic Marathi songs like Jai Jai Maharashtra Mazha (Victory to my Maharashtra), to generate support for merger.

To counter them, a young brigade of singers, musicians and lyricists led by Ulhas Buyao entered the arena, styling themselves as the Jai Gomantak Kala Pathak. Their Konkani campaign songs like Goenchea Mhojea Goenkarano, Jayat Jage and Channeache Rati long outlived the movement to become popular folk songs that even today’s younger generation continues to enjoy. Interestingly, while the banners displayed at public meetings by both sides were always in Marathi in the New Conquests, all the speeches made by even the pro-merger Goan leaders, were almost always in Konkani.

Another unique campaign came up when the pro-merger camp brought the ‘padukas’ (sacred footwear) of the goddess Bhavani, a beloved Maratha icon, to Goa, in an attempt to polarise voters on religious lines. Shabu Desai, himself a proud Maratha and staunch MGP supporter from Cuncolim, rose up in rebellion against his own party. He marched across the length and breadth of Goa with a Sangh Pradesh Jyot (Union Territory Torch), along with an image of Goa’s own beloved deity, Shantadurga Kunkolikarin of Fatorpa. Hundreds of youth joined his march, and devout Goans welcomed the deity, especially in the Hindu-dominated New Conquests.

The Lobbies & The Groups

It was an established fact that the small and big landlord class was strongly against the merger because Maharashtra, among all the states, had the most revolutionary land reforms in the country. It had begun producing results with a co-operative movement, which unfortunately later became the powerful political and financial lobby of Sahakar Samrats. But there was another influential lobby that wholeheartedly supported the antimerger movement financially, that of the mine owners in Goa. The Portuguese regime had granted 893 mining concessions, and made them deemed owners of the iron ore mines.

Post-World War II, in its reconstruction phase, Japan began importing low-grade iron ore from Portuguese Goa. Goa’s first mining concession was granted in 1906, but the mining business actually started booming only in the last decade of Portuguese rule in Goa.

Soon after liberation, Goa’s iron ore mines were brought under the ambit of The Mines and Minerals (Development and Regulation) Act 1957, governed by the Government of India, to convert these concessions into leases. Since then, Goa’s mine ‘owners’ have been moving from the Bombay High Court to the Supreme Court to retain their ‘rights’. The court case is still pending before the Supreme Court.

When the Opinion Poll was announced, the obvious fear was that if Goa was merged into Maharashtra, the mines would be governed by the laws in Maharashtra and India, on par with mines of bigger states. Consequently, Goa’s mining lobby stood firmly behind the anti-merger movement, giving it full financial support. Rashtramat was one such venture of seven mine owners. However, there were also some passionate mine owners like V M Salgaocar, who was playing a pro-active role to retain Goa’s identity by taking Bhau head-on. My maternal uncle Ulhas Buyao told me that VM used to personally attend his musical shows held on open grounds and honour him with garlands of currency notes if he liked any particular song. On the other hand, Chowgule’s Gomantak was tilting more towards the merger.

In the campaign that Bandodkar led for the Flower, much of the publicity material as well as the speakers were ‘imported’ from Maharashtra. The Maharashtra Vilinikaran Samiti took the initiative to constitute an All-Party Goa Merger Committee consisting of the Congress, the Praja Samajwadi Party (PSP), the communist parties CPI and CPI(M), the Jan Sangh, the Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh (RSS), and even trade unions like the Congress-run INTUC and the Workers’ Union of India.

At Bandodkar’s request, 100 volunteers were sent from Maharashtra to campaign. But the most powerful orators like Acharya Atre, Jayantrao Tilak, Shirubhau Limaye, S M Joshi, etc., stayed away. Congress leader and Rajya Sabha MP Mohan Dharia coordinated the campaign from behind the scenes, while Socialist leaders like Barrister Nath Pai, the MP from Goa’s neighbouring Rajapur constituency, addressed public meetings.

The anti-merger camp worked on five different platforms, with hardly any coordination. The different groups seldom shared a platform, even though they had no significant political differences; if they came together at all, it was at the initiative of locals. All the groups came together in only one large antimerger rally that was held in Margao.

The Congress camp was not seen in public. Since the party was vertically divided over the issue in Maharashtra and Goa as well as at the Centre, party President K Kamaraj imposed a ban on public participation in the Opinion Poll campaign and told party members to ‘play neutral’. Congressmen in Goa worked only at the cadre level and campaigned secretively. No major Congress leader from Maharashtra came to Goa to campaign.

The United Goans Party held public meetings, but predominantly in the Christian belt. Its leader Dr Jack de Sequeira, however, moved all over Goa fearlessly and tirelessly, in spite of threats to his life from opponents. He is believed to have addressed 120 public meetings in 30 days. Not to be outdone, Dayanand Bandodkar addressed 133 meetings during the campaign.

UGP’s propaganda was centred around Goans losing their identity, language, and culture. The party’s modus operandi was to get each and every voter to the polling booth. The UGP did not spare any efforts to get the maximum number of people, especially Christians, onto the electoral roll.

The young Rashtramat brigade comprised young writers and thinkers in their 20s and 30s, not politicians. They concentrated their efforts in the Hindu-dominated New Conquest areas, facing all kinds of risks. Getting booed, stoned, and even beaten up was all in a day’s work. But the oratory and logical arguments of these Young Turks made people introspect and rethink their emotional attachment to becoming a part of Maharashtra.

The Teasers & The Arguments

There were quite a few interesting sidelights in the campaign. To run the private Marathi schools that came up during Portuguese rule, hundreds of teachers had been encouraged to come to Goa from Maharashtra, especially in the New Conquest areas. These gurujis were among the most respected people in their villages.

After liberation, they were all absorbed into government service under the central government pay scale. It provided them job security as well as a huge increase in their income. During the Portuguese era, they were paid by the villagers themselves; sometimes just a handful of rice from each peasant household, a traditional form of crowdfunding called mushtifund.

Salaries for teachers in Maharashtra were much lower than the central government scale. The teachers also wanted to protect themselves from possible transfers in a huge state like Maharashtra with an area of 3 lakh square kilometres; in comparison, Goa’s 3700 sq.km area seemed like a comfort zone. Consequently, teachers secretly campaigned house-tohouse in their localities, endorsing the anti-merger arguments raised by the Rashtramat group.

The major employer of educated youth from the villages, after liberation, was the Government of Goa, which paid the central government scale. The Maharashtra government’s pay scale was lower in comparison. This created a scare among the young educated white-collar neo-middle class from the Bahujan Samaj, who were often the most influential people in their localities.

Goans were also concerned about price rise. They were already somewhat upset over the taxation policy of the Centre in the liberated union territory. Under Portuguese rule, Goa had been a duty-free port. Taxes in Maharashtra were much higher than in the union territory.

Liquor was banned in Maharashtra which, unlike Goa, had Prohibition. This became a bone of contention. To counter the ‘scare’, Maharashtra chief minister Vasantrao Naik announced in the legislative Assembly that his government would not extend Prohibition to Goa.

To clear the confusion, the Bombay-based All-Party Goa Merger Committee and Goa’s pro-merger leaders formally met the Maharashtra Chief Minister, and requested him to make his government’s policy clear on the pay scales of government employees, on price rise as well as Prohibition. They also demanded a special position for Goa in its five-year development plan, and for representation in the state cabinet. However, no firm assurance, except on Prohibition, came from the Maharashtra CM.

The arguments were many. Besides the historical background of Maharashtra kings ruling Goa, it was argued that Marathi had deep roots in Goan society, from education and culture to literature and even religious rituals. The anti-merger stance was labelled a ‘Portuguese mentality’.

The anti-merger camp, especially Rashtramat, said the merger was an expansionist action by Maharashtra. They insisted that Goa had a distinct culture, unique from Maharashtra, and that Konkani was an independent language. Goans adopted Marathi for education only because Konkani was suppressed in Goa during Portuguese rule, while Marathi was able to flourish in neighbouring Maharashtra. To counter the ‘Portuguese mentality’ charge, they overtly exhibited an anti-Portuguese nationalist spirit with the help of freedom fighters who opposed the merger.

To cite a few creative arguments, people were asked:

“Do you want to get marginalised from 28 constituencies to a mere four?”

“Is it possible for your MLAs to become ministers in Maharashtra and take quick decisions for your welfare?”

“What do you prefer? Going all the way to Bombay to get your work done at the state headquarters or going to Panaji?”

“In Goa, the MGP has already implemented a ‘Land to the Tiller’ Act. Why do we need to be in Maharashtra to get our land rights?”

And the final masterstroke, which worked wonders: “Don’t you want ‘our’ Bhau (Bandodkar) to continue as chief minister? In Maharashtra, at the most, he would become a token ‘minority minister’.”

Three-Day-Long Football Match

Sunday 15 January 1967 witnessed the silence before the storm. Only the roar of the sea could be heard; no one knew which way the wind was blowing. The campaign had stopped at 5 pm on the previous day. It was the eve of a perfect storm. The ‘outside’ Goans landed in Goa, many of them on 16 January itself, by air, rail and the most popular and cheapest means of travel to Goa then, by ship. In fact, two ships arrived from Bombay, the Champavati and Konkan Sevak. Some Goans flew in from as far away as Delhi. A few even travelled from African countries like Kenya and Mozambique.

People lined up at all the 442 election booths much before polling started at 8 am. Many polling officers had to extend the deadline of 5 pm by two and even three hours. In villages without electricity, Petromax lanterns had to be brought in for the polling process to be completed. Not just old people, but even patients and those bedridden were carried to the booth to cast their votes.

There was an allegation that a large group of underage seminarians from the Rachol Seminary had voted. In fact, the 1951-born former Chief Minister of Goa Luizinho Faleiro once admitted publicly that he had cast a bogus vote – twice – in the Opinion Poll when he was just 15 years old.

The total turnout was 82 per cent. Altogether 3,17,633 people voted. Just two per cent of the votes were declared invalid. The enthusiasm of the voters was unprecedented. The subsequent Assembly election held just after a month, on 21 February 1967, recorded only a 68 per cent turnout, the thirdlowest in 13 Assembly elections till 2017.

VOTER TURNOUT (%): 1963 & OPINION POLL

Constituency | 1963 | OP | Difference | Constituency | 1963 | OP | Difference
Aldona | 76 | 97 | 20 | Cortalim | 73 | 87 | 14
Ponda | 73 | 96 | 23 | Shiroda | 62 | 85 | 23
Madkai | 76 | 95 | 20 | Tivim | 71 | 85 | 14
Panaji | 77 | 94 | 18 | Benaulim | 67 | 84 | 17
St. Cruz | 82 | 94 | 12 | Margao | 74 | 83 | 10
Mapusa | 76 | 93 | 17 | Pale | 74 | 83 | 10
St. Andre | 79 | 93 | 14 | Curchorem | 72 | 82 | 11
Calangute | 73 | 93 | 20 | Mandrem | 70 | 82 | 12
Siolim | 74 | 90 | 17 | Curtorim | 65 | 80 | 15
Bicholim | 78 | 89 | 12 | Sattari | 65 | 80 | 15
St. Estevam | 77 | 89 | 12 | Canacona | 72 | 79 | 8
Quepem | 73 | 88 | 15 | Pedne | 60 | 76 | 16
Cuncolim | 63 | 88 | 25 | Sanguem | 67 | 75 | 8
Navelim | 70 | 87 | 18 | Mormugao | 76 | 74 | -3

All across Goa people showed enthusiasm. Eleven constituencies recorded polling percentages of nearly 90 per cent or above. Aldona recorded the highest: 97 per cent. Not a single constituency recorded below 74 per cent. This was unprecedented compared to the previous Assembly election held three years ago or any other election held in Goa till date. In Mormugao, three per cent less voting than 1963 was recorded. But in terms of numbers, it was nearly double that of the previous election, because the number of voters had shot up in this port town from 11,000 to 21,000. Compared to 8624 polled in 1963, people who came out for Opinion Poll were 16,000. Obviously, the large turnout had increased the hopes of both the sides − merger and anti-merger.

The Goa government had declared a holiday for counting, which began on 17 January. But it continued till the morning of 19 January, much beyond the scheduled deadline; the afternoon of the 18th. The counting centre at the Institute Menezes Braganza in the heart of the state capital, Panaji, was surrounded by armed policemen, including central paramilitary forces.

At sharp 9 am started Goa’s most exciting ‘football match’. The local station of All India Radio (AIR) was continuously broadcasting a live commentary on the counting. Even then, hundreds of people gathered round this historic building to listen to the announcements of booth-wise results over the loudspeaker.

A graph displayed on a huge billboard showed the cumulative percentage of votes for the Flower and Two Leaves. It boosted and depressed the blood pressure of the public for three long days. It was like watching a gripping football match; a game which Goans dearly love.

The first day’s counting saw jubilation in the mergerist camp, as 11 constituencies from North Goa with 1,21,374 votes (31 per cent) were taken up for counting. It included five segments from the New Conquests and six from the Old Conquests, eight of which were MGP strongholds. These were Pernem, Mandrem, Siolim, Mapusa, Tivim, Bicholim, Pale, and Sattari. The UGP strongholds were Calangute, Aldona, and Panaji. At the end of the day, the Flower led by 10,579 votes. Though the pro-merger public was ecstatic, pro-merger politicians were disappointed. Two Leaves had got nearly 26 per cent of the votes in the MGP strongholds, which was not at all expected.

The election authorities could not complete counting the votes on the second day. Ballots in 13 more Assembly segments were counted. One again, eight among them were MGP strongholds: St Estevam, Madkai, Ponda, Shiroda, Sanguem,Canacona, Quepem, and Curchorem. The UGP The graph shows percentage of votes polled in the constituencies of MGP & UGP strongholds counted were only five: St Cruz, St Andre, Cuncolim, Benaulim, and Navelim. By end of the day, all the 16 MGP strongholds were counted against only eight UGP bastions. In spite of this, Two Leaves were leading by 7802. Even in the remaining eight MGP strongholds, Two Leaves garnered 23 per cent of the votes. In contrast, the Flower got barely 9 per cent of the votes in the five UGP strongholds. Counting stopped at 8.30 pm, leaving the jubilant Maharashtrawadi camp nervous.

Two major cities remained to be counted. First, the port town of Vasco, dominated by a mixed population of workers who had moved from the New Conquests and migrant workers from outside Goa. The second was the commercial city of Margao. It was considered to be the fortress of Hindu and Christian Brahmins, but it also had many small traders belonging to the Hindu Bahujan Samaj, known as the Bazarkar Mandalli. Two Christian-dominated constituencies of Curtorim and Cortalim, both within Salcete, a Christian majority taluka, were also yet to be counted.

Only Mormugao showed a vertical division of opinion; 49 per cent for merger and 51 per cent opposing it. It was a complete rout in the other three constituencies. Two Leaves bagged 93 per cent of the votes in Curtorim, 89 per cent in Cortalim, and 70 per cent in Margao. Its graph kept zooming up, increasing the lead to 34,000.

GOA: OPINION POLL VERDICT

Opinion (Symbol) | Votes | %
Anti-Merger (Two Leaves) | 172191 | 55.48
Merger (Flower) | 138170 | 45.52
Margin | 34021 | 9.96
Valid | 310361 | 79.91
Invalid | 7272 | 1.87
Polling | 317633 | 81.78
Voters | 388392 |

So certain was the victory for Two Leaves, that Chief Minister Dayanand Bandodkar did not even turn up at the counting centre on the third day. His party colleague Atchyutrao Usgaonkar has written that he found Bhau playing cricket with his grandchildren with a toy bat at home when he went to visit him soon after the result. Apparently, Bandodkar had predicted the result.[^16]

It was on 19 December 1961 that Goa was liberated from Portuguese rule. On 19 January 1967, it celebrated yet another liberation of sorts, with 55.48 per cent of Goa’s electorate rejecting the proposal to be part of a bigger state. Nearly half – 45.52 per cent – had voted for the merger. A little less than 10 per cent – 34,021 votes – had made the BIG difference.

Lions Retain Goa

Like any exciting football match, even in the Opinion Poll people still remember the constituencies of Curtorim (93%), Cortalim (89%), Margao (69%) and Mormugao (51%), the last four seats which were counted on the third day. This simply fired up the Identity graph. Many newspapers also made special mention of some constituencies in the Old Conquests, like Benaulim (94%) and Cuncolim (84%). Overall, it was a reverse trend. Unlike 16 seats won by the MGP in the 1963 Assembly election, the Two Leaves won 16 seats in the Opinion Poll. Four more from the MGP bastions: Curchorem, Quepem, Siolim, and Mapusa. The 16 versus 12 ratio of the 1963 election had turned to 12 versus 16 in the Opinion Poll!

But in reality, this was not enough to win the Opinion Poll. The huge amount of votes in the Old Conquests and especially the Christian-dominated UGP bastions was an expected trend. It was only one lakh out of the total 3.17 lakhs of votes polled. Hardly one-third. Because even in the 12 UGP seats, the Flower of Merger had polled nearly half of the votes: 49 per cent. It was not at all a one-sided affair. And certainly not enough to win the Opinion Poll.

OPINION POLL 1967: VOTES & MARGIN MGP STRONGHOLDS

No | Constituency | Polling | Flower | | Two Leaves | | Margin
| | | Votes | % | Votes | % | Votes
1 | Curchorem | 12281 | 5425 | 44 | 6856 | 56 | -1431
2 | Quepem | 7664 | 3447 | 45 | 4217 | 55 | -770
3 | Siolim | 11451 | 5583 | 49 | 5868 | 51 | -285
4 | Mapusa | 11748 | 5859 | 50 | 5889 | 50 | -30
5 | Sanguem | 9060 | 4560 | 50 | 4500 | 50 | 60
6 | Sattari | 9479 | 4974 | 52 | 4505 | 48 | 469
7 | Canacona | 10454 | 5832 | 56 | 4622 | 44 | 1210
8 | Shiroda | 10534 | 6369 | 60 | 4165 | 40 | 2204
9 | St. Estevam | 11537 | 6903 | 60 | 4634 | 40 | 2269
10 | Tivim | 9636 | 6110 | 63 | 3526 | 37 | 2584
11 | Pale | 9973 | 6305 | 63 | 3668 | 37 | 2637
12 | Pedne | 8271 | 5967 | 72 | 2304 | 28 | 3663
13 | Ponda | 11172 | 8082 | 72 | 3090 | 28 | 4992
14 | Mandrem | 12760 | 8993 | 70 | 3767 | 30 | 5226
15 | Bicholim | 9924 | 7741 | 78 | 2183 | 22 | 5558
16 | Marcaim | 10079 | 8408 | 83 | 1671 | 17 | 6737
TOTAL | | 166023 | 100558 | 61 | 65465 | 39 | 35093

OPINION POLL 1967: VOTES & MARGIN

UGP STRONGHOLDS

No | Constituency | Polling | Flower | | Two Leaves | | Margin |
| | | Votes | % | Votes | % | Votes |
1 | Curtorim | 13473 | 926 | 7 | 12547 | 93 | 11621 |
2 | Benaulim | 11398 | 629 | 6 | 10769 | 94 | 10140 |
3 | Cortalim | 11787 | 1376 | 12 | 10411 | 88 | 9035 |
4 | Cuncolim | 10854 | 1774 | 16 | 9080 | 84 | 7306 |
5 | Navelim | 13416 | 3061 | 23 | 10355 | 77 | 7294 |
6 | St. Cruz | 12920 | 4311 | 33 | 8609 | 67 | 4298 |
7 | Margao | 10398 | 3241 | 31 | 7157 | 69 | 3916 |
8 | St. Andre | 11520 | 3930 | 34 | 7590 | 66 | 3660 |
9 | Calangute | 13074 | 4928 | 38 | 8146 | 62 | 3218 |
10 | Aldona | 12309 | 4700 | 38 | 7609 | 62 | 2909 |
11 | Panaji | 10420 | 4175 | 40 | 6245 | 60 | 2070 |
12 | Mormugao | 15726 | 7654 | 49 | 8072 | 51 | 418 |
TOTAL | | 147295 | 40705 | 28 | 106590 | 72 | 65885 |

The surprise swing of votes in the New Conquests played the magic. The pro-merger camp never expected such a dramatic shift in votes. It was not Curchorem, Quepem, Siolim, and Mapusa alone where Two Leaves polled between 50 to 56 per cent votes. Even in Sanguem, the margin of Flower was hardly 60 votes. It was 50:50. The hard core Lions even in Sattari (48%), Canacona (44%) as well as Shiroda and St Estevam (40% each) preferred Two Leaves.

Yet another interesting phenomenon stunned the mergerists. In the 1963 Assembly election, the anti-merger UGP could not find candidates to field in Pernem, St Estevam, Madkai, and Shiroda. But in the Opinion Poll, these four constituencies fetched nearly 13,000 votes in favour of Two Leaves. It was 40 per cent in St Estevam and even 17 per cent in Madkai, where Bhau had polled a record 93 per cent votes in the bye-election. Compared to the 1963 Assembly poll, 11 out of 16 MGP strongholds went against Bhau and his agenda of merging Goan identity into Maharashtra. The only huge rise was in Ponda, 63 per cent more. Then it was St Estevam (25 per cent more), Sattari (24 more), Pernem (23 more) and Mandrem (mere 3 per cent more). Hard-core Lions in the rest of the 11 constituencies, mainly the Hindu Bahujan Samaj, tore the petals of the Flower into pieces.

And in the 12 UGP strongholds, the percentages of Two Leaves surpassed the UGP votes of 1963 everywhere. Cuncolim (39 per cent more), Curtorim (35 more) and Benaulim (27 per cent more) were at the forefront. This was a clear indication that the anti-merger trend was almost a state-wide phenomenon. It was neither Hindu-Christian, Old vs New Conquests, nor Hindu Brahmins versus Hindu Bahujan Samaj.

The Agony And The Ecstasy

It may have been with a slender margin of 10 per cent, but Goans had opted to retain their distinct identity. The promerger camp was fuming. To keep the situation under control, the Lt Governor imposed Section 144 CrPC throughout Goa for seven days. People celebrating the victory were lathi-charged and tear-gassed. Two truckloads of people were detained. Dayanand Bandodkar humbly accepted the people’s verdict. But he also told the press: “Today, we have lost the battle, but not the war. I am sure we will win the war. We lost because the pro-merger camp was not united.”

But he did not take the war ahead. In fact, in the newly constituted Assembly of 1967, the MGP supported the resolution urging the Centre to grant statehood for Goa. It was passed unanimously. But to actually gain statehood, Goa had to wait for two more decades. After Konkani was made Goa’s official language, the Congress government led by Rajiv Gandhi granted statehood to Goa on 30 May 1987.

The Opinion Poll proved Nehru’s contention that Goans were indeed Ajeeb. In the first Assembly election held in 1963, the Goans wiped out the Congress and elected the MGP, representing the Hindu Bahujan Samaj, with 16 seats. The UGP got 12 seats. In the 1967 Opinion Poll, Goans defeated the MGP’s cause of merger. This time, 16 constituencies voted against the merger, and only 12 for.

But when a fresh Assembly election was held three months later, on 28 March 1967, the same Goans voted MGP leader Bhausaheb Bandodkar back to power, once again with 16 seats. The ‘victorious’ UGP camp was split into two groups due to internal differences between Dr Sequeira and Dr Alvaro de Loyola Furtado. Dr Sequeira’s UGP was back, but once more as Leader of the Opposition, with only 12 seats. The Congress didn’t even contest.

Chief Minister once again, Bandodkar attended a felicitation function in Sangli a few months later. There, a local leader asked him at an informal get-together: “What made you lose the Opinion Poll when you are so popular?” The CM instantly replied with a smile: “Bhau (me) made me lose the Opinion Poll”. He explained how his opponents had exploited his personal popularity to create a false narrative and defeat the pro-merger point of view. Ajeeb logic of Bhau to justify the victory of independent-minded Goans in the Opinion Poll!

The Opinion Poll, the only plebiscite held in the country, is an object lesson in Indian democracy. It simply cannot be equated with an election to the Assembly or Lok Sabha, where parties or individual candidates matter. Opinion is different. To sort out vexed public issues, a properly conducted referendum is the only solution. The country needs to learn a lesson from Goa!

The Opinion Poll also set an electoral culture in Goa. It made people think and vote. Since then, the culture continues. By and large, they never vote blindly or by falling prey to the usual electoral tactics of caste, religion, money, or muscle power. People know that they can make the situation upside down if they think and vote. The only tragedy of Goa’s politics is that the thinking pattern has shifted from performance to delivery. It sometimes doesn’t matter if the candidate is a defector, smuggler, rapist, or highly corrupt, as long as he “delivers”. Perhaps educated Goan voters are thinking on the wrong lines

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्ति नंतरचा गोवा, पान 23
Governor’s Address to the Assembly, 13 January 1964
The Navhind Times, 21 October 1964
The Navhind Times, 1 November 1964
The Navhind Times, 1 November 1964
The Navhind Times, 3-4 November
The Navhind Times, 6 November 1964
गोमंतक, डॉ􀇛 सि कैरांची कोलांटउडी, 9 नोव्हेंबर 1964
गोमंतक, 2 व 6 नोव्हेंबर 1964
Narayan Rajan & D’Cuz Sharon; Triumph of Secularism: Battle of the Opinion Poll in Goa, P 15
The Navhind Times, 8-9 November 1964
राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्ति नंतरचा गोवा
The Navhind Times, 2 December 1966
The Navhind Times, 9 & 10 December 1966
गोमंतक; 14 जानेवारी 1964
उसगांवकर अच्युत; आमचे भाऊ (सहकाऱ्या च्या दृष्टि कोनातून भाऊसाहेब) पान 223

Chapter 3

HISTORY OF BHUMIPUTRAS

The history of Goa does not begin with the Portuguese conquest of Goa in 1510. Rather, it ends with the end of Portuguese colonisation, just 60 years ago.

The Portuguese conquered the first island of Goa in the 16th century. Vasco da Gama discovered India for the European traders. When he landed first on 20 May 1498 at Calicut, he was guided by an Arab pilot. India at that time was trading with Arabs, due to which the sea is called the Arabian Sea.

Neither does the history of Goa begin with Lord Parashuram, an incarnation of Lord Vishnu’s Dashavatara. The 'Sahyadri Khand', which tells us of his tale was added to the 'Skand Purana' later, probably to establish that Goa or Gomantak Bhumi was created by Lord Parashuram and that the Brahmins were the first settlers of Goa. One of the legends says that Parashuram, the warrior sage, stood on the peak of the Sahyadri Ghat and shot an arrow towards the sea. The water receded and the land rose from the sea. It was filled with salt and unsuitable for habitation; so Parashuram invoked the Snake King Vasuki, who spat holy poison and converted the soil into fertile lush green land. Out of respect, Vasuki and all snakes were appointed as protectors and guardians of the land.^1

The 'Sahyadri Khand' terms the Himalayas as Devatma (soul of the Gods) and Sahyadri as Viratma (soul of the heroes). The entire Sahyadri range does not touch the sea anywhere from River Tapi to Kanyakumari, because of Lord Parashuram’s heroic work. The Sapt Konkan, which Parashuram created from the North to the South includes Chiplun, Guhagar (now in the Konkan region of Maharashtra), Gomantak, Karahat, Karnat and Tuludesh. Parashuram then got Brahmins settled in Sapt Konkan, which included Bhargava, Nagare, Chitpavan, Karhade, Saraswat, Havik and Nambudri.^2

You may ask why this controversial issue is raised here as we discuss the elections and politics of Goa. It is not only important, rather the most important point, because the legend of Parashuram Bhoomi is directly connected to the land holdings of Goa, around which the politics of Goa has been moving right from ancient times till date. It is thus important to know who were the early settlers of Goa, to whom the land belonged to, how the Brahmins and a few Kshatriya Sardar classes became the Bhatkars (landlords) of Goa, and how the Bahujan politics evolved in Free Goa.

The Myth of Parashuram Bhoomi

This mythological legend is challenged by many historians. It primarily tries to say that the Gaud Saraswat Brahmins were the first settlers in Gomant Bhoomi due to which it is called Parashuram Bhoomi. The tale claims that Parashuram brought 96 Saraswat Brahmin families from Tirhut (probably in Gaur, Bengal, now in Bihar) in Northern India and got them settled in the most fertile region of the Konkan, that is Goa. Out of them, 66 families occupied the 66 villages of Sasastti (Salcete), and the remaining 30 families settled in the 30 villages of Tees-wadi (Tiswadi). Thereafter, these Brahmin families spread out into the neighbouring areas of Baradesh (of 12 villages - Bardez), Pedne, Kudal (Sawantwadi), and other parts of the Konkan.

While quoting several other historians, Gerard Pereira, an expert in history and political science, raises eyebrows over this myth:^3

“The legend of Parashurama’s reclamation of Goa and the subsequent settlement of the Saraswats therein, is questionable from both geographical and historical points of view. If the Gaud Saraswats were the first and early settlers in Goa, then how do we account for the existence of Dravidians, aboriginal Gavdas and Kunbis and other Aryan groups prior to their settlement? The legend itself would want us to believe that the mythical Parashurama annihilated the Kshatriyas not less than twentyone times before ‘creating’ new lands of Konkan. That would mean that the Konkan regions including Goa were inhabited by other people before the Gaud Saraswats came on the scene.”

Prof D D Kosambi, a renowned historian and a Goan by origin, argues that such a dense, trackless mountainous jungle infested by snakes and tigers, was fit only for hardy pioneers; the strong west-coast monsoon brings on a rapid growth of the forest, which no Brahmin settlers could possibly have cleared without a labour supply. The problem was solved in remarkable fashion, by sharing profit between the Brahmins to whom the land was given and the actual workers on the land recruited from the aboriginal Gaudas (still both caste and tribe), with a few Kunbi and other low caste peasants.

Pereira also quotes Dr Bhau Daji Lad, who states that

“it does not appear that the Gaud Saraswat Brahmins came to Goa prior to 1000 CE but some seven to eight centuries ago.”

The geologists, archaeologists, and historians have finally put this controversy to rest by explaining scientifically, how the entire Konkan coast got created. Anant Ramkrishna Sinai Dhume, a historian, in his acclaimed book The Cultural History of Goa: From 10,000 BC to 1352 AD, states:

“..the cultural history of Goa...; begins from the appearance of the land of Goa from the depths of the saline waters of the Arabian Sea, which occurred due to the seismic movement of Earth which took place at the end of the fourth pluvial period of the southern terrestrial globe in about 10,000 B.C. As a result of this seismic movement, a strip of the sea-bottom from the mouth of the Tapti river in the North to Kanyakumari in the South, along with the adjacent area of the Deccan trap closest to the sea, was elevated above the sea waters. This elevation resulted in the Sahyadri and Nilgiri ranges. The bottom of the sea rose near the trap-border about 600 m above the mean sea-level.”^4

Dhume substantiates this contention by quoting Dr Gerhard Oertel, a German citizen and professor of Geology at Pomona College, Claremont, California in the USA. Oertel headed a commission set up by the Portuguese government, consisting of mining engineers and geologists, to study the mineral occurrences and geology of the territory of Goa. He worked from December 1953 to September 1954 and even wrote a book on it, titled ‘Geologia de Goa’. However he could not visit the northern portion of Sattari and north-eastern part of Pernem, due to the liberation movement going on in this area.

Dhume also quotes Dr Darashaw Nosherwan Wadia (regarded as the Father of Indian Geology), zoologists EL Jordan and Dr PS Verma as well as several other experts to support his claim.

However, Dhume does believe that Parashuram was a historic figure, rather than a legendary or mythical figure. He dates him back to 2400 BCE, and not 10,000 BCE, when a conflict had taken place between the Haihayas (clans ruling in western and central India) and the Brahmins. “The origin of the legend of Parashurama is traced back to the aborigines who transmitted it to new-settlers,” he states.^5

Pereira, who was also an eminent Leftist trade union leader of Goa, concludes the whole controversy in this manner:

“From the above discussion, it can be stated that the Gaud Saraswat Brahmins are late-comers in Goa and their existence cannot be traced earlier than 1000 A.D. In the ‘Gada Parva’ of the Mahabharata, it is stated that Saraswat, a son of Rishi Dadichi, who lived on the banks of river Saraswati (probably Sarsuti near Thaneshwar in the Punjab), gave shelter and fed some sixty-thousand (Satsahastra) Aryan Brahmins; they came to him when there was a ravaging famine in Northern India for twelve years; they were fed on the fish diet obtained from the river Saraswati.

Subsequently, with the Aryan colonisation of Northern India, the Saraswat Brahmins spread themselves and settled in Siad, Rajputana, Bengal (Gaur) and other regions. And it is from Tirhut that the Brahmin Parashurama brought them to Goa. It may be inferred that they were named Saraswat after the river Saraswati and Gaud after their original abode at Tirhut in Gaur (Bengal).

The next immigration to Goa by these Saraswat Brahmins took place later on (in about the 10th century?) when they came from Kannauj. ‘Mangesh Mahatmaya’ relates that they were led by Devasarma, Lamasarma and Shivasarma on their way to Rameshwaram. They were so much attracted by the beauty of the place, on their halt at Goa, that they gave up the idea of proceeding further to their holy destination and settled at Kushasthali (modern Cortalim) and Keloshi (modern Quelossim). God Mangesh (Mangarisa) and Goddess Shanta Durga were brought by them and adored in the two villages. After the conquest of Goa by the Portuguese, God Mangesh and Goddess Shanta Durga were removed to a safer place in Ponda taluka where they still exist in two temples.”

Even today in the 21st century, has the situation changed? People from all over the world visit Goa as tourists, fall in love with the place and decide to settle down by either buying a small flat or a piece of land to build a palatial house. Precisely due to this, from that ancient time to now, land in Goa has become the most significant component of the Goan economy, around which the politics of Goa moves.

Who Were the First Settlers?

The question thus remains: Who were the first settlers of Goa, whom did the land belong to, and how did the feudal system evolve – with Bhatkar and Kull or Mundkar? How did the Gaunkari evolve into the land holdings by the Communidades? Only history can tell us the truth, provided we dig out the real truth and the real history. Not the ruler-centric history written by the rulers but by the ruled-centric, excavated by historians, sociologists, and researchers, based on ground realities. Gerard Pereira aptly says:^6

“History is not made by a few rulers and kings, nor should it mean just their so-called great feasts and achievements. History is made by the people − the Gavdas, Kunbis and the poor peasants who tilled the land and helped the advancement of the mode of production from the days of early mankind. The common people create history in the course of struggle for existence. Naturally, the clash continues permanently between the rulers and the ruled.”

The subsequent and consistent digging of history by the historians and archaeologists has gone back to 10,000 BCE when the first settlement was found in Goa, of hunter-gatherers. Scientific studies conducted by experts provide us with a detailed scenario :^7

“Until 1993 the existence of humans in Goa during the Paleolithic and Mesolithic period was highly debated. The discovery of rock art engravings on lateritic platforms and granite boulders from Usgalimal, on the banks of west-flowing river Kushavati River, has shed light on the prehistory of Goa. This site was discovered by Dr P P Shirodkar, then heading the Archaeology Department of Government of Goa. It was subsequently studied by the National Institute of Oceanography based in Goa. More than 125 forms were found scattered on the banks of river Kushavati in south-eastern Goa. For hundreds of years, the Kushavati rock art of Goa was known locally as ‘Gorava Rakhnyachi Chitram’, or pictures made by cowherds. After thorough study of these forms, scholars have concluded that these petroglyphs differ from those found elsewhere in Goa.

The rock shelter at Usgalimal has enough space for 25 to 30 people. The perennial stream in the vicinity which might have served Stone Age man for centuries as a source of water. Exploration of several Mesolithic sites of the Mandovi-Zuari basin, at other sites such as Keri, Thane, Anjuna, Mauxim, Kazur in Quepem, Virdi, has led to the discovery of several scrapers, points, bores, cones, etc. A hand axe has also been found at Usgalimal. Further unifacial choppers were recovered on a flat-based pebble of quartzite from a pebble conglomerate at Shigaon on the Dudhsagar River. Evidence of Palaeolithic cave existence can be seen at Dabolim, Adkon, Shigaon, Fatorpa, Arli, Maulinguinim, Diwar, Sanguem, Pilerne, Aquem-Madgao etc.

On the basis of recent DNA-based work on human migration, Dr. Nandkumar Kamat has ruled out the possibility of Kushavati shamans belonging to the first wave of humans to arrive in Goa. They were not negritoes or austrics. Most probably they were the earliest Mediterraneans who had descended the Western Ghats, probably in their search for sea salt on Goa’s coast. As the Kushavati transitioned into a Neolithic society, they began the domestication of animals and were in the last phase of using stone tools. The entire realm of shamanism underwent a radical transition. Today evidence of the metamorphosis in the masked dance drama ‘Perni Jagor’ can be seen in the same cultural region.”

No evidence however is found till date whether these hunter-gatherers finally settled down in Goa.

Mundari, Kol, Asura

According to Dhume, while the Konkan coast was created due to seismic movement 10000 BCE, the pluvial rains continued, though with diminishing intensity, for one thousand years:^8

“During this period mud and salt of marine origin continued to be de-salted and the process of cohesion started and continued slowly... By 9000 BC, the pluvial rains suddenly stopped and the climate became very hot and completely dry. Soon after came the high winds from the West to the East. The influence of these cyclones impacted some areas of the west coast from Britain to India, and even Iran and other countries of the terrestrial globe, except China. Due to these cyclones, trees were uprooted and large areas were inundated with hot silt and sand, sometimes remaíníng on basalt rock covered with the powder of basalt-schist, under pressure, and thus were fossilized in caverns.

With habitats disrupted by the sudden environmental impacts, people had to search for a safe shelter. The cyclones generally damaged the tops of mountains, but even low lying areas suffered with the deposits of hot silt and sand up to a great height. This situation probably continued for about 500 years in the west coast of India. And after the cessation of this calamity, and with regular seasonal rains, the surviving population continued their migration through the foot of mountains as well as by spreading out to the west up to the sea-shore. From around 5000 B.C. security among settlements in Goa was more or less assured.

During the period when man dwelled in caverns, there was scarcity of food and so there was increased mortality. Now the conditions changed. The population gradually increased and people wandered here and there in small groups in search of food and sweet water. Even these groups did not try to settle permanently. They were forced to frequently change their dwellings in search of edible roots, wild fruit and gram. The population grew, and as such new sites were selected for settlements. Simultaneously, by natural instinct especially among the women folk, they practised rudimentary agriculture, cultivating wild grain and fruit and preparing mud-vessels for storing the grain.

The people from North as well as the South came to occupy the new-born area starting from the western foot of the Sahyadri and Nilgiri ranges. The human folk which first established themselves in Goa are those that came from the foothills of the Sahyadri range. They were named by the newcomers (in the Mundari language) from North India as Mhars, meaning “of the eldest house” or say the most ancient settlers. The Mhars did not hunt because they had no implements. So their food was only that which was produced spontaneously. They ate flesh but only of the beasts already dead. Kills with stone were rare. They worshipped only the dead ancestors, believing in the existence of spirits.”

The next migration, according to Dhume, was in 4000 BCE, of a buffalo-rearing pastoral tribe from South India. They followed a matrilineal system. They had knowledge of domestication of animals and after centuries were eventually divided into two groups, the Naik caste and a second group of the matriarchal system consisting of Chedvans, Bhavins and Kalavants and their brothers.

By 3500 BCE there migrated another tribe called the Asura, from the northern area around Chota-Nagpur, a plateau of around 65,000 square kilometres in eastern India. It covers much of today’s Jharkhand state as well as adjacent parts of Bihar, Odisha, West Bengal, and Chhattisgarh. They started agriculture by the cut-and-burn method, locally known as the Kumeri system and produced cereals. The Kumeri system of shifting agriculture continues till date.

They were later subdued by the subsequent Kol tribe who dispossessed them of their land. For livelihood, they shifted to other professions like black-smiths, potters, and even landless labourers while some formed part of the Vani caste. The Bharvankar caste in the Christian community is of this stock.

The next migration Goa witnessed was in 3000 BCE (5000 years ago) of Kols, Mundaris, and Kharwas, from the same area as the Asuras. The Kols occupied the lands, cultivated paddyfields and organised a village-socio-economic administration, establishing a ‘Barazan’, that is a group generally formed of twelve hamlets of villages. Their main goddess was Roinn, the anthill, which was later named as Santer. They were later called Santerkar, which then got renamed as Satarkar. Being primarily a Kullwadi caste, Dhume divides Satarkars into two categories: (1) Satarkars of Ponda taluka and Rivona village in Sanguem (a small settlement is also found in Loliem village of Canacona - Author) and (2) Satarkar, a lower Maratha caste in Sanguem, Sattari, Bicholim, and Pernem talukas.

The Mundaris, who probably came after the Kols, worked under their hegemony. They had no special cultural features, except for the worship of a forest-tree named Kel. The Munda tribe enjoyed the highest status among all the tribes such as Kols, Hos (Larka Kols), Santals, Bhumija, Korwars, Juang, Birhor, Asuras and so on. The word Mundkar, meaning ‘protector’ of property, is derived from this Mundari word.

According to Dhume, the Gavddo tribe belongs to two different settlements. One belongs to the Asur-Munda tribe, which came from Chota Nagpur. The Satarkars, originally from Advai village of Sattari, shifted to Savoi-Verem (for reasons not known), defeated the Gavdde there and established their settlement. These Gavdde must have then settled elsewhere in Goa.

The second tribe migrated along with the Goud Saraswat Brahmins from Kannauj (Uttar Pradesh) and established themselves at Kutthali (Cortalim). They are called Kelshi- Kutthalkar Gaudde. They are believed to have developed the Khazan lands in Madkai, across the Zuari river.

According to Dhume, Kullambi is originally not a caste or tribe, but the cultivating class. It represents the professional status of different ethnic groups of lower status in Goan society whose main means of substance was agriculture. Who are these Kullambis? The Christian Gaudde from Salcete, the Christian Bharvankar Gaudde from Salcete and Quepem, the Velips and Gaonkars of Sanguem and Canacona as well as Konkani Kunbis who migrated to North Canara. All these settlements have their Mhal leader, who is called Gaonkar.

The Kharwis came probably along with the Mundaris, but there is no proof for their independent settlement in village form. They took to the profession of fishing and boating and formed the present Kharvi (fishermen) community.

Aryans, the Latecomers

The advent of the Aryans began around 2400 BCE, almost six to seven centuries after the first settlement arrived in Goa in 9000 BCE. It was the end of the Rigvedic age and the Aryans from the Indus valley were highly influenced by it. The Indus Valley civilisation was the most widespread, its sites spanning an area stretching from today’s northeast Afghanistan (Gandhar), through much of Pakistan (most of the Sindhu Pradesh), and into western and north-western India. The tale of Parashuram is connected with the first phase of migration of Goud Saraswat Brahmins − Bhargavas and Angiras, especially in Salcete, Tiswadi, and Bardez talukas.

They lived in a joint family and the patriarch had full powers over the members of the family. He was almost like a king. His jurisdiction expanded as the joint family expanded into a large federation of several natural families springing from a common ancestor, living in the same village. This system is found to be prevalent among all the Indo-European communities, which establishes the fact of where the first wave of Aryans came from.^9

They were not nomads. They lived a settled life and built cottages of wood and thatch for their dwellings. Milk and its products were the most important part of their food, besides cakes of rice or barley, porridge, as well as meats of goats and sheep which were sacrificed. The cow was considered to be sacred and could not be killed. They did not interfere with the life, religion, customs, festivities, or even the Barazan system of the earlier settlers. But they obviously held sway over the others because of their superiority in attack and defence strategies. They knew how to make swords, helmets, hand-guards, armour, etc. of steel.

This immigration from the North continued. References of more migrations of Havig Brahmins are found during the Kadamba regime in the fourth to sixth century and Madhvacharya’s sect in the 13th century.^10 Later, during religious conversions by the Portuguese, these Brahmins also migrated outside Goa, especially to Karnataka and Kerala.

The second wave of Aryan migration occurred around 700 CE when the entire bed of the Saraswati river of a length of about 1500 kilometres supposedly disappeared and the people along its banks suffered a severe drought. This led to the migration of Aryans as well as non-Aryans to various parts of India.

Since the river Saraswati is mentioned only in the Rigveda, experts have been debating over its exact location. It is believed that the river originated in the high Himalayas and descended to the plains in Haryana, Punjab, adjoining parts of Pakistan and joined the Arabian sea at Rann of Kutch in Gujarat. Some geologists claim that the Saraswati could have been a major all-season river in the Indus-Yamuna interfluve. Claims are also made that it has remained as the Ghaggar-Hakra intermittent river between India and Pakistan, which flows only in the monsoons and ends at the Thar desert. There are also counter-claims made that the river never existed and that all this is just myth.^11

India’s eminent historian Romila Thapar does not dispute that the Saraswati river existed, but refuses to buy the argument that it is the Ghaggar:

“The identification of the Ghaggar with the Sarasvati, mentioned in the Rig-Veda, is controversial. Furthermore, the early references to Sarasvati could be to the Haraxvati Plain in Afghanistan… This has led to the theory that originally the Old Iranian and Indo-Aryan speakers were a single group but dissensions led to their splitting up. It was then that the Indo- Aryan speakers living in the Indo-Iranian borderlands and the Haraxvati (Sarasvati) area of Afghanistan gradually migrated to the Indus plain, bringing with them their language, rituals and social customs, to settle as agro-pastoralists in the Sapta- Sindhu.”^12

The second wave of Aryans in Goa consisted of Saraswat Brahmins, Kshatriyas, Vaishyas, and even Gaudde. The Saraswat Brahmins were from Kosala in Chattisgarh as well as from Chedi. The Bhoja Kshatriyas were from Ujjain and Chediyas from the Chedi kingdom, from Bundelkhand, both from Madhya Pradesh. Besides Vaishyas, the families also consisted of artisans and of non-Aryan stock from Goud, known in Goa as Gaudde. They came by the road route, from Mathura and Ujjain, and then to the South by western coast to Laat in Gujarat to Goa. Some Saraswat Brahmins, who had taken up trade in Laat in Gujarat, came by sea later in 700 CE and joined them in Goa to settle down.^13

“The Kshatriya-Bhojas and Chediyas, named together as Chaddes, expelled the Satarkars who fled to the south up to the village of Rivona in Sanguem taluka and occupied the villages and established their headquarters at Amonem village. They however kept the Mundari tribe as well as other families of the original pastoral tribe in their service. They established the system of kingship under the hegemony of the Bhojas, which is the first kingship to appear in the area of Goa in about 600 B.C. However, the village administration system of adjacent Salcete taluka was adopted with slight modifications. In the beginning of the occupation the three main clans held common ownership of the land and cooperative farming was practiced, the net income being equally distributed among those three sub-groups. But later on, the lands were distributed among those three memberclans, while the forest and pasture lands, village wise, were kept under common ownership.

The areas of Kudal and later on of Pedne and Bardez talukas were occupied by the families of the second wave of Aryans consisting of Saraswats, who had arrived there by the land route. They continued with the system of private ownership of the lands. Later, around the beginning of the Christian Era, the people from Deccan Plateau appeared and settled there and entered the local administration. However, there is no clear evidence as to whether these people gained hegemony or equal status as compared to the Brahmins who had settled earlier.

In Sattari taluka, the people from the Deccan Plateau came from the Western Ghats, about the beginning of the Christian Era. They entered through Rivem village, attacked the Satarkars who had occupied that area and expelled them… The expansion of these people continued in the Hemadbarcem division of Sanguem taluka (now in Dharbandora taluka) and in a part of Bicholim (Dichol) taluka. As occupation progressed, the ruler brought families of his matrimonial relations from their original home and established headquarters at Surla of Sanguem and Kudnem of Bicholim (Dichol) talukas.”

Game-Changer Iraqi Sumerians

In between the first and second migration of Aryans, there was a significant migration around 2000 BCE from Sumer, which is today part of Iraq. Why were the Sumerians so significant? It is because the world’s first civilisation had been created in Mesopotamia under the Sumerian leadership. They were a highly knowledgeable tribe among those who had settled in Goa in terms of weapons, housing, cuisine, and all other facets of community living. They were into trade with Egypt and India, including Goa, of gold, cedar, and copper. They knew about the location as well as the environment and facilities for settlement in Goa. Through the Persian Gulf, the sea route took them about three years to reach Goa.

Though proficient in agricultural activity, a famine hit them very badly, which compelled them to migrate. History says that about 2,000 B.C, “the civilisation of Sumer had been kindled there, sparks had leapt to Egypt and India.” Anant Sinai Dhume is perhaps the first person who proved this migration with various kinds of evidence that indicate Sumerian settlement in those cities.

Who were these Sumerians settled in Goa almost 4000 years ago? Mainly the Padhye Brahmins, and also quite a few of the smith class:^14

“All the people who migrated from Sumer could not have sheltered in Goa, so that people travelled to the south of Goa by the sea-route. It appears that the families of the highest class, Paddyas, settled in Goa and persistently maintained their customs whereas the families of other classes, mainly artisans and craftsmen and perhaps some families of the highest caste travelled to the south (India) where they might have amalgamated their customs with those of the original settlers of these areas.”

But then where did the name Paddya or Padhye originate from? Dhume links it to one of the Sumerian kings, whose name was A-an-ni-pad-da. Being from the highest class among all, they called themselves Paddye. “And similarly, with slight deviation, the families of lower class named themselves ‘Fatto’ and another family as ‘Maddo’. This last family settled in the area now known as Marcaim (Madkai) which is probably a version of Maddaki, as the word ‘ki’ means land in the Sumerian language.” They came from the city of Ur, situated on the shores of Persian Gulf, from which Dhume feels the name of a village in Ponda taluka − Orgao − could have been derived.

Their first settlements were in three talukas − Ponda, Bardez, and Salcete. Even today the highest number of Padhye Brahmins are found in Ponda taluka. In Bardez, they settled in Serula and Betim-Verem and in Varca village of Salcete taluka.

The migration of the Sumerians brought changes in the thinking process of even the first wave of Aryans, who began to follow their customs. Their culture is deeply rooted in Goa today, perhaps because it was a dominant ruler-priest class. They brought the concept of a permanent structure for God − a temple − in Goa. As in the Sumerian system, in the sanctum (garbh kood) of a temple, only the Bhat and the Mahajans, who founded the temple, are allowed. The institution of Devadasi system (dancing girls, temple servants, etc.) was also brought to Goa by the Sumerians.

The most interesting elements are that of agriculture and land management. The Padhyes introduced a special type of ploughshare made of iron, and were skilled in reclaiming river land, constructing dykes, and using land for cultivation. They were pioneers in shaping the early methods of cultivation, with irrigation management and modern ploughing tools. Even today, the Padhye Brahmins are considered to be the most progressive farmers in Goa. They are also the real models for the co-operative management of the agricultural economy, by adapting the Gaunkari system to the changing modern times. The classic example of this is the Goa Bagayatdar Sahakari Kharedi- Vikri Sanstha. From buying and selling agricultural products at the optimum price and providing all the agricultural tools, implements as well as fertilisers and pesticides, the Bagayatdar today runs Goa’s best supermarkets for the Goan consumer at a minimum possible price.

It was a tribal concept that land belonged to the whole community and its deity. Land belonging to the king was an Aryan concept. And land belonging to the village god or goddess was a Sumerian concept. The early settlers of Goa, the tribals, developed a Gaunkari system for the management of cultivable land. They cultivated collectively but appropriated the cultivated produce individually. Administration of the whole village was also run by the assembly of elders. The Sumerians (or the Padhye Brahmins), to a large extent, transferred this authority to the local temple and its managers. They introduced the concept of collective farming, through this authority, with all the obligations of maintenance and repairs of dykes and irrigation systems placed upon the cultivators. The templepalace played a crucial role in mediating the relationships and disputes between farmers, herdsmen, fishermen, craftspecialists, and the State.

The Sumerians built temples in Goa. Houses were typically built with an entrance room, an open courtyard, verandah, passages from one room to the other rooms, kitchen, etc. They also devised the irrigation system, dug up canals, and maintained them to prevent silting. A lot of labour was engaged in all these activities. Perhaps this was the first major construction activity that had taken place in Goa. And for this, the construction labour was imported. This labour class also settled in Goa and became Goans − our ancestors!

The Padhye Brahmins are quite different from the Saraswat Brahmins in terms of the agricultural relations they maintain with the farmers, tenants, and even the landless agricultural labour. They personally work in the fields and hold dignity of labour in their social approach. Also, the Gauda and Kunbi-Velip communities have immense respect for the Padhye Brahmins as compared to the Saraswat Brahmins with ‘bhatkar’ mentality.

Perhaps this is the reason Sudin Dhavalikar is unbeatable in Madkai, which has a sizable vote bank of Gawda community. His brother Deepak also rides this ancestral legacy in the tribal dominated Priol constituency. This could be the reason why the Bhahujan Samaj feels quite comfortable when he heads a party like the MGP.

Ajit Painginkar, a veteran journalist from Canacona and a researcher of folk art, tells me that the Kunbi-Velip community even in his taluka is found to be more connected with the Padhey Brahmins than the other communities. Both the communities, even three decades ago, had lots of similarities in terms of the hard work they put in, their involvement in agriculture, their lifestyle and even the attire including the chenchi (a pouch with a string to sling it around the shoulder) of paan-tambakhu (tobacco paan). Both the communities are also staunch temple devotees.

While both these communities developed the Gaunkari system of community farming together, they imported the construction labour from other parts of the country, who are now settled in Goa. It is a similar situation to what we witness in Goa today where the labour class is imported from other parts of the country and they too are slowly settling down in Goa. The cultural confrontation between the insiders and outsiders remains for one or two generations after which they also become Niz Goenkar, like how our ancestors became and started calling ourselves “Original Goans”.

Goans were confronted with a major controversy when the BJP government, in 2021, introduced a Bhumiputra bill. The debate led to who is the Bhumiputra and who is an outsider migrant. From the ancient history before any dynasty started ruling Goa, can we define who is a Bhumiputra and who is an outsider? Is migration a modern phenomenon? Or is the history of Goa full of migrations, from all over the world as well as different parts of India? What are we originally? Iraqis? Afghanis? Pakistani? Indo-Europeans? Aryans? Dravidians? Bengalis? Odiyas? Jharkhandi? Bihari? Madhya Pradeshi? Chattisgarhi? Gujarati? Mundaris? Kol? Sumerians? Arabs?

If we analyse this history, we find that different tribes came down and settled in Goa in different centuries. And here Goa’s politics has started moving around a migration, which is not even one century old. 1961 to 2021 is the tail end of the 20th century and the early beginning of the 21st century. The history of barely 60 years!

Wikipedia: Parshurama↩︎

गायतोंडे व्याकरणाचार्य गजानन शास्त्री: सह्याद्री खंड↩︎

Pereira Gerard A: An outline of pre-Portuguese History of Goa↩︎

Sinai Dhume Anant R: The Cultural History of Goa, From 10000 BC - 12352 AD. P 334↩︎

ibid P 26↩︎

Pereira Gerald A: An Outline of Pre-Portuguese History of Goa↩︎

Wikipedia: History of Goa↩︎

Sinai Dhume Anant R: The Cultural History of Goa, From 10000 BC - 12352 AD. P 334-336↩︎

Sinai Dhume Anant R: The Cultural History of Goa, From 10000 BC - 12352 AD. P 173↩︎

Ibid P 179↩︎

Wikipedia: Ghaggar-Hakra river↩︎

Thapar Romila: The Penguin History of Early India: From the Origins to AD 1300↩︎

Sinai Dhume Anant R: The Cultural History of Goa, From 10000 BC - 12352 AD. P 178-179↩︎

Sinai Dhume Anant R: The Cultural History of Goa, From 10000 BC - 12352 AD. P 116-167↩︎

Chapter 6

The 'State' of Migrants

Unlike the rest of India, Goa is a state formed by four kinds of major migrations. Two among them are similar to the rest of India while the other two are unique. To analyse local politics, knowing the history of migrations is of utmost importance. We have already analysed two migrations that took place in Goa. One, from the early settlers to the settlements followed by the different dynasties and the role they played in shaping up Goa’s polity. The second one is unique to Goa, caused by Portuguese colonialism and the religious conversions of Hindus and Muslims as well as the horrific Inquisition inflicted upon the converted Goan Christians. This saga resulted in a series of migrations, first by the Hindus in the 16th and 17th centuries and then by the neoconverts, especially in the 17th century.

Then came a major spate of migration of Goans, which gained momentum from the 19th century. The decaying economic situation in Goa, in the Estado da India, and the opportunities thrown up all over the world led to the migration of many aspiring people from the Christian community of Goa. This migration still continues. In the last three decades Goa’s educated Hindu population has also been migrating in a big way, due to lack of opportunities in their home State.

On the other hand, Goa has also been witnessing inward migration from all over India after liberation in 1961. One, largely by the labour class and lower middle class, to seize the employment and professional opportunities which the locals shy away from. And the second migration is by the ‘cream’ of India’s elite society, which is buying land at throwaway prices and settling down in Goa. Having a holiday home in Goa has become a big craze among the wealthy class of India and also among the foreigners.

To understand Goa’s politics, it is necessary to travel down history and perceive the mindset of Goan voters, who consist of those who had migrated to Goa centuries ago, the new migrant population of this century, as well as the Goans who out-migrate to work but remain strongly connected with the concerns and welfare of their motherland.

More Christians Than Hindus Left Goa?

We know that Goa was historically divided into two Goas − the Velhas Conquistas (Old Conquests) and Nova Conquistas (New Conquests). By 1788, when the eight talukas of the latter were annexed to Goa, the Portuguese had changed their policy on religious conversions. They had agreed to respect the traditions and customs of their population. The Inquisition, though finally abolished in 1812, had lost its teeth when it was suspended in 1774 and revived four years later.

The Christians found in the New Conquests today are the migrants from the Old Conquests, they are not local converts.^1 Having been ill-treated by the Portuguese regime as inferior citizens, especially those from the Sudir caste, they shifted to the New Conquests as landless agricultural labourers, toddy tappers, and fishermen. They could buy their own land and build houses only when they started working overseas on hard labour jobs as seamen, as well as in the Gulf, and now in the UK.

But it is not true that Christians were always a minority in Goa. Even after the New Conquests were annexed to Estado da India, the Christians were the majority. The official figures of the Portuguese Census indicate that way back in 1850, Christians comprised 64 per cent of Goa’s population. Out of a total of 3.64 lakh population, Christians were 2.32 lakh and Hindus 1.29 lakh; a difference of over one lakh. But by the end of the century, the situation had changed drastically. It had come down to 50:50. The major proportionate drop was in the first three decades, till 1881. The Christian population did rise, but by only 10,000 (2.41 lakh). The Hindu population on the other hand rose by one lakh (2.30 lakh). And by 1910, Hindus (2.70 lakh) were equal to the Christian (2.68 lakh) population. Subsequently, not only in terms of percentage, but even in terms of number, the Christian population kept on declining till Goa was liberated in 1961. From 1850 to 1960, the whole picture had reversed. Hindus (3.54 lakh) were one lakh more than the Christians (2.25 lakh).

Note : Other religions like Buddhists etc are included in the category of Muslims Source : Portuguese Census of Estado da India, An Historical and Archaeological Sketch of City of Goa & Census of India

Was it a state-wide transition? It was, but to a large extent in the Old Conquests. Let’s analyse the following graph, which shows the percentage of religions in 1848, 1961 and 2011.

In the Old Conquests, the Christian population has declined substantially, from 88 per cent to 35 per cent. Comparatively, it has declined marginally from 15 to 11 per cent in the New Conquests over one and a half centuries. In contrast, the decline and rise of Hindus in the Old and New Conquests appears quite reasonable up to 1961.

A further break-up of the population in the talukas of both the conquests clearly indicates that the major decline in the Christian population happened in the Bardez taluka. There was a huge drop by 60 per cent in 163 years, till 2011. The Christian population in Tiswadi dropped to half (50 per cent), followed by Salcete, where Christians reduced by 40 per cent. No talukawise break-up of 1848 is available for the New Conquests. But the Christian population also dropped there by 31 per cent from Liberation to 2011.

Population numbers always keep increasing in society even if family planning is practiced vigorously. However, the percentage either drops or rises due to two reasons. Here in this case it was outward migration (emigration) of Christians from Goa and inward migration of Hindus from outside Goa. Obviously, there was no reason for the Hindus to migrate to Goa till it was liberated. But the prime reason for the decline of Christian population appears to be emigration.

POPULATION SHIFT TALUKA-WISE: 1848-2011

TALUKA | HINDU | | | CHRISTIAN | | | MUSLIM | |
| 1848 | 1961 | 2011 | 1848 | 1961 | 2011 | 1848 | 1961 | 2011
| | | | | | | | |
Bardez | 14 | 58 | 67 | 86 | 42 | 26 | 0 | 1 | 7
Tiswadi | 22 | 52 | 62 | 78 | 46 | 28 | 0.2 | 2 | 9
Mormugao | | 41 | 65 | | 53 | 22 | | 5 | 13
Salcete | 6 | 22 | 35 | 94 | 75 | 54 | 0.1 | 3 | 11
OLD CONQUESTS | 12 | 42 | 55 | 88 | 56 | 35 | 0.1 | 2 | 10
Pernem | | 87 | 89 | | 12 | 10 | | 0.41 | 1
Bicholim | | 92 | 91 | | 6 | 2 | | 2 | 7
Sattari | | 93 | 91 | | 2 | 1 | | 5 | 8
Ponda | | 89 | 84 | | 10 | 8 | | 1 | 8
Quepem | | 61 | 64 | | 38 | 29 | | 1 | 7
Sanguem | | 74 | 79 | | 24 | 14 | | 2 | 7
Canacona | | 76 | 80 | | 24 | 18 | | 0.48 | 2
NEW CONQUESTS | 84 | 83 | 83 | 15 | 15 | 11 | 1 | 2 | 6
TOTAL | 36 | 60 | 66 | 64 | 38 | 25 | 0.4 | 2 | 8

Source: Portuguese Census of Estado da India, An Historical and Archaeological Sketch of City of Goa & Census of India

It means that not only did the Hindus migrate to settle outside Goa during the Portuguese regime but the Christians did so too. It began during the Inquisition, perhaps in large numbers in the 17th century, when the neo-converts could not bear the forceful de-culturalisation and migrated to the Konkan belt in Maharashtra and Belgaum as well as to North Canara in Karnataka.

The second major emigration is recorded at the end of the 17th century, when Chatrapati Sambhaji of the Maratha empire had almost captured Goa in 1683 and the Portuguese Governor had actually pleaded for divine intervention by placing his sceptre on the relics of St Francis Xavier at Old Goa.

Goa’s history would have been different if the Mughals had not invaded the Maratha territories at that point of time, due to which Sambhaji had to retreat from Goa. However, after this episode, by the beginning of the 18th century, native Christians had started migrating to Karnataka. Almost 40,000 Christians are reported to have been settled across the Portuguese borders, returning annually only to collect their zonn (dividend) from their respective Communidades.^2

Goans began working for the British when the naval fleet of the British Indian government was stationed in Goa between 1797 and 1813, in anticipation of an attack by the French (which never took place). They employed Goan Christians due to their familiarity with Western culture. When the British fleet withdrew from Goa and established stations in Bombay, Karachi, Madras, Calcutta and Singapore their Goan staff followed them. Later, after the War of Independence in 1857, the British began setting up a vast railway network for the quick movement of troops, including in Goa. The Goans poured out and got jobs in the railway-related works and subsequently settled in large numbers in Hubli, Belgaum, Mumbai, and Pune.^3

Then occurred a major exodus, largely of Christians, when the Anglo-Portuguese Treaty was signed in 1878 and Goa became the prime supplier of labour to British India. Official figures from Portuguese records show that 3.23 lakh Goans had left Estado da India (Portuguese Goa) and settled in Bombay as the citizens of British India, in just 30 years, from 1880 to 1910. Ninety-two per cent among them were from the Old Conquests. Obviously, the majority of them were Christians. Besides Bombay, some of them also settled in Madras and Bengal.^4

“Goa’s rural scene became increasingly more desolate. When the first Goan Provincial Congress met in 1951, one participant presented statistics of unemployment: 5000 jobless, 1500 beggars, 1,50,000 idle bodies…the Second Provincial Congress in 1971 paid more attention to the problems of emigration; it concluded that the horrendous exodus was a pathological phenomenon for which the Portuguese colonial administration ought to accept responsibility. Those who stayed behind could find relief in the ever-growing number of taverns. The Seventh Provincial Congress in 1927 regretted the government’s manifest lack of concern in controlling this vice. Obviously, the licensing of more taverns brought more income to a revenue-starved administration.”^5

There have been two separate studies conducted to estimate the exodus of Goans during this period till 1910, when the Portuguese monarchy was replaced by the Republic. The first one was conducted by two researchers from Portugal and the Netherlands: Paulo Teodoro de Matos of the Instituto Universitário de Lisboa in Lisboa and Jan Lucassen of the International Institute of Social History in Amsterdam. Of the total number of 37,345 passports granted between 1847 and 1855 by Estado da India from Goa, they selected 2,042 passports, corresponding to a sample of 5.5% (constant for each year).

They found that almost all the applicants (96%) went to Bombay. Most of the migrants were from the Old Conquests, largely from Bardez (67%), and nearly 90 per cent of them were Christians. Only 6 Christians from 1787 (a sample) were from the New Conquests. The rest of the 55 were Hindus from the New Conquests. Comparatively, hardly seven per cent of Hindus migrated from the Old Conquests.

Passengers’ Religion Taluka-Wise (5% Sample) 1847-1855

RELIGION | BARDEZ | TISWADI | SALCETE | OLD CONQUEST | NEW CONQUEST | TOTAL
Christians | 1141 | 116 | 337 | 1594 | 6 | 1600
Hindus | 47 | 69 | 8 | 124 | 55 | 179
Muslims | 0 | 6 | 0 | 6 | 0 | 6
No Info | 2 | 0 | 0 | 2 | 0 | 2
Total | 1190 | 191 | 345 | 1726 | 61 | 1787

Source: Goa at work around 1850…. By Paulo Teodoro de Matos & Jon Lucassen

The second study recorded by Dr Remy Dias shows the real magnitude of the exodus over three decades, from 1880 to 1910. Over 3.23 lakh Goans left Goa, mainly to Bombay, and a few of them went to Madras and Bengal, up to Karachi (today in Pakistan due to which they have lost their ancestral land in Goa, as India considers it ‘Enemy Property’!).

It was the Old Conquests (92%) once again with Bardezkars (48%) topping the list, which was almost half of the total number of emigrants. The volume of annual migration doubled in the second half of the period. Saxttikars were next in numbers and there were around 25,000 from Tiswadi. Equivalent to the onetime Island of Goa were the Goans from the whole of the New Conquests. On an average, 4000 Goans left the state for good every year.

“Goans who migrated during this period to British India were both Hindus and Christians. Women migrated independently to British India. They were mostly unmarried women or widows from lower classes. Among independent female migrants were ‘bailadeiras’ (dancing girls). Large number of women who migrated worked as domestic staff at the homes of Parsi and British families, while others worked as nurses and secretaries. Men generally migrated to the rest of India without their families. They were engaged in skilled and unskilled manual jobs. A small number took up white-collar jobs or worked as musicians. Some proceeded to Bombay for further studies in medicine and other fields.”^6

Emigration Of Goans To British India: 1880-1910

YEAR | TISWADI | SALCETE | BARDEZ | OLD CONQUESTS | NEW CONQUESTS | TOTAL
1880 | 1562 | 9050 | 15623 | 26235 | 2981 | 29216
1890 | 1972 | 9203 | 18743 | 29918 | 2981 | 32899
1900 | 3564 | 11881 | 19598 | 35043 | 1978 | 37021
1906 | 3340 | 15814 | 19679 | 38833 | 3612 | 42445
1907 | 3702 | 17084 | 19557 | 40343 | 3500 | 43843
1908 | 3699 | 16817 | 20530 | 41046 | 3605 | 44651
1909 | 3950 | 17113 | 20932 | 41995 | 3654 | 45649
1910 | 3954 | 18773 | 21164 | 43891 | 3557 | 47448
TOTAL | 25743 | 115735 | 155826 | 297304 | 25868 | 323172
% | 8 | 36 | 48 | 92 | 8 |

Source: Some Aspects of the Consumption History of Estado da India: 1900-50 by Dr Remy Dias

The trend of emigration continued till Goa was liberated, and also for various other reasons like the economic blockade imposed by independent India. Many people left their land because their family-earners in India could not remit money to Goa freely.^7 Besides, a series of epidemics that broke out at the beginning of the 20th century, especially of influenza, hit the Old Conquests taking a heavy toll of lives.

The third study is an official document of the Government of Goa, called Goa Migration Study 2008. It’s a sample survey conducted by the NRI Commission of Goa of 6000 households selected by the Stratified Multistage Random Sampling Method. Of these, 3100 households studied in the report are from the three major talukas of the Old Conquests: Salcete, Tiswadi and Bardez. The report examines various aspects of the life of these Goans, who travelled outside Goa as emigrants (settled outside) as well as migrants (moved out for jobs, education, etc.) as well as returned-emigrants and returned-migrants, who resettled in Goa.

As per this study, almost 60,000 Goans had migrated in 1931, out of which 45,000 settled in Bombay, 3500 in Karachi, 1000 in Calcutta and 800 in Rangoon, besides other parts of India. Nearly 85 per cent among them were Christians; only 7500 were Hindus and Muslims. After recession hit British India in 1930, many Goans either returned home or went to the Gulf. But in 1938, around 55,000 Goans were left behind. After World War II, as Bombay grew as a business centre, the number soared to one lakh, out of which the majority occupied positions in business, liberal professions and administration, as well as in public services like restaurants, guest houses, and tailoring shops. By the time Pakistan was created, several Goans there had established business houses and large public companies which they headed as their chief executives. Many streets in Karachi were named after eminent Goans. However, many young Goans left Karachi. In 1958, Karachi had 5000 Goans.^8

The trend of out-migration, especially by the Christian community, continues till date. Due to this, in the last 60 years since liberation, the 38 per cent Christian population of Goa has reduced to 25 per cent; from one-third to one-fourth of Goa’s total population. These are the figures from the 2011 census. The 2021 census is certainly expected to show further reduction, also because a large chunk of the population has migrated to the UK during this decade, by adopting Portuguese citizenship and giving up their Indian citizenship.

If not for this huge exodus of Christians, the political scenario vis-a-vis elections would have been totally different today. Goa would have continued to be a Christian-dominated state. This issue cropped up significantly during the Opinion Poll of 1967, when Dr Jack de Sequeira’s United Goans Party demanded voting rights for the Goan expatriates. Did they get the right to decide about the identity of their state? It is one of the interesting episodes in the chapter in this book, dedicated to this unique historic and exciting referendum held in the Indian Republic.

Foreigner Goenkars

The next phase saw Goans migrating abroad and settling in those respective countries. This again consisted largely of Christians, since it was considered inauspicious and taboo for Hindus to cross the seas. The Hindus would actually be outcasts from the community if they did so. Hence, the number of Hindus migrating abroad was negligible. The Portuguese economy in Goa had almost collapsed, agriculture did not bear enough fruits for a comfortable living, and the promotion of education threw up new opportunities for the neglected Christians in Goan society. The migration began with East African countries in 1895 and then took a real leap from the first decade of the 20th century.

Margaret Frenz, a historian and Oxford University scholar who has studied migrations across the world, has written extensively on migrations from Asia and also specifically from Goa. According to her, the main focus of Goan migrations was on East Africa. Goans migrated in two phases: in the first decade to settle in East Africa, and then in the second half of the 20th century to settle across the ‘western world’ in the UK, Canada, USA, Australia, New Zealand, Brazil, Portugal, and other countries. She not only deals with migrations but also with how Goans settled down in different countries of Africa as a Goan community, their social and cultural behaviour, and their active involvement in local politics.^9

It sounds quite interesting when their brothers and sisters living in Goa today keep grumbling about the ‘invasion’ of Goa by our own Indian migrants from other states, especially the labour and trading class, whom we humiliate as Ghantis. More interestingly, our Goans living abroad are now financing the political outfits that have sprung up in Goa to fight elections on the grounds of ethnicity, with their vote-guns pointed at the politicians who nurture vote banks of migrants. But when the migration of Goans abroad is studied from a socio-cultural viewpoint, their tales sound similar to what we witness among the migrants in Goa today.

EAST AFRICA

The Industrial Revolution in Europe and the USA had a direct repercussion on Estado da India in terms of new opportunities for employment, including self-employment. The destination was British colonies in East Africa. The first Goan ‘pioneers’ migrated in 1895 to Zanzibar, an island in Tanzania, to work in the administrative units of the Imperial British East Africa Company and then to Mombasa, Dar-es-Salaam, and Nairobi between 1900 to 1907, once again to work in the administrative setup of the construction companies of Uganda Railway. By 1911, around 1200 Goan clerical officers worked in the Kenyan and Uganda administrations. The treasury and audit departments were completely in Goan hands. It was a three-tiered system on ethnic lines, with Europeans in the top tier, African staff in the lower ranks, and Indians (including Goans) in the middle.

A chain movement then started off, of getting Goan family members, relatives, and fellow villagers to work in different parts of East Africa, not only in the administrative service but also in various professions and business enterprises in which Goans had expertise. This included hotels, restaurants, bars, bakeries, photo studios, tailoring shops, teaching, healthcare, law firms, etc. The following table is a census conducted in these countries, where Goans were listed separately and not with other Indians since they came from the Portuguese Estado da India.

Goans In East Africa (1911-1948)

Year | KENYA | UGANDA | ZANZIBAR | TANGANYIKA | TOTAL
1911 | 1136 | 0 | 440 | 656 | 2232
1921 | 2431 | 474 | 869 | 798 | 4572
1928 | 3131 | 929 | 954 | 1445 | 6459
1931 | 3979 | 1124 | 1004 | 1722 | 7829
1938 | 6205 | 1257 | 871 | 1839 | 10172
1948 | 7159 | 1448 | 681 | 2006 | 11294
TOTAL | 24041 | 5232 | 4819 | 8466 | 42558

Source: Global Goans, Migration Movements and Identity in a Historical Perspective by Margaret Frenz, University of Oxford (2007)

The major attraction however was the ‘government service’ since it had a hefty salary, a permanent position, prospects for promotion and other benefits, as well as six-months of leave every four years. This allowed Goans to visit their homes in Goa regularly and leave their children behind with their grandparents for ‘good education’ in Goa.

The sports and culture-loving Goans set up their own clubs in major cities, conducting sports tournaments, regular parties, dances, and celebrating their own festivals. Marriages took place strictly within the Goan community through these regular social interactions at the clubs, sports events, and schools meant for Goan communities. The most popular sport was hockey, followed by badminton, cricket, tennis, table tennis, billiards, and others.

Besides village communities celebrating their Goan festivals locally, the feast of St Francis Xavier was celebrated throughout East Africa on the 3rd of December each year. Quite a number of East African Catholic churches were built with generous Goan support, including prominent ones like the St Francis Xavier Church in Nairobi, and Christ the King Cathedral in Kampala.

Goans in East African countries were also active in politics. The freedom movement in India had an impact on the nationalist movement in East Africa. With their involvement in local politics, two Goans reached one of the highest positions in Kenya. Joseph Murumbi (1911-1990) and Pio Gama Pinto (1927-1965) were the second vice-presidents of Kenya. Pinto was shot dead in 1965, the first victim of a series of political assassinations.

However, the situation changed drastically in the 1960s when East Africa achieved independence and nation-states were created with international boundaries. Uganda attained independence in 1962 and Idi Amin seized power in early 1971. Zanzibar and Kenya became independent in 1963 and Mozambique in 1975. Meanwhile Goa was also freed from the four-and-a-half century colonial rule of the Portuguese in 1961. There was total Africanisation of the local administration all across East Africa. New immigration acts came into force and the rights of Commonwealth citizens (including Indian Goans) grew restricted in terms of citizenship. Furthermore, the revolution in Zanzibar in 1964, the expulsion of Asians from Uganda in 1972, and the coup in Kenya in 1982 created an atmosphere of apprehension in the Goan community.

Goans had no other option than to leave. But very few Goans came back to Goa and hardly anyone preferred Portugal. Most of them moved to other industrialised western countries like the UK, Canada, USA, Australia, New Zealand, Brazil etc.

In 1972, approximately 29,000 Asians arrived in the UK from Uganda, including Goans. One survey conducted by the Goan community in 1970 found 5000 Goans settled in London city alone. While 80 per cent among them found white collar jobs, others had to start afresh or work in lower positions and work their way up in various careers, from hairdressers to university professors and IT and finance professionals. Margaret Frenz writes that in 2007, there were 800 Goans left in Kenya, 500 in Tanzania, 100 in Zanzibar and 50 in Uganda.^10

USA

Goan settlers began arriving in the US from East Africa around 80 years ago. In 1990, the US had 5000 Goan families, mostly Goan Christians.^11 However, the 21st century has witnessed a large migration of Goan Hindus to the US, mainly as IT professionals. Till January 2020, 12.80 lakh Indians are recorded to be living in the US, which, of course, includes Goans.^12

PORTUGAL

Despite Goa being a colony of Portugal for over four centuries, the number of Goans settled in Portugal is less compared to other European countries. The embassy of India in Portugal, on its website, states that there are 90,000 people belonging to Indian-origin diaspora and another 30,000 Indian nationals. However the Goans there − all Catholics – number barely 15,000. In fact, the Indian Hindus in Portugal amount to almost the largest chunk of which comes from Gujarat (40,000), probably including Daman and Diu, followed by Punjab (30,000), Haryana (10,000) and Kerala (2000). The Sikhs are 35,000 and Muslims are 20,000.^13 Another study conducted in 1992 states that there are 11,000 Goans in Portugal, of whom 6000 live in Lisbon.^14

However this may not include the Goans, mostly Hindu goldsmiths, who had migrated in the early 16th century, or the upper-class Christians and Hindus who moved there in the second half of the 19th century. Most of them migrated for higher education and settled there as clerks, doctors, engineers, lawyers, magistrates, teachers, journalists, officials in armed forces, and bureaucrats.

“There are thus broadly four distinct groups of Goans who have settled in Portugal; (i) those who came straight from Goa and settled down in Portugal during the colonial regime, which can be classified as pre-1961; (ii) those who came from Goa post-1961 after Goa was taken over by India; (iii) those who came via Africa, especially the former Portuguese colonies, particularly after the independence of Angola and Mozambique; and (iv) more recently those who have migrated to Portugal with a view to settling in other developed countries in Europe or elsewhere."^15

The latest migration Goa is presently witnessing for the last three decades is that of thousands of Goans, mostly Christians but also including some Hindus. They have taken advantage of the provision in Portuguese law that allows those born before Goa’s liberation in December 1961 and two generations thereafter to opt for Portuguese nationality. As Portuguese citizens, they are EU passport holders and thus eligible to move, live, and work across the bloc. However, it needs to be seen how much the decision of BREXIT, the exit of the UK from the EU, will affect the ongoing migration of Goans to the UK via Portugal.

The British government has already assured enough security to those who are already working there. Two types of status will be granted to Goan-origin Portuguese and other EU citizens: Settled status for those who have lived in the UK for five years or more, and pre-settled status for those who have been in the UK for less than five years.

No authentic figures are available to ascertain how many Goans have given up their Indian citizenship, adopted Portuguese citizenship, and actually migrated to the UK.

“The citizenship is granted directly in Lisbon by the Central Civil Registrar… There are an estimated 17,000 Goans with Portuguese citizenship living in the UK. Only a minority of these migrants remain in Portugal. According to an unconfirmed source, there is currently a waiting list of 12 to 13 thousand for passports at the Portuguese consulate in Goa and a few thousand passports are issued to such applicants each year. There are also some recent instances of non-Goans who have sought to apply for Portuguese nationality, using false papers.”^16

WORLD POLITICIANS OF GOAN ORIGIN

COUNTRY | NAME | HIGHEST POSITION HELD | YEAR | BORN | ORIGIN
Portugal | Alfredo Nobre da Costa | Prime Minister | 1978 | Lisbon, 1923 | Goa
| Narana Coissoro | Member, Assembly of Republic | 1976-2005 | Goa, 1933 | Panaji
| Alfredo Bruto da Costa | Minister for Health & Social Welfare | 1979 | Goa, 1938 | Margao
| Nelson de Souza | Minister for Planning | 2019 | Goa, 1954 | Goa
| Antonio Costa | Prime Minister | 2015 | Lisbon, 1961 | Margao
| Jorge Barreto Xavier | Secretary of State & Culture | 2012 | Goa, 1965 | Goa
| Joao Leao Fernandes | Finance Minister | 2020 | Lisbon, 1974 | Sarzora
UK | Ernest Soares (Gaitonde) | MP from Barnstaple | 1900 | Goa, 1864 | Ucassaim
| Valarie Vaz | MP from Walsall South | 2010 | Aden, 1954 | Assolna
| Keith Vaz | Minister of State for Europe | 1999 | Aden, 1956 | Assolna
| Sayonara Luxton | Mayor of Windsor & Maidenhead, UK | 2016 | Goa, 1955 | Colvale
| Seulla Braverman | MP from Fareham | 2015 | London, 1980 | Assagao
Kenya | Pio Gama Pinto | Member of Central Legislative Assembly | 1963 | Nairobi, 1927 | Goa
| Joseph Murumbi-Zuzarte | 2nd Vice President | 1966 | Kenya, 1911 | Goa
Pakistan | Cincinnatus Fabian D'Abreu | Councillor, Karachi Municipality | 1900 | Goa, 1862 | Saligao

Goans when settled abroad not only assimilated into their new countries but some of them also played a major role in politics. Some of them reached the highest possible positions. Portugal had two prime ministers of Goan origin and four in ministerial positions. Similarly, Kenya had a Goan as the second vice-president. The following table has listed 15 Goans who reached high positions in four countries. Half of them were born in Goa and then migrated to the respective countries.

One among them, Sayonara Luxton, the Mayor of Windsor and Maidenhead in the UK, was brought up in Goa, schooled in Mapusa, and then moved to Dubai at the age of 21. She then moved to the UK in 1993. Recognising her social work among the drug-addicted youngsters, her town elected her as councillor. She then rose to the position of deputy mayor and eventually became Mayor.

While we proudly celebrate the elevation of our Goenkars in political positions in foreign countries, in Goa, we look at our own Indian migrants as a ‘threat to Goa’ if they rise up in political positions after working sincerely in social and political fields. Is Goa’s politics stooping to regional and ethnic fanaticism while our bright Goans with a worldwide vision shine in different parts of the world? Goa’s ‘broadminded’ politics needs introspection indeed!

GULF

The oil boom in the Gulf region of Middle East in the 1960s and 1970s lasted till early 1990s. Thousands of Goans, from the Old and New Conquests, largely Christians but also Hindus, made fortunes by working at various levels in the Gulf.

“There were 50,000 Goans in Kuwait, Dubai and Abu Dhabi in the 70s and a total of 150,000 Goans in the Gulf in 1987. Goan migration to the Middle East was never a permanent phenomenon since the countries in that region do not grant citizenship to foreign nationals; however, many have spent decades there. Goans still prefer to move to those countries, believing that a job there would be more rewarding than employment in Goa.”^17

Goans who migrated to the Middle East have not settled there permanently, neither do Goans who are now going to the UK with Portuguese citizenship have plans to settle in Europe. But unlike the Gulf Goans, the ‘Portuguese Goans’ have given up their citizenship. In both these categories, Goa has received a huge amount of remittances, which are being invested in education, medical treatment and housing. However, since India has no system of dual citizenship like the Portuguese, these migrated Goans have opted for OCI (Overseas Citizen of India) cards, in order to have a hold over their properties in Goa. But this is not a permanent solution.

“Remittances to Goa, around Rs 700 crore (annually) have a significant effect on the economy. Remittances are 6.3 per cent of the State Domestic Product of Goa. Remittances are one-third of the revenue receipt of Goa but only 6 per cent of the Government expenditure.”

But this has slowed down substantially due to the worldwide pandemic of Covid19. Thousands of migrants working abroad as well as the emigrants have come down to Goa. They have no source of income. Their future is uncertain since it is not known when the waves of Covid19 will permanently die down. While the Christian community, especially in the Old Conquests, is fuming over this, it would not be surprising if this becomes a major election issue. But, right now, no political party seems to be seriously applying its mind over this economic crisis.

Are Migrants Outgrowing Goans?

The emigration of Christian Goans did not stop after Goa’s liberation. But the trend of leaving Goa and settling outside did slow down. In fact many Christians who had settled in other Portuguese colonies in East Africa came back to their motherland. Despite this, the Christian population of Goa has kept shrinking.

The graph below shows a decline in Christian population even after liberation, in the last 50 years. In the New Conquests, it has declined marginally from 15 to 11 per cent. But in the Old Conquests, it has slipped down from 56 per cent to 35 per cent.^18 That’s stunning!

Source: Census of India

The graph shows that this trend in the last 50 years (till 2011 census) is more visible in the Old Conquests, where the Hindu population has increased substantially, by almost 13 per cent. Added to this is the eight per cent rise in the Muslim population, though small in numbers. This has affected the number of Christians in the Old Conquests. There is a sharp decline of 21 per cent, due to emigration as well as in-migration of non-Christians.

A few Christians however have also migrated to Goa from coastal states like Kerala or tribal hilly states like Jharkhand. But the emigration of the Christian community is not the sole reason for its declining population in Goa. Added to this is the huge amount of in-migration of Indian Hindus and Muslims from other states due to which Christian population is proportionately declining. The Christian population at the time of Goa’s liberation was 2.25 lakhs. Today, it has risen to 3.66 lakhs, a steady rise of around 62 per cent. But compared to this, the Hindu population has soared in the last 50 years from 3.54 lakhs to 9.64 lakhs, a rise of 150 per cent. The Muslim population has also risen from 12,000 in 1961 to 1.22 lakhs in 2011, generally due to in-migration.

It’s an interesting phenomenon that Goan Christians go all over the world and set up shop and take up different professions in the service industry. But similar opportunities in Goa are overlooked by them. This vacuum is then filled by Indian migrants from other states, especially in trade and business. Goa’s migrant population does not include the working class labourers alone but also the middle class traders, upper middle class professionals and also the upper class retired elite of India. In addition, most celebrities in India have a second home in Goa.

But what is the actual migrant population residing in Goa today, since 1961? Unfortunately, no government has bothered to conduct any extensive survey in this regard nor has any political party demanded it. However the politicians are busy competing with each other to win over these ‘vote banks’ by providing them basic amenities like housing, water, electricity, ration, etc., not as their basic right as Indian citizens, but as ‘favours’. The only data available is the Census conducted every 10 years by the central government. But it is not very accurate in the count of migrants since they have different criteria set to measure the in-migration.

The quantifying of migrant population is a complex exercise but it is needed to understand the current demographics of Goa. Understanding this is of utmost importance because there are sweeping statements made by responsible leaders of the society including ministers, businessmen, educationists, and even priests, that migrants from other states are flooding the state in a big way. If this trend continues, Goans would be pushed into a minority. Is it true? Let us examine this.

The table below shows some interesting statistics. It shows the decadal growth in Goa’s rural and urban population. Urbanisation is a normal trend in which we always find an increase in urban population and a decline in rural population. In the first decade after Goa’s liberation, in 1971, the rural population shows a normal growth of 18 per cent. Despite this, the urban population has grown by 133 per cent. Obviously, this is not just due to Goan villagers rushing to the cities but due to a huge influx of migrants.

Decadal Growth In Rural-Urban Population: 1960-2011

YEAR | TOTAL | RURAL POPULATION | | URBAN POPULATION |
| | PERSONS | GROWTH | PERSONS | GROWTH
1950 | 547448 | 476517 | | 70931 |
1960 | 589997 | 502668 | 5.49 | 87329 | 23.12
1971 | 795120 | 591877 | 17.75 | 203243 | 132.73
1981 | 1007749 | 684964 | 15.73 | 322785 | 58.82
1991 | 1169793 | 690041 | 0.74 | 479752 | 48.63
2001 | 1343998 | 675129 | -2.16 | 668869 | 39.42
2011 | 1458545 | 551731 | -18.28 | 906814 | 35.57

Source: Census of India

“The port town of Mormugao is a classic example of this phenomenon where the growth of population recorded was as high as 579.70 per cent during the last decade. The town of Madgao in Salcete taluka is a big commercial centre of the territory which has recorded a high growth rate 216.28 per cent, next to the port town of Mormugao. A number of smallscale units located on the periphery of the Madgao town had also helped add up to its population during the decade.”^19

The Census report also observes that the migrants did not consist of merely the working class but also others who cited various opportunities due to the developmental works taken up by the Indian and Goa government. As a Union Territory, opportunities sprang up in the field of education, health, transport, and construction work. For example, Goa’s 614 educational institutes in 1960 increased to 1441, including a few colleges in the cities and primary schools all across the Goan countryside. This brought in a large number of teachers, especially from Maharashtra. Goa had only 38 hospitals and health centres, which rose to 262, creating job opportunities for doctors, nurses, compounders etc. The construction activities taken up to develop infrastructure needed labour. This led to migration from Karnataka, Andhra Pradesh, Kerala, Uttar Pradesh, Tamil Nadu etc.

The following table compiled from the Census reports explains it with a state-wise break-up. It is based on the information recorded about a person living in Goa but was born in another state. Of course it includes a Goan born outside the state and does not include a migrant child born in Goa. But it still certainly provides a rough picture. Unfortunately, this data is not available beyond the 1981 census.

Even during Portuguese rule, Goa had migrants, not only from other states of India but also from other countries, besides 6689 Portuguese. There were 461 Africans, French, Germans, Italians, Egyptians, Spanish, Japanese and even Chinese. None of them are found in the 1971 census. The total number of migrants from within India was 6085. This number however jumped to nearly one lakh in the first ten years and then went on swelling every decade. In 1991, it rose to 1.70 lakhs, but interestingly, reduced to 1.20 lakhs in 2001. The census figures of migrants in the 2011 census have not yet been released.

Why is the number of ‘migrants’ reducing? The reason is found again in the Census. By 1991, almost half of these migrants were found to be living in Goa for more than 10 and 20 years. Almost one-fourth of them live for more than 10 years, and around 18 per cent for more than 20 years. No figures in this category are available in the 2001 Census and the 2011 figures are not yet out. While these figures are derived from the state they were born in, their children were born in Goa and even their parents have become Niz Goenkar since they have been living here for the last 50 years. A large chunk of them also speak fluent Konkani. This assumption is proved by yet another Census finding, based on their mother tongue.

Migrants In Goa From States In India: Census

STATE | 1961 | 1971 | 1981
Karnataka | 1017 | 33510 | 71976
Maharashtra | 3751 | 33579 | 52077
Kerala | 113 | 5329 | 8136
UP | 527 | 5241 | 5110
Andhra | 48 | 2889 | 3547
Tamilnadu | 192 | 2640 | 3320
Gujarat | 137 | 1496 | 1841
W Bengal | 54 | 716 | 995
MP | 37 | 617 | 934
Orissa | 2 | 189 | 797
Bihar | 9 | 733 | 770
Rajasthan | 94 | 667 | 717
Punjab | 27 | 1052 | 715
Delhi | 20 | 341 | 638
Haryana | 0 | 504 | 324
Himachal | 1 | 283 | 198
J&K | 8 | 84 | 133
Assam | 4 | 177 | 128
UTs | 44 | 59 | 128
Tripura | 0 | 8 | 24
Meghalaya | 0 | 2 | 23
Sikkim | 0 | 1 | 10
Manipur | 0 | 15 | 8
Nagaland | 0 | 1 | 6
TOTAL | 6085 | 90133 | 152555

Source: Census of India

MOTHER TONGUE OF GOANS: CENSUS INDIA

LANGUAGE | 1961 | 1971 | 1981 | 1991 | 2001 | 2011
Konkani | 556297 | 556237 | 600004 | 602513 | 769805 | 963980
Marathi | 11630 | 168339 | 265803 | 390220 | 304208 | 158757
Hindi | 1647 | 11375 | 20498 | 31873 | 63921 | 126020
Kannada | 945 | 16504 | 33473 | 54292 | 74615 | 67923
Urdu | 9414 | 18910 | 27580 | 39927 | 54163 | 41242
Malayalam | 120 | 5620 | 7562 | 12919 | 15081 | 12983
Telugu | 209 | 3870 | 5527 | 7887 | 11926 | 11116
English | 614 | 2654 | 6367 | 4816 | 8190 | 9765
Bhojpuri | | | | 439 | 3197 | 9185
Lamani | | | | 3690 | 5896 | 7300
Bengali | 41 | 709 | 800 | 1836 | 4111 | 7099
Tamil | 286 | 2233 | 3861 | 6770 | 7903 | 6947
Gujarati | 1345 | 2444 | 3164 | 4432 | 9273 | 6846
Oriya | | 151 | 97 | 679 | 2681 | 5558
Bhilli | | 39 | 206 | | 94 | 2665
Nepali | 8 | | 450 | 960 | 2135 | 2600
Other | | | 5099 | 2635 | 2400 | 2500
Rajasthani | | | | 296 | 1060 | 2202
Punjabi | 14 | 1260 | 1229 | 1825 | 1815 | 1959
Banjari | | | | | 708 | 1728
Marwari | | | | 244 | 583 | 1407
Assamese | | 97 | 12 | 144 | 195 | 1107
Sanskrit | | 20 | 3 | | 46 | 1055
Sindhi | 53 | 227 | 369 | 300 | 527 | 656
Kashmiri | | 11 | 10 | 212 | 472 | 372
Manipuri | | | | 49 | 367 |
Others | 239 | 182 | 428 | 884 | 1331 | 898

Source: Census of India

These figures of the mother tongue simply don’t match with the figures of migrants from other states. For example, we know that people from Karnataka are still migrating. In 1981 they numbered 72,000. Three decades after that, there are only 68,000 Kannada-speaking people. It means the onetime Kannadigas have assimilated in Goan soil and have been registering their mother tongue as Konkani. Let’s take yet another example. The most humiliated Indian community (Ghanti) among these are the Lamanis, who are also called Banjara. The Goa Banjara Samaj President Suresh Rajput once told me in a TV debate that over one lakh Lamanis are settled in Goa and they have come from different states. Despite this, in the 2011 Census, only 9028 have registered their mother tongue either as Lamani or Banjari.

This can be also argued as a well-planned design of the migrants in order to grab all kinds of benefits Goans get. Do they get these benefits? There was a survey conducted in 2006 by Children’s Rights in Goa (CRG), an NGO working for the welfare and rights of children of Goa. The survey was fully focussed on Goa’s migrant labour and their children. The findings were a real eye opener, exploding all kinds of myths we believe about migrant labourers. Let me cite a few of them:

More than one-third of migrant labourers have been living in Goa for over 15 years and legally fall in a domicile category, meaning they are Goans by all measures. More than half of them live in rented premises, 16 per cent live in their own houses and hardly eight per cent live in shanties (slums). Fish and rice is a staple food for over half of them and 17 per cent among them eat Xit-Koddi. Nearly 60 per cent of the adults and over 80 per cent of children speak Hindi, but over 40 per cent of adults and nearly 65 per cent of children also speak Konkani. They are the vote bank of politicians, this is the usual allegation. In reality, half of them don’t vote and 20 per cent of them vote in their native states since they have no local voting cards. Almost two third of them want to settle in Goa and 96 per cent of children ‘like’ Goa.^20

Do we find it surprising? What did our ancestors do? The first settlers of Mundari tribe came from Chota Nagpur in Bihar. This was followed by ‘migrants’ (Ghanti?) coming from Indian states like Bengal, Orissa, Jharkhand, Madhya Pradesh, Chhattisgarh, Gujarat, Maharashtra, etc. as well as foreign countries like Afghanistan, Pakistan, Iraq, Europe, Arab countries etc. After living here for many generations and getting assimilated completely with the local language, culture and lifestyle, we call ourselves Niz Goenkars. Not enough; we − the migrants at one time − call the new migrants Ghantis and look at them as a threat!

At the same time, we Goans go all over the world to work, settle there, assimilate there and even establish ourselves successfully in all kinds of fields, from business to politics. When some of them become mayors and presidents of the country, it’s a proud moment for us. Not a threat to those respective countries! Is this not a double standard? Let’s introspect.

Why do we look at the neo-migrants as a threat to Goa? Because we go out and they come in. We seize the opportunities available all around the world while they jump at the opportunities getting created in Goa. And then we fear that one day they will outgrow us. Goa’s politics has been moving around this anxiety. Is there truth in this unknown fear?

The table of the people who have registered their mother tongue as Konkani or Marathi, coupled with the people who were born outside Goa; in Maharashtra. The figures of Marathi speaking and Maharashtrians simply do not match. When the Konkani-Marathi controversy started heating up in Goa, a call was given by Marathi protagonists to the Goans to register their mother tongue as Marathi. In response, the number of Goans calling themselves ‘Marathi’ went on rising till the historic official language agitation of 1986.

Konkani & Marathi Of Goa & Maharashtra

LANGUAGE | 1961 | 1971 | 1981 | 1991 | 2001 | 2011
Konkani | 556297 | 556237 | 600004 | 602513 | 769805 | 963980
Marathi | 11630 | 168339 | 265803 | 390220 | 304208 | 158757
Maharashtrians | 3751 | 33579 | 52077 | | |

Source: Census of India

The issue was finally resolved in 1987, around which time the Census of 1991 was also conducted. In the heat of agitation, the number of ‘Marathis’ rose up to 3.90 lakh, which was almost half of the ‘Konkanis’ registered in the Census. With the language controversy cooling down in the 21st century and the new generation opting for Konkani, the number of ‘Marathi Goans’ has now reduced to half of the number registered in the 2001 Census. It is bound to reduce further in the 2021 Census. The graph is a clear indication of the trend.

It needs to be seen how many ‘Marathi Goans’ remain in the 2021 Census, along with the Goans born in Maharashtra. But even without them, the number of Konkani-speaking Goans remains three times more than the migrants. And if we add so called Marathi-speaking Goans to it, the number of migrants slips to one-fourth of Goa’s population. In that case, are we fighting a non-existent demon? Is it worth fighting elections on these fanatic grounds by aiming at soft targets like the migrant workers, whom Goa needs for our daily existence? Are we missing the target? Are they the real enemies of Goa? Or are the land sharks the real enemies, who are grabbing our land and selling it to build holiday homes to those for whom Goa is nothing but a holiday destination to exploit? And who are the ones who are selling our land to the land sharks? Friends of Goa? Are they Niz Goenkar? Bhumiputras?

Mendonça Delio de: Conversions and Citizenry, Goa under the Portugal 1510-1610 P 85↩︎

De Souza Teotonio: The Portuguese in Goa↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Some Aspects of the Consumption History of Estado da India: 1900-50 by Remy Dias↩︎

De Souza Teotonio: The Portuguese in Goa↩︎

Da Silva Gracias; Goans away from Goa, Migration to the Middle East↩︎

Quality of life in colonial Goa by Fatima Gracias↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Frenz Margaret; Global Goans, Migration Movements and Identity in a Historical Perspective↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Ministry of External Affairs↩︎

Embassy of India, Lisbon, Portugal↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Chanda Rupa & Ghosh Sriparna; Goans in Portugal: Role of↩︎

ibid↩︎

Goa Migration Study 2008↩︎

Census of India↩︎

Census of India 1971↩︎

Talpankar Prashanti; Shadows in the Dark 2006↩︎

Chapter 9

Laying the Ground for a Revolution

The process towards establishing democracy in Goa began with the military administration being replaced by Lt Governor T Sivasankar on 8 June 1962, six months after liberation. The first step was to appoint two Members of Parliament from South Goa and North Goa on 20 June − Dr Antonio Colaço and Dr Pundalik Gaitonde, respectively.^1 Dr Gaitonde belonged to the Indian National Congress, a Goa branch of which was formally founded on 11 June. Dr Colaço, an eminent medical practitioner and a landlord from Borda, Margao, represented the Goa Provincial Congress.

Dr Colaço’s appointment to the Lok Sabha ignited the first spark of public protest in Free Goa. At a public felicitation function of both the MPs held in Mapusa on 6 July 1962, hundreds of people gathered outside the Mapusa Municipal building, shouting slogans against Dr Colaço and demanding elections for MPs. Lt Governor P Sivasankar, who was the chief guest, even had to face stone pelting at this public function.^2

This was followed by a fast-unto-death by a young freedom fighter, Roque Santana Fernandes, in the lobby of the Margao municipal building from 9 July. He ended it after five days only when he got a firm assurance to fix a meeting with PM Pandit Nehru in Bangalore to resolve this issue. His other freedom fighter colleagues assured him that they would go on a joint hunger strike if Nehru didn’t satisfy him. Fernandes did not pay heed even to the written assurance by AICC General Secretary K K Shah, during his Goa visit, that elections would be held. The fast was also supported by several freedom fighters who held public meetings at the venue.^3

The prime contention of Roque Santana Fernandes was that Dr Colaço was an associate of the Portuguese regime and that he was one among those who were demanding autonomy for Goa within the Portuguese empire when Goans were giving their lives for total freedom and joining the Indian Union.^4 These appointments developed into the first political controversy, which probably laid the foundation of the historic Assembly election of 1963.

The people at large were also upset over the manner in which Lt Governor T Sivasankar had set up a 24-member Consultative Council. Besides freedom fighters, trade union leaders, Shetkari Sanghatana activists and leaders of the political parties, the Lt Governor had also nominated on the Council Goa’s prominent landlords and mine owners like Vaicuntrao Dempo, Madhavrao Talaulikar as well as some doctors and professors who had always aligned with the Portuguese. Due to this the Council had to take mild stands on some land-related issues, which the people wanted Free Goa to resolve immediately. This accommodative approach created skepticism in the minds of the political activists.

Making & Breaking Of The Congress

It all evolved through the National Congress Goa (NCG), which had led Goa’s non-violent freedom struggle. Divergent views were prevailing in the NCG even during the freedom struggle, on the issue of Goa’s proposed merger into Maharashtra. A strong group within the NCG had laid down a two-point programme: 1) To free Goa from the Portuguese and make it a part of India; and 2) To merge Goa into Maharashtra. However, there was another group that did not want any confrontation on the issue of shaping up Goa, especially when mining was severely affected due to world recession, agriculture was in a bad shape, and building Goa socio-economically seemed a Herculean task.

A group of the NCG espousing the cause of merger convened a convention in Mapusa on 22 May 1962, chaired by the eminent freedom fighter P P Shirodkar. The convention passed resolutions demanding Goa’s immediate merger into Maharashtra and to promote Marathi as the official language while calling Konkani a dialect of Marathi. This NCG group also supported pro-merger fronts organised in several parts of Goa like Mapusa, Kaisuv, Bicholim, Virnoda, Kavlem, Mardol, Quepem etc, in the New Conquests as well as in Bardez. They propagated their cause by holding meetings during the Marathi dramas performed at Zatras (Hindu temple festivals).^5

Another NCG group met at the People’s High School in Panaji to decide whether the organisation should be retained or dissolved. It was attended by Peter Alvares, Gopal Apa Kamat, Pandurang Mulgaonkar, Shankar Sardesai, Dr Vinayak Mayekar, Anthony D’Souza and Prafull Priolkar among others. The meeting not only decided to retain the organisation but also formed a committee, which met Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru in Delhi and requested him to maintain the separate identity of Goa by promoting Konkani as well as Marathi languages.^6

According to Purushottam Kakodkar, who later led the Congress for over a decade, he had decided to withdraw from politics as he felt alienated and left out by his own like-minded colleagues. The second NCG group did not even invite him for this meeting and also did not show him the memorandum to be submitted to the PM when his colleagues met him in Bombay. There was no question of the pro-merger group contacting him since he was one of the most vociferous leaders who opposed merger and supported Konkani as the language of Goa. However, he changed his mind when Adv Pandurang Mulgaokar, Adv Gopal Apa Kamat and Prof Shankar Sardesai persuaded him by meeting him twice in Margao requesting him to take the initiative of forming a branch of Indian National Congress in Goa. Accordingly, on 11 June 1962, an ad-hoc committee of the INC Goa was formed with Kakodkar and Dr Pundalik Gaitonde as its convenors.^7

Other members of the committee were leading freedom fighters too: Mulgaonkar, Kamat, Sardesai, Dr J F Martins, Dr Vinayak Mayekar, Dr Ram Hegde, Prof Laxmikant Bhembre, Anthony D’Souza, N B Rao, Alvaro Pereira, Dr Laura D’Souza and Mitra Madhav Bir.^8

These are the founders of the Congress party in Goa. It was a group of freedom fighters who had their differences of opinion on merging Goa into Maharashtra. Kakodkar himself was a strong proponent of maintaining a separate identity of Goa while Dr Gaitonde was supporting the merger. The committee members also had a mix of these opinions.

They immediately formed an Agriculture Cell headed by Madhav Bir and Adv Mulgaonkar with the intention of taking ahead the cause of exploited peasants who were the tenants of Bhatkars and Communidades, as well as the issues of Kumeri cultivators etc. On the other hand, the Azad Gomantak Dal had been converted into the Goa Democratic Party and had organised a Shetkari Parishad in August 1962. Later on, the Congress leaders succeeded in pursuing the militant leaders like Adv Lawande etc to join the national party and fight unitedly for the cause of the downtrodden masses. This move also strengthened the force of mergerists within the Congress since most of the AGD members favoured merger.

Differences within the Congress came to the fore when the first organisational election was held on 20 March 1963. Congress leader Radha Raman from Delhi was the returning officer. The battle lines were drawn, especially for the post of the President of Goa Pradesh Congress Committee (GPCC). Madhav Bir was the candidate proposed by the pro-merger leaders Adv Vishwanath Lawande and Tulshidas Malkarnekar. Shankar Sardesai and Ligorio Cota Carvalho proposed Kakodkar’s name. It was 20 versus 13. Kakodkar became Goa’s first elected president of a party, winning the election by seven votes. For the post of Treasurer, Vasco businessman Vasant Joshi (eight votes) lost the election to Apa Karmalkar (20 votes). Manju Gaonkar from Canacona was elected unopposed as the vice president.

The other members elected as GPCC members were Shankar Sardesai, Ligorio Cota Carvalho, Gopal Apa Kamat, Anthony D’Souza and Chandrakant Kerkar. Dr Jose Francisco Martins, Sardesai and Malkarnekar were elected as members of AICC.

But the battle was not limited to the contest between the two groups. Laura D’Souza, an eminent freedom fighter who was heading the National Congress Goa in 1955, sat down on a hunger strike in front of the Congress House, alleging malpractices in the elections. She had several complaints about the conducting of elections in Benaulim, Vasco, Tiswadi and Pernem, and that the Congressmen who had complained about the malpractices to the high command had been restrained from entering the election venue. The party had to then appoint a two-member inquiry committee consisting of R S Panchahazare and Ramdatta Dubey. After investigating, the Committee did admit some instances of irregularities, but termed it minor and refused to conduct elections afresh. After that, the Kakodkar Raj began in the Goa Congress.^9 Laura D’Souza was then allotted a ticket to contest the MP election from South Goa.

In a lengthy interview to Gomantak, Kakodkar denied all the allegations made against him including that he had received a cheque of Rs 25,000 from Kantilal Gosalia, a mine owner and that this money had been used to buy votes in his favour. He however admitted that he had received some donations from wealthy people of Goa and that the account books were open for scrutiny. He also claimed in this interview that Goa had many wealthy people, but hardly any person who could be ‘termed’ a Capitalist. What he meant by it was clear when candidates were chosen to contest the first Assembly election.

The Churning Of Thoughts

On the other hand, after some of the leading NCG and AGD members joined the Congress, the socialists including Peter Alvares, Shivaji Desai, Gajanan Raikar, etc. founded the Goa branch of the Praja Socialist Party. The Communist leaders and trade unionists decided to work under the guise of Frente Popular, in an attempt to try and attract the minorities who were against the Communists due to the influence of the Church.

Waman Radhakrishna, a veteran journalist and freedom fighter, in his book on the Maharashtrawadi Gomantak Party, has aptly described the mindset of the common Goenkar at this juncture:

“The Bahujan Samaj was happy with Goa’s freedom but was not trying to understand why it had remained backward. He was uneducated, but was not trying to find out the root cause behind their backwardness. Rather than being self-critical, he preferred to blame the community which had reached far ahead of him. To quite an extent, it was true. The high class people enjoyed all the privileges under the Portuguese regime… There were three sections of Goan society that were exploiting the Bahujan Samaj. The Bhatkar (landlords), the Savkar (moneylender) and the Empregado (bureaucrat). Sometimes all these three sections were found together in one family. There were also some educated people from the Bahujan Samaj who were into money lending or working as Empregado. These egoistic people were considering themselves to be the high class. From the point of view of the Bahujan Samaj, they had also become ‘Bamonn’ (Brahmins)... The Bahujan Samaj was scared that the same people would continue exploiting them using their power of education and influence.”^10

Amidst these developments, two more socio-cultural organisations were in search of a political solution. One was the Gomantak Maratha Samaj (called Pragatik Maratha Samaj in those days), its members were educated, some of them had migrated to Bombay, and some had risen up locally in business and as professionals. They had a well-educated and sensible leadership. They were engaged in discussing how to end the exploitative system through democratic means in Free India. On the other hand was the Goa Hindu Association (GHA) of Bombay, which was largely dominated by educated and progressive-minded Saraswat Brahmins as well as members from the Gomantak Maratha Samaj and a few educated members from other communities. Around the time of Goa’s liberation, Maharashtra had also become a state through a prolonged struggle. Yeshwantrao Chavan had adopted the Bahujan formula to rule while enacting the Land to the Tiller Act. The agricultural sector had started progressing on co-operative lines in leaps and bounds in Maharashtra.

As a result, some of the leaders from the GHA took the initiative and formed the Maharashtrawadi Gomantak Mandal (MGM) in Bombay, echoing the demand of Goan Bahujan Samaj to merge Goa into Maharashtra and get a lifetime of freedom from the nexus of landlords, moneylenders, and bureaucrats.

Most of them were strong proponents of Marathi. The Bombay based artists from the GHA were dominating the field of theatre, music, dance, films, literature, etc. in Maharashtra. Adv Sushil Kavalekar, one of the leading lawyers of Bombay and originally from Ponda, was elected the President of the MGM, Bombay.

Shashikant Narvekar, a veteran journalist originally from Mapusa, as well as Ramdas Prabhugaonkar, an artist originally from Loliem, Canacona, were elected the general secretaries.^11 84-year old Prabhugaonkar, who was the Secretary of the GHA for around 25 years, told me an interesting anecdote in this regard. To celebrate the first anniversary of the MGM, Bombay, they went to invite P K Atre, popularly known as Pracharya Atre, one of the firebrand and fearless leaders of Samyukta Maharashtra movement, as the Chief Guest of the function. To their surprise, he flatly refused to accept the invitation, asking in his witty style why they wanted to merge Goa into Maharashtra when “you have nothing to eat and I have nothing to drink”. (Maharashtra government had imposed prohibition on liquor consumption at that time). Interestingly, Pracharya Atre’s periodical Maratha played a major role later during Goa’s Opinion Poll and Atre himself addressed public meetings in Goa, supporting the merger.

While they were wondering whom to invite instead, Jagannath Sukhatankar, a writer and their member, assured them that he would try and get Dayanand Bandodkar, a businessman and social reformer from Goa. Accordingly Bhau Bandodkar graced the function. He liked the name of the organisation and commented: “We are also trying to form a political party in Goa. This name would suit us well.”

The Lion In The Making

But the MGP of Goa was neither an extension of the Bombay MGM nor an initiative of Bandodkar. The wheels of the Assembly election had started moving with the Parliament passing the Union Territories Act 1963 on 10 May. Union Home Minister Lal Bahadur Shastri had also announced that the first Assembly election for 30 seats including one each of Daman and Diu, as well as the two Parliamentary seats, would be held in the first week of December. The first democratically government would be installed on the second anniversary of Goa’s liberation − 19 December 1963.

Just eight months before the elections, the MGP was formed in Goa.

Different groups in Goa had been discussing the formation of a political alternative to the existing parties, especially the Congress and the Praja Samajwadi Party. As said earlier, the youth in different parts of Goa had constituted fronts to champion the cause of the merger into Maharashtra and to seek freedom from land-enslavement. The cause of the merger received a major boost with Vishwasrao Chowgule launching Goa’s first Marathi daily Gomantak on 24 March 1962. He was a mine owner who came from Marathi-speaking Belgaum and set up his business in Goa during the Portuguese regime. B D Satoskar, the editor of Gomantak and a Marathi writer, was a strong proponent of the merger. Followed by this, Janardan Shinkre, another freedom fighter from Ponda, launched the second Marathi daily Pradeep on 6 September 1962^12 as a Free Voice of the people of Goa, without any strings attached like the business interest of the Chowgules. The four-page daily was priced at five paise. Incidentally, both Satoskar and Shinkre were Saraswat Brahmins, but of a firm view that landlordism should come to an end and the tiller should be the owner of his own land.

The person who took the initiative to bring all the promerger forces under one common banner was Janardan Shinkre. While running his pro-merger Front from Ponda, he realised that many people wanted to join the cause but had their reservations about the National Congress Goa. He discussed the matter with P P Shirodkar and both of them convened a meeting of all the like-minded leaders at Mardol on 6 March 1963. Bandodkar was also invited to this meeting. PSP leader Shivaji Desai proposed that a forum on the lines of Samyukta Maharashtra Samiti be formed. But it was election time. The thought boiled down to the forming of a political organisation and contesting elections.^13 Bandodkar proposed the name Maharashtrawadi Gomantak Sanghatana, on the lines of the MGM in Bombay. It was agreed upon unanimously.

Bandodkar was elected as the founder president of the MGS. By 7 April 1963, the National Congress Goa group led by P P Shirodkar had formally merged into the MGM at a meeting held at Mardol. Eventually, the MGS was registered as the Maharashtrawadi Gomantak Party (MGP) and the Election Commission of India allotted Lion as its symbol. This Lion roared in the hearts of the Bahujan Samaj of Goa and ruled uninterruptedly for the next 17 years.

A little before the first meeting held to form the MGS, a secret meeting of non-Brahmin leaders was convened at the residence of Tukaram Lolayekar, a businessman in Madgao, which was also attended by Bandodkar as well as Narayan Karwarkar, the then president of Gomantak Maratha Samaj, Rajaram Painginkar and Bhalchandra Kankonkar. The proposal was to form a ‘Non-Brahmin Party’ on the lines of the Justice Party of Madras. However, Bandodkar vehemently opposed the idea of coming together based on a divisive agenda and creating an anti-Brahmin front that would divide the Goan society on caste lines. He strongly proposed that all the communities from the entire state should work together under one banner.^14 “Where did you find this Bandodkar?” asked Raghunath Tople of Mapusa to Shinkre of Ponda the day the MGS was formed. Shinkre told him: “He carries lots of respect among the Bahujan Samaj.”[^15]

People knew Bandodkar in those days as a young businessman and mine owner, who was generously donating funds for any good social cause, especially in the educational and cultural fields. But very few people knew what ideology he belonged to. Tarkateertha Lakshman Shastri Joshi has revealed this in an article he has written on a book published on Bhausaheb on the occasion of his 60th birthday:

“I met Bhausaheb Bandodkar in 1962. I was not aware that he knew me for the last 25 years. I was invited to Goa to inaugurate the Shetkari Parishad. I was put up at a bungalow on Altinho where I was welcomed by a smart-looking midage impressive personality called Dayanand Bandodkar, who was the mastermind behind the farmers’ conference. He had assigned his daughter Shashikala to look after me. He told me that during his stay in Bombay in 1942, he had heard all my speeches. At that time, I was the official spokesman of the Radical Democratic Party, founded by Com M N Roy (based on his Marxist philosophy of Radical Humanism). Bhau was attending my study circles on international politics, Marxism etc, held at our Dadar office. He had even heard M N Roy, was impressed with his lectures and had become a Royist himself. However, he stayed away from joining the party when the internal differences in the party came to the fore.”^15

B D Satoskar, the first editor of Gomantak, says that Bhau gave credit to Lokmanya Tilak for his mission of Charity.^16 Sitaram Tengse, yet another senior journalist and former Editor of Rashtramat, says that many politicians in those days were inspired by Royist theory of Humanism, including Maharashtra’s first chief minister Y B Chavan, D B Karnik and especially veteran freedom fighter Com Shamrao Madkaikar in Goa, who was very close to Bhau. Being a Marxist himself during his student days, Tengse says Royism was much ahead of Communism, Royism respected human sentiments, freedom of thought and efficiency of human beings, irrespective of caste, creed or religion.^17 According to Amrut Kansar, Bhau was equally influenced by the reformist movements of the 19th century in Maharashtra, led by Vithal Ramji Shinde, Mahatma Phule, Shahu Maharaj, Dr Babasaheb Ambedkar etc.^18 The concept of ‘Bahujan’ had evolved through these influences which Chavan had implemented in Maharashtra and Bhau wanted it to be extended to Goa, by merging it into Maharashtra.

This makes it crystal clear why Bhau opposed an anti-Brahmin party and refused to be part of any organisation that would divide the Goan society. For him, more than Marathi or Maharashtra, oppression of the downtrodden classes was the real issue and ending the exploitative system through democratic means was of paramount importance. However, he and the MGP represented the feelings of the farming community from the New Conquests. It was a different scenario altogether in the Old Conquests, except for some parts of Bardez.

The MGP leadership did not realise that Marathi was an alien language for the Christian farmers as well as the landless labourers from the Old Conquests. Christians from the New Conquests were studying in the Marathi schools, but they were not even one-fifth of Goa’s total Christian population. The majority among the Christians lived in the Old Conquests and were not at all comfortable with the thought of merging their Goan identity into Maharashtra, calling themselves Marathi.

The divide and rule policy of the Portuguese by suppressing the development of Konkani was bearing fruits in the first election itself.

Morarji Versus Nehru

While mergerist forces were uniting under the banner of the MGP, union home minister Morarji Desai paid a two-day visit to Goa, confusing the whole issue further. At a crowded press conference held on 12 May 1963, he stated that all the union territories would be merged into the larger neighbouring states sooner or later. This directly contradicted the stand taken by Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru that the distinct identity of union territories like Goa or Pondicherry would be maintained for at least ten years, after which its future would be decided by the people of those respective territories, not by the central government.

It was a ‘shocking’ press conference. He dismissed the possibility of restarting the lotteries, at the cost of revenue loss. At the cost of even further revenue loss, he said liquor prohibition would also be extended to Goa. He refused to accept the argument put forward by some journalists that social drinking was part of Goan culture. He was not sure that the territory’s economy would continue to be financially viable, while making it clear that all kinds of taxation measures would be extended to Goa shortly. And the final stroke in this comment: “The prime minister has never said that Goa would remain separate if it succeeds in becoming self-sufficient.”

Within 10 days, Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, the liberator of Goa, arrived on a three-day visit, from 22 to 24 May 1963. He was one man who had been consistently saying, even before liberation, that India would maintain Goa’s distinct identity. The issue of merger had been hounding Goa since 1940, and Nehru was the sole Congress leader who had countered all kinds of pressures from his party colleagues, especially from Maharashtra and to some extent from Karnataka, to merge the territory which was half the size of any district of the neighbouring states. But the Prime Minister had not left a single opportunity to display his firmness. While addressing a rally of Goans in Bombay on 4 June 1956, Nehru had said:

“What have we done in the French settlements? First of all, we have maintained their identity. We could easily or we can easily, in future, absorb them into the state of Madras or some district of Madras State. We do not propose to do that, because we want to maintain the individuality of Pondicherry and Karaikal. We want to maintain the type of French culture that has developed here, the French language that has developed there and they have complete freedom to continue their own laws, their educational apparatus and everything… So, here is an example for you which obviously would be applied by us to Goa when the time comes. I am saying this because some people are misled, either by false propaganda or by overenthusiastic people in India who say that Goa would be attached to Maharashtra or Karnataka Province… I hope you will be very friendly and cooperative neighbours.”[^20]

[^20] Kelekar Ravindra; (Editor) Nation’s Solemn Commitments on Goa 1963

Nehru said this repeatedly in Bombay and also in the Parliament before liberating Goa and even after finally making Goa a part of the Indian Union through Operation Vijay, the military action. Perhaps this was the reason he was greeted with a grand welcome everywhere, from the time he landed in Goa on 22 May 1963 at 11.55 am at Dabolim till he flew back from Vasco by helicopter on 24 May. During his threeday tour from Dabolim to Panaji, Margao, Mapusa, Calangute, Bicholim, Old Goa, Mangeshi, Ponda, and Vasco, no less than one and a half lakh Goans had either gathered to listen to him or greet him while his motorcade was passing through. Apart from the public rallies, he had three special get-togethers with children in Panaji, Calangute, and Bicholim, a meeting with newly elected panchas in Margao, and a special convention of farmers in Ponda. On the first day itself, on the way to Panaji from the airport, he had to face the first unscheduled stop at Sancoale, where the locals disregarded police arrangements and garlanded him. He was greeted at the airport by a crowd of over 10,000 and on the last day, when he had planned to meet citizens of Vasco after visiting the Mormugao port and the naval base, the small scheduled meeting had to be shifted to Tilak Maidan to control the crowd of thousands, including women holding their babies in their arms.^19

Nehru did not disappoint anybody. He kept the hopes of mergerists alive by telling them at each and every rally as well as the press conferences that after a decade Goans would be given an opportunity to decide whether they wanted a merger or not. On the first day itself, at a rally at Bandodkar Maidan in Panaji, Nehru allayed the fears created by Morarji Desai a week before.

“There should be no hankering for Goa’s merger with this state or that. Goa should develop as it likes in the framework of India, particularly because Goa was potentially a rich place and it had all the makings of being a self-supporting state. If the Goans themselves brought about economic developments and raised the living standards, there was no reason why it should not function as a separate unit of federal India.”^20

Goa and Goans proved this visionary right. Since 1987 Goa has thrived as a self-sufficient State with the highest per capita income, highest standard of living, and also topping several parameters like the health index and more.

At the press conference, he also clarified on certain issues on which Morarji had created panic. No liquor prohibition would be enforced in Goa in the foreseeable future, he clarified. He also assured that his government did not want to impose on the Goans anything they themselves did not desire.^21 Here are some more statements Nehru made either at the public rallies or the press conferences:

“Purely on merits, I think it (Goa) should be kept separate. Apart from merits, because a considerable number of people here − it is immaterial whether they are a majority or minority − a considerable number here are afraid of being submerged by another individuality, if I may say so.

It is quite absurd to put Konkani against Marathi or Marathi against Konkani. This kind of linguistic approach of suppressing a language is bad. Therefore, I think that while all the languages should flourish here, particular attention should be paid to Konkani, which is the common people’s language.

India is like a beautiful carpet, the textures of which bring out beautiful differences. But it is one carpet, and one whole, that is the beauty. So we must continue to go on weaving it by our activities, thoughts and by our actions. But always remember the unity of it, the unity of design of it, and yet l maintain the beauty of individual parts of it.”

The Media Blackout

Nehru had tried to awaken the Goan masses, but perhaps the Goan media had a different agenda. Goa had four newspapers, including two Portuguese dailies carried forward post-liberation, O Heraldo and A Vida, besides Gomantak, the Marathi daily. A year later, on 18 February 1963, The Navhind Times was started by Dempo Group, Goa’s leading mine owner and a prominent landlord. These two latest newspapers had a significant mass reach among the newly educated Goans, who could read English and/or Marathi. Both the newspapers very skilfully blacked out Nehru on one important aspect he spoke repeatedly at all his public rallies − his dream of Land to the Tiller.

On the day he arrived in Goa, at a rally held at the Bandodkar ground in Panaji, attended by around 30,000 people, he said:

“Apart from that the Portuguese here and if I may say so to some extent in their own country have developed a society which is completely out of date in the modern world. I am prepared to admit that our society in India is also out of date in a different sense, and we have to change it; but this change in ending of the Portuguese domination here necessarily resulted in changing many things. The changes are going on. And when a change happens in the social fabric, it has an upsetting feature. It may ultimately be good; it may even immediately be good for many; but for some, it is upsetting. And I can well understand that.

Now we do not want this change or any change to occur which causes harm or injury to the people, but sometimes it cannot be helped. Suppose, as in India, one of our major reforms has been putting an end to the big landlord system, the big zamindari system, because we thought it was bad for the peasantry and for the people generally to have this big landlord system. That is the common thinking all over the world today. But in removing the zamindari system, the poor zamindars suffered. We gave them compensation and they said it was not enough. They suffered.

When there is social change, it has to be faced. One tries to minimise the inconvenience of the suffering, but for the larger social good, it has to be faced. Anyhow, it was inevitable that some changes should take place here, should upset your normal way of living. We did not want it to happen, we try to avoid that. We have to minimise it, but the fact is there and we want to work well, we want rather to leave it to you to work and according to your wishes so as to proceed to have this change over quietly and as far as possible for the benefit of the larger number of this."^22

Nehru was clear in his thoughts about abolishing the ‘outdated’ feudal system, which we called Bhatkarshai in Goa. He was also blunt enough to state that he could not help if it upset the existing system in Goa. The next day, at a much bigger rally of around 30,000 in Margao, he explained why abolishing the feudal system of Zamindari was the need of the hour if we ha to progress and compete with other developed countries:

"So we want to create a society in India which gives opportunity to everyone and which lessens greatly the differences that exist between the people, rich and poor: That is a difficult job, but it is a possible job and we are going to achieve it. It was not possible perhaps in the old days, but science has made progress, and science and technology have made it possible for us by our own labour to produce enough for everybody. That will take some time.

You know how rich America is, how rich England and Germany and Japan are, and Russia? What is there in common between a capitalist country like America and Communist country like Russia? A common factor is that both depend on science and technology and both have made progress. Their Gods are science and technology. They may have different religions but the real Gods they worship are science and technology. And there is no capitalism in science and no communism in physics and chemistry and other things. It is just knowledge as such.

And it is by that knowledge that they have progressed and it is by that knowledge that we shall progress. Science and the children of science, technology etc, that will tell us how to increase the wealth that we produce from the land, from industry, and that is the only way. We cannot produce wealth except by hard work and by understanding modern methods of working on land and for industry. It is not a thing by going to an astrologer that you get rich, or by other methods like that; it is hard work.

So, we adopted, soon after freedom came to us we adopted this major method, this major approach, which we call the planning approach, thinking out what we should do. One of the first things we did was to put an end to the large landlords in India because they came in the way of the country’s progress. A bad agrarian system prevents a country from progressing, and that is the first thing that has to be removed. In Europe it was removed by bloody wars. In Japan it was removed after the last great war. Everywhere this is the first thing. So we had decided, even before independence, to remove it and we removed it and we have very largely succeeded. We want peasant proprietors on the land and you will remember that in our country 80 percent of the people live in the villages. And our country will really only progress when the 80 percent progress. It is not the cities, big cities like Bombay and Calcutta and Delhi or Madras, that make a difference, but the villages that must progress. And therefore, we have to think of this general progress of the country- villages and towns and the like."^23

Goa, at that time, was also 80 per cent rural. It was getting educated. It was struggling. It was looking for an alternative economy that would stop out-migrations of Goans for better prospects and develop the existing geographical structure of Goa. Nehru had laid down the plan before the people. And then when he went to Ponda the same day to address Goa’s farmers, he even told them how to achieve this goal:

"In the olden days, we had a feudal system in India and all the land was owned by zamindars, taluqdars, jagirdars and princes. The rest of the people worked for them which was not right. That system has been abolished. Now we want that the tillers of the soil should own the land too. [Applause] It is gradually happening. It has already come to pass to a very large extent. But it is not enough to have abolished feudalism. We must increase production from land. We have to adopt the right methods.

First of all, as I said, education of children is extremely important… We have adopted the Panchayati Raj system to strengthen the development programme… So now you will find that you do not have to belong to a wealthy family or a high caste to attain some position. Those who work hard and serve the country will be chosen for their ability. No one will occupy high positions because of his birth or connection… We want that the people of Goa should take the reins of government into their own hands as it is being done in the rest of the country… You will elect representatives to the Lok Sabha in Delhi who will participate in the law-making processes for the entire country. Secondly, you will have your own legislature in Goa to which the people will elect their representatives."^24

It was a clear-cut election agenda he set for the people of Goa. Abolish the feudal system of Bhatkarshai, let the tillers own their land, educate their children, and learn modern technology. To achieve this, elect your own representatives through elections and start ruling Goa for the haves and the have-nots. Did the Congress party adopt Nehru’s strategy to achieve this goal? We will deal with this question in the next chapter on how the candidates were chosen and what was the result of it.

Landlords Rally Around The UGP

The core component of Nehru’s speeches did not go public through the media, except for one day in Gomantak. But not less than one and a half lakh people had heard him. It was discussed in the towns and the villages, at the markets, tinttos, tea shops, taverns and practically everywhere since the first election was at the doorstep. While the farming community and the common Goan were in a cheerful mood, the landlord community, across the religious lines, was quite upset. If they didn’t pull up their sleeves, it could be the end of their age-old hegemony and feudal rule.

On the other hand, the Christian community was getting restless over the growing mood of merging Goa into Maharashtra. Though migrant Christians were familiar with Marathi in Bombay, they were not well-conversant with it. It was an alien language for Christians living in Goa. Secondly, in a four-crore strong Maharashtra, Christians were hardly six lakhs. Even if Goa had merged into Maharashtra, it would be a drop in the ocean, with the Christian population not able to cross two per cent. In Bombay, they had experienced it while facing the domination of Gujaratis and Marathis.

As the elections approached, a tug of war began within the Congress over allotment of tickets to some landlords, and the pro-merger lobby started pressuring the party leadership. This uncertainty perhaps created panic among the landlord class and they decided to align with the Christian community, who were trying to mobilise the anti-mergerist forces as a political alternative. In a shrewd manner that is typical of the upper class Brahmins, the landlords across all the religions decided to override the sentiments of the minority community and pose a challenge to the movement of land reforms that Nehru had spelt out in clear terms.

Hardly three months ahead of the Assembly and Lok Sabha elections scheduled in the first week of December, on 13 September 1963, a formal announcement was made of a new regional party. Five political groups functioning in the Old Conquests came together under one common banner − the United Goans Party (UGP). Most of the leaders either belonged to Christian Brahmins (Bamonn) and Kshatriyas (Chardo), owning land and/or were doctors, professors, or lawyers earlier aligned with the erstwhile Portuguese rulers. The Hindu Brahmins from Margao, the stronghold of Saraswat Brahmins, also joined hands with them. John de Souza was the sole freedom fighter among them.

The oldest and biggest organisation among the five was Partido Indiano, led by Dr Alvaro de Loyola Furtado, which had earlier contested the ‘high-class’ Parliamentary elections during the Portuguese regime. The party was founded by Alvaro’s Portuguese-speaking grandfather. Dr Loyola Furtado was a prominent Saxttikar Bhakar and equally respected doctor from Chinchinim. During the Portuguese regime, he was known for his liberal views.

*A India Portuguesa was Goa’s first weekly in Portuguese started in 1850 and was changed to A India after liberation. It was the mouthpiece of Partido Indiano. After coming to power, in 1964, the MGP government had imposed press censorship on its publication, alleging that it favoured the Portuguese. It was later shut down. At that time, however, it was run by Loyola Furtado’s daughter Leonor Loyola Furtado e Fernandes.

Dotor Loyola Furtado, as he was popularly known in Saxtti, was chosen as the founder president of the UGP.

Dr Jack de Sequeira, a 48-year old doctor and a landlord from Panaji, had founded Goencho Pokx, during the same period. He was known for his liberal views and courageous attitude.

The Goa National Union led by J M de Souza was pursuing with the central government an entirely new democratic setup for Goa. He had proposed a legislative council of 48 members, four each elected from 12 talukas (conselhos in Portuguese regime) and a cabinet of 12, one each from a conselho, administered by the Centre. He had even met Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru on 10 January 1962 in this regard.

Besides this, there were also two other small groups, the United Front of Goans led by Meilicio Fernandes and Democratic Party by Dr Joao da Costa Pereira.^25

Within three days, on 16 September the Sunday, the UGP had its first public meeting at Saligao in Bardez. It was attended by around 500 people. Besides these five leaders, it was also addressed by Lima Leitao, the Vasco-based lady mine owner and landowner; Sadashiv Desai, a Bhatkar from Pernem as well as Jagdish Rao. Their prime attack was on the Congress, blaming the party for Goans going through hardships since liberation due to restrictions imposed on mining, banning of the lottery, and curtailing imports. The speakers also cautioned the people of the next probable step to prohibit consumption of liquor.

Incidentally, on the same day, the Congress President Purushottam Kakodkar, Ligorio Cota Carvalho and Tulshidas Malkarnekar, in a meeting organised by the Margao block, carried out a scathing attack on the UGP. Calling it a communal party, they alleged that the leaders had their selfish motives and had no interest in protecting the interest of their community.^26 In its meetings, the Congress leaders also made fun of the Land to the Tiller demand made by the UGP leaders. Since most of their leaders were wealthy Bhatkars, the Congress leaders publicly asked if they agreed with the demand and whether they would now personally hold the plough in their hands and get into the field physically.^27

The UGP manifesto had land reforms and Tenancy Act as one of the prime points, though in public meetings they mainly harped upon their demands like Statehood for Goa and opposing merger of Goa into Maharashtra.

Clear cut battle lines were thus drawn in Goa’s first historic election where three major parties were crossing swords, the Congress, the UGP, and the MGP. The battleground was The Land!

Annual Report of the Ministry for External Affairs 1962-63↩︎

गोमंतक; 7 जुलै 1962↩︎

गोमंतक; 9-14 जुलै 1962↩︎

गोमंतक; 10 जुलै 1962↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; महाराष्ट्रवादी गोमंतक पक्षः स्थापना आणि वाटचाल पान 18↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा पान 11↩︎

नागवेंकार डॉ हरिश्चंद्र ; पुरुषोत्तम काकोडकार, जिवीत आनी कार्य, पान 72↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा पान 17↩︎

Parobo Parag D; India’s First Democratic Revolution P 117↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; महाराष्ट्रवादी गोमंतक पक्षः स्थापना आणि वाटचाल पान 13, 15↩︎

Interview with Ramdas Prabhugaonkar↩︎

प्रभू परेश वासुदेव; गोमंतकीय मराठी पत्रकारितेचा इतिहास, पान 213, 216↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; महाराष्ट्रवादी गोमंतक पक्षः स्थापना आणि वाटचाल, पान 20↩︎

कारवारकर उर्फ मराठे नारायण आ; आमच्या समाजाचे स्फूर्तीस्थान (आमचे भाऊ,↩︎

जोशी लक्ष्मणशास्त्री; अनेक तेजस्वी पैलू असलेले व्यक्तिमत्व (आमचे भाऊ, ना. भाऊसाहेब बांदोडकर षष्ठ्यद्विपूर्ती↩︎

सातोस्कर बा. द.; समाजसेवक बांदोडकर (आमचे भाऊ, ना. भाऊसाहेब बांदोडकर षष्ठ्यद्विपूर्ती गौरव ग्रंथ) पान 91)↩︎

टेंगसे सीताराम; एक असामान्य लोकनेता (भाऊसाहेब गौरव ग्रंथ 2011) पान 23-24↩︎

कांसार अमृत; अभिवादन समाजपुरुषाला (भाऊसाहेब गौरव ग्रंथ 2011) पान 14↩︎

The Navhind Times; 23 to 25 May 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; Nehru Conquers Heart of Goa, 23 May 1963↩︎

The Hindu; 26 May 1963↩︎

Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru; Series 2/Vol. 82/May 1963-July 1963 Pg 162↩︎

Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru; Series 2/Vol. 82/May 1963- - July 1963 Pg 183↩︎

Selected Works of Jawaharlal Nehru; Series 2/Vol. 82/May 1963- - July 1963 Pg 191-92↩︎

The Navhind Times; 14 September 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; 17 September 1963↩︎

गोमंतक; 14 ऑक्टोबर 1963↩︎

Chapter 10

The Revolutionary Election

Differences within the Congress started coming to the fore with the beginning of the election process and the releasing of the party manifestos. The party preferred to play with words on the most debatable issue of Goa’s merger in order to please both the camps, and invited wrath from both the sides. On the issue of merger, the manifesto stated:

The Government of India has made it clear that the future of Goa and whether it should merge into the adjoining territory of Maharashtra will be ultimately decided according to the wishes of the people of Goa. For the present this question does not arise as we have to stabilise and strengthen the economy and facilitate the changes that are taking place because of the integration of Goa in the Indian Union.^1

The UGP camp wrote lengthy articles in newspapers, cutting Congress to the size, by asking varied questions, about Who, When and How? Who are these people who would decide? Goans living in Goa or also Goans living outside Goa? And will Goans living in Goa also include people from Maharashtra and other states living in Goa? When will this be decided? Later, means after 5 months? 5 years? 50 years, or more? And how would it be decided? By means of a plebiscite?^2

The Congress kept mum.

On the other hand, Gomantak carried the news of the manifesto as an eight-column headline, claiming that the Congress has finally agreed to merge Goa into Maharashtra and has left the decision to the people, linking it directly to the forthcoming election.^3 The AICC, on the day the election manifesto was approved in Delhi on 2 October 1963, had made it clear that the future of Goa would not be an election issue.^4 Still, it was made an election issue by the mergerists. Amidst the confusion, the pro-merger camp within the Congress dashed off to the national capital and met Nehru, pressing for immediate decision on the issue of merger. They were furious because the original draft sent by the manifesto committee chairman Adv Pandurang Mulgaonkar had been altered by Purushottam Kakodkar by sending a counter note. His note was included in the manifesto.[^5] The delegation led by Dr Pundalik Gaitonde included Adv Gopal Apa Kamat, Anthony D’Souza and Madhav Bir. Due to this, AICC General Secretary K K Shah came down to Goa on 12 October to pacify the party functionaries.

While claiming that the confusion has been resolved, Shah told the media that he also met the MGP and the UGP leaders and even they were convinced about the stand taken by the Congress. This enraged the UGP and Dr Jack de Sequeira and Dr Melicio Fernandes clarified that they had never met Shah and that they stood by the party’s demand of Statehood for Goa.^5

Bhausaheb Bandodkar admitted to having met Shah, but did not disclose what transpired in the meeting. However, Waman Radhakrishna narrates a completely different version of this meeting. According to him, Bhau was kept waiting by Shah at Hotel Mandovi, where he was deliberating with his party colleagues like Kamat, Mulgaonkar, etc. After a long wait, he was called inside at the request made by Gomantak Editor B D Satoskar to the Congress leaders. He saw Bhau sitting restlessly in the lobby and intervened. But Bhau was apparently furious. He told Shah and the local Congress leaders that he had come there with a plan to join their party, but now he has changed his mind after the humiliating treatment he received from the local and national Congress leaders.^6

During this visit, Goa’s leading mine owners like Shantilal Khushaldas, Vasudev Salgaoncar, Pandurang Timble and Dempo also met Shah.

On the other hand, the PSP leaders from Maharashtra started pressing for the immediate merger of Goa into Maharashtra, which embarrassed the Congress further.

Congress Embraces The Mighty Bhatkars

While the manifesto controversy was dying down, another big controversy arose with the Central Parliamentary Board releasing the first list of the Congress candidates on 30 October 1963. Prominent among them was Goa’s biggest mine owner and landlord Vaicuntrao Dempo, who was allocated a ticket from Pernem. There were also some small landlords chosen to be the candidates, contrary to what Nehru had announced during his Goa visit. Also, cleverly, some of the mergerists were allotted constituencies over which they had no hold while the anti-mergerists had comfortable constituencies for them.

The other candidates included 18 freedom fighters: Lucio Rodrigues (Siolim), Dr Jose Francisco Martins (Aldona), Atmaram Karmalkar (Mapusa), Mitra Bir (Tivim), Gopal Apa Kamat (Bicholim), Pandurang Mulgaonkar (Pale), Jaykrishna Shirodkar (Sanguem), Dr Vinayak Mayenkar (Ponda), Ravindra Kelekar (Madkai), Shankar Sardesai (Shiroda), Alvaro Pereira (St Estevam), Anthony D’Souza (Panaji), Tukaram Kankonkar (St Cruz), Dattatray Deshpande (Mormugao), Ligorio Cota Carvalho (Cortalim), Laxmikant Bhembre (Margao), Joao Cabral (Curtorim), Purushottam Kakodkar (Curchorem) and Dr Ram Hegde (Quepem).^7

The list also included other candidates like Shivram Azgaonkar (Mandrem), Rudolph D’Mello (Calangute), Baburao Hirbarao Desai (Sattari), Maria Elvina Pinto Menezes (St Andre), Irene Barros (Benaulim), Irene Fereira (Cuncolim), Bernardo do Reis (Navelim) and Shivram Fondu Naik Desai (Canacona).^8

The real shock to the Congressmen was Vaicuntrao Dempo, who did not fit the criteria laid down by the party to choose candidates. Gomantak, in its editorial, tore into the Congress party. B D Satoskar pointed out that the pro-mergerist candidates were allotted seats contrary to their choice of the constituency they had mentioned in the application form. Secondly, he observed that the major criteria of participation in the Goa independence movement had been blatantly violated by allotting tickets to the opportunist bootlickers of the Portuguese. He also alleged that the Congress had accommodated them in the party fold in order to prevent them from joining the UGP.^9 (This clearly suggested that Goa’s Bhatkars were rallying around the UGP.)

Though neither Gomantak nor any other prominent daily had named anyone in particular, it was crystal clear that the prime target was Dempo. It was also because he had been elected as one of the three Deputados (Member of Parliament) in the Portuguese Parliament for a four-year term from 1961 to 1965, before Liberation.^10 `The history of the loyalty of the Dempo family with the Portuguese was an open book. His great grandfather Guiridora, known fondly as Guiri-bab, was

“honoured by the Portuguese with a title, Cavalier of the Land for Valour, Loyalty and Merit" in 1869. Another illustrious Dempo forefather was Guiri-bab’s nephew, Rayu-bab. It was he who was decorated with a baronetcy by the Portuguese (Barao, baron in Portuguese).”^11

The reaction this time was more antagonistic. Within five days, 18 prominent Congressmen resigned from the party’s primary membership in protest of the selection of candidates, including two candidates: Anthony D’Souza (also the GPCC Secretary) and Dr Ram Hegde. Their resignation letters stated that the Parliamentary Board had betrayed the basic aspirations of the people of Goa, bypassing the pledge of socialism and the ultimate goal of the merger; and that the election made the battle easier for the established reactionary and anti-national forces. The letter also hinted at tickets being allotted to those who were in good books with the Portuguese establishment till yesterday.

The other 16 members who resigned were GPCC vice president Narayan Naik, the President of Goa Chamber of Commerce and Industry Madhavrao Talaulikar, businessmen Bhagwant Naik, Damodar Kashinath Naik and Prabhakar Angle, Adv Vishwanath Lawande, Dattaram Desai, Punaji Achrekar, Manju Gaonkar, Zotico D’Souza, M S Prabhu, A S Naik, Shrirang Karmali, Tulshidas Malkarnekar, Prabhakar Ghodge and even Madhav Bir, whose wife Mitra was allotted the ticket from Tivim.

Shah had to rush down to Goa within a month, on 9 November, hardly two days before the former union home minister Lal Bahadur Shastri was scheduled to launch the election campaign. He along with Mohan Dharia and G B Nevalkar succeeded in working out an amicable solution to try and end the crisis. But only half of the protesters withdrew their resignations after exchanging their constituencies.

Accordingly, Madhav Bir was given the ticket in Tivim instead of his wife Mitra and Anthony D’Souza withdrew from the fray, paving the way for Alvaro Pereira to shift from St Estevam to Panaji. The other exchanges were Laxmikant Bhembre from Margao to Sanguem, Jaikrishna Shirodkar from Sanguem to Madkai, Ravindra Kelekar from Madkai to Margao, Shankar Sardesai from Shiroda to St Estevam and Dr Ram Hegde from Quepem to Shiroda. Anthony D’Souza and Tulshidas Malkarnekar declared that they would work for the party. Businessmen Madhavrao Talalulkar, Damodar Kashinath Naik, and Bhagwant Naik also withdrew their resignations.

Meanwhile, the Bombay MGM publicly appealed to all those who had resigned to join the MGP, Goa. Accordingly, the remaining nine including Prabhakar Angle joined the MGP. Four of them were given tickets by the MGP: Punaji Acharekar from Calangute, Narayan Naik from Panaji, Vishwanath Lawande from St Andre, and Dattaram Desai from Quepem. Interestingly, except for Dattaram Desai, the other three neo-MGP stalwarts lost the battle to the UGP candidates. Zotica D’Souza, M S Prabhu, A S Naik, and Shrirang Karmali did not contest, but joined the MGP.

The Congress list was further modified twice. In Canacona, Shivram Fondu Naik Desai was replaced by Ganaba Desai. Moreover, Dr Vinayak Mayenkar was shifted from Ponda to Quepem to accommodate mine owner and landlord Madhavrao Talaulikar. The much bigger blow to the Congress was the dropping of Shivram Azgaonkar, perhaps the only Scheduled Caste candidate, to give the ticket of Mandrem to Raoraje Deshprabhu, yet another pro-Portuguese mighty landlord, who would often proudly display the honorific Portuguese title of Visconde de Pernem conferred upon the family of Porobo Dessai since 1893. During the Republic, in the 1919 election when Luis de Menezes Braganza had led the Boycott Election campaign, Vasudev Porobo Desai Deshprabhu was one of the government-backed candidates elected to the Legislative Council from the New Conquests.^12

These developments, perhaps at the behest of Purushottam Kakodkar, caused a distancing of the Nehru-loving Goans from the Congress. Murmurs began among the masses about the economic background of the Congress candidates. No doubt the party had a maximum number of freedom fighters, but most of them were also Saraswat Brahmins and quite a few landlords. Comparatively, hardly five candidates belonged to the non- Brahmin Bahujan Samaj.

Bhau Enters The Poll Fray

With tickets being given to the big Bhatkars, mine owners and pro-Portuguese elements, the disappointed political activists had started gathering around the MGP as well as the UGP. It is not true that Bhau Bandodkar, the MGP president by then, did not want to contest elections. In fact his was the first candidature announced by the party: the Lok Sabha ticket from the Panaji (North Goa) constituency.

Later on, this man, having little political ambition, compromised his own seat to strike a pre-poll alliance with the Praja Socialist Party. The Panaji Lok Sabha seat was won by Peter Alvares of the PSP. Similarly, in Sattari and Ponda, the MGP decided to support the PSP candidates. Jaisingrao Venkatrao Rane and Gajanan Raikar were elected.

Bhau and his charged cadres started choosing candidates from among the Bahujan Samaj. Most of them were unknown faces beyond their villages or constituencies. They were young or middle-aged teachers, lawyers, small traders, other professionals and even illiterate farmers, either from the middle class or lower middle class. Compared to the Congress candidates, only nine of the MGP candidates were freedom fighters: P P Shirodkar (Siolim), Shambhu Palienkar (Tivim), Narayan Naik (St Cruz), Vishwanath Lawande (St Andre), Vasant Velingkar (Madkai), Tony Fernandes (Sanguem), Dattaram Desai (Quepem), Vithal Subray Karmali (Curchorem) and Venkatesh Verenkar (Cortalim). Six among them won the election. Narayan Naik, Vishwanath Lawande, and Venkatesh Verenkar did not make it.

Similarly, an impression was created that the MGP was an anti-Brahmin party. But Bhau and his associates had chosen almost eight Saraswat Brahmins, who were progressive in their thoughts and firmly believed in the Land to the Tiller demand. Some of them were even small Bhatkars in their ancestral villages. These included Atchutrao Usgaonkar (Pale), Govind Dhume (Panaji), Vishwanath Lawande (St Andre), Mukund Shinkre (Ponda), V S Karmali (Curchorem), Ranganath Santu Kamat (Navelim), Govind Prabhu (Cuncolim) and Vishwambhar Salkar (Mormugao). Usgaonkar and Karmali among them were elected while Shinkre was elected as the South Goa MP after the Ponda seat was allotted to the PSP.

Two among them were Christians, Minguel Rodrigues (Benaulim) and Tony Fernandes (Sanguem), also a freedom fighter who was elected. The MGP had also fielded Ashraf Aga from Sattari, but he was unofficially withdrawn after the MGPPSP alliance was struck. Despite this, the popular Aga polled 29 per cent votes, next to the winner Jaisingrao Rane of the PSP, their own ally.

But the most important and unique characteristic of the MGP, unlike the Congress or the UGP, was that 19 of their total 27 candidates were from the Bahujan Samaj and 17 among them did not carry any additional label as a freedom fighter or being a Christian or a Muslim. They were common men, chosen from the masses.

In fact, the most interesting anecdote shared with me was by Adv Ramakant Khalap, who succeeded Bhau in Mandrem after his sudden death in 1973. He went to meet former MGP MLAs to seek their blessings and this is what Kashinath Shetgaonkar, the Pernem MLA in the first Assembly and an uneducated farmer, told him:

“I was ploughing my field and a jeep suddenly stopped near the bandh. Two men got down, called me, and told that Bhau Bandodkar had called me to Panaji. I had heard of Bhau but had never met him personally. Wondering why I was suddenly called, I went home, changed my clothes and sat in the jeep. When I was introduced to Bhau, he told me that I would be the MGP candidate. It was an absolute surprise to me when he told me that I would have to fight against Vaicuntrao Dempo, Goa’s mighty landlord and a mine owner. Hesitantly, I surrendered to Bhau’s insistence. Never in my life I had contested any election, even the recently held Panchayat election. But when we started moving around, I was utterly astonished with the response we were getting. And then, I was declared elected, polling almost half of the votes. Dempo could poll only one third. We had defeated the Bhatkar.”

Bhatkars Ride Over The UGP

Diametrically opposite to this was the scenario in the UGP. The Bhatkar community of Goa was rallying around the UGP by riding the wave of keeping Goa separate, preserving the Konkani language, and defeating Nehru’s Congress as well as the Hindu Bahujan Samaj. The party contested 24 seats out of 28 in Goa. No candidates were fielded in four constituencies of the New Conquests: Pernem, St Estevam, Madkai, and Shiroda.

Among these, 16 were Christians, seven Hindus and one Muslim, Shaikh Kadar (Curchorem). Also, 10 among them were upper caste Brahmins including four Hindu Bhatkars as well as seven from Chardo (Kshatriya) community including Tatoba Rane, a Hindu Khashe, from Sattari. Almost 12 among them were wealthy Bhatkars from both the religions. All the 16 constituencies of Christian-dominated Old Conquests were represented by wealthy Bhatkars from Brahmin or Chardo communities. Only four among them were freedom fighters: John M de Souza (Calangute), Shivaji Dubhashi (Bicholim), Cristovao Furtado from Chinchinim (Sanguem), and Enio Pimenta (Curtorim).

Former independent MLA and political analyst Adv Radharao Gracias tells me that it was a tradition in the 1960s and ‘70s that elections were contested by educated and rich people. The lower class Christians, especially from the Sudir community, never ever dreamt of contesting elections. Perhaps this could be the impact of the Portuguese system where only Portuguese-speaking upper class persons who could pay three times more tax than the common men (not women) were eligible to contest elections to the Portuguese Parliament, Goa Legislative Council, or the Camara Municipal.

The wealthy Bhatkars included Alvaro da Loyola Furtado, Dr Jack de Sequeira, Maurelio Furtado, Urminda Lima Leitao, Orlando Lobo, Dr Luis Proto Barbosa, Enio Pimenta, John de Souza as well as Vasudev Sarmalkar, Sadashiv Desai, Tatoba Rane, and Shivaji Dubhashi.

The UGP, till it existed, was always supported by Christians at large as well as the Brahmin Bhatkars from the Hindu community, even in the New Conquests. MGP activists like my father and some of his associates in Canacona, who were also Brahmin Bhatkars, were humiliated by other Brahmin Bhatkars who were dead against the MGP policy of Land to the Tiller.

My father and a small group who were campaigning among the illiterate farmers not to give more than one-sixth of their produce to the Bhatkar after the Land to the Tiller Act was enforced, were dubbed as ‘Latan Sabha’, as they were carrying a lantern to move from house to house. Later on, these Hindu Brahmin Bhatkars shifted to the Congress when the UGP split into the Janata Party and the Congress. Now, the majority of them are with the BJP. Politically, they opposed the merger, supported Konkani but used only Marathi even in the temple administration, where they are the Mahajans. For them, perhaps, the prime agenda was Land to the Tiller linked to the threat of merger and not the language controversy.

Communists In Disguise

The Communists in Goa, who were mainly involved in trade union activities in the port town of Vasco as well as the mining belt at that time, were also a force to reckon with, besides the Congress. Even before the MGP and the UGP came into being, they had been working among the peasants, having formed the Shetkari Paksh (Farmers’ Party).^13 However, they did not contest with their Communist symbols but came together as a political front, called Frente Popular. It was a tactical strategy since the people, especially the Christian community, were under the influence of the Church, for whom the Communists were Enemy Number One.

Though they contested only eight seats, the candidates were true stalwarts who had played a pioneering role in the freedom struggle and were working among the masses even after Goa’s independence. They were Berta Menezes Braganza (Cortalim), Gerald Pereira (Mormugao), George Vaz (Tivim), Narayan Desai (Pernem), Divakar Kakodkar (Curchorem), Chandrakant Kakodkar (Sanguem), Vithal Parab (Mandrem), and J P Braganza (St Cruz).

In spite of having a clear-cut agenda of ‘Land to the Tiller’ as well as problems of the working class of Goa, their selfless work did not get translated into votes. The party could not garner more than two per cent votes. The only ‘Comrades’ who could get a little public support were Narayan Desai in Pernem (21%) and Gerald Pereira in Mormugao (19%).

When I was working fulltime in Vasco for Naujawan Bharat Sabha and was moving from house to house in our struggle to legalise the so-called illegal houses of the working class in the port town, I heard a common tale about Gerald Pereira’s election battle in 1963. This simple but intelligent man moving on his feet throughout the constituency was invited by the people to address election meetings in their areas rather than the Frente Popular mobilising the people. He enjoyed so much overwhelming support that his victory was a foregone conclusion. The polling day, 9 December 1963, was a Monday.

The Sunday Mass held the previous day changed the whole picture overnight. Urminda Lima Leitão e Mascarenhas, a mine owner and a landlord, was elected the UGP MLA by polling 3209 votes. Comrade Pereira was pushed down to the third position, with only 1612 votes!

The Shinkre Controversy

It is not the Congress alone that faced a rebellion, but also the MGP. In fact, the party lost their leader, Janardan Shinkre, who had founded the party. He developed serious differences with Bandodkar on the issue of aligning with the PSP. Since the whole local leadership was new and PSP had expertise in electioneering as well as politically experienced workers, Bandodkar accepted the proposal made by PSP leader S M Joshi to offer them one Lok Sabha seat and four Assembly seats. In return, the PSP offered to manage MGP’s whole election campaign. Bhau sacrificed his own Lok Sabha seat to Peter Alvares from Panaji (North Goa) and brought down the proposal to two Assembly seats: Jaisingrao Rane (Sattari) and Gajanan Raikar (Ponda). Immediately, Mukund Shinkre, who was contesting the Assembly poll from Ponda, was fielded as the Lok Sabha candidate from Mormugao (South Goa).^14

MGP General Secretary Janardan Shinkre did not agree with this deal. He was also upset because Ashraf Aga was not fielded from Ponda but shifted to Sattari and then out of the fray due to the PSP candidate. In protest, he filed his nomination for Lok Sabha from Panaji, as a dummy candidate to Bhau. It meant that if Bhau withdrew, Janardan could then contest as the official MGP candidate. While Bhau was authorised by the party to decide the candidates, the B Forms of party candidates had to be issued by Shinkre. Bhau immediately moved into action, withdrew Shinkre’s powers to issue B Forms and declared on 18 November 1963 that the MGP had snapped ties with Shinkre.^15 Interestingly, as an independent candidate, Shinkre was allotted for the Lok Sabha election the symbol of ‘Two Leaves’, which later on in the Opinion Poll was the symbol for anti-merger. He forfeited his deposit by polling just 3226 votes from the whole of North Goa.

However, this last minute controversy over the alliance created a few problems for the MGP-PSP combine. The official Assembly candidates of the PSP − Rane and Raikar − had to contest as Independent candidates, on different symbols. But the alliance managed to turn the pro-merger votes in their favour and win both the seats.

The only PSP candidates who could withdraw from the fray were P P Pednekar (Siolim), Parulekar (Calangute), Shantaram Dhond (Aldona), and Namdev Haldankar (Mapusa). The other eight candidates remained on the paper as Independent candidates, polling negligible votes. They were Bhanudas Pollji (Mandrem), Vishwas Desai (Pernem), Shivaji Desai (Pale), Shantu [Satudatt] Pal (Bicholim), Pandurang Rane (Tivim), Madhu Shirodkar (St Andre), Mukund Mortu Shet (St Estevam), and Rajaram B Gaonkar (Madkai).

S M Joshi, a towering personality among the socialists in Maharashtra, not only came for the election campaign but sent his entire team to work behind the curtains for the MGP-PSP alliance.

National Leaders & Regional Media

Despite this, the MGP campaign remained a low-key affair since no Maharashtra leader, except Socialists S M Joshi, Madhu Dandavate, and Barrister Nath Pai came down for their campaign. The heart and soul of the Maharashtra Congress leaders was with the MGP, but they could not publicly identify with the party and thus stayed away from the Goa campaign.

In fact a controversy broke out in Goa when Maharashtra’s influential revenue minister Vasantrao Naik, who later became Maharashtra chief minister, came to Goa with the campaign material for the Congress but stayed at Bandodkar’s bungalow. GPCC President Purushottam Kakodkar objected to it in the party meeting, raising suspicion over the Maharashtra Congress leaders secretly supporting the MGP. Naik however dismissed it, claiming that Bandodkar was his ‘personal friend’.^16

Except for the PSP factor, the MGP as well as the UGP stressed more upon corner meetings in the localities and direct contact with the people. Goa was politically divided between the Old and the New Conquests. The MGP was pulling in crowds in the New Conquests while most of the people in the Old Conquests were fired up by the emotional speeches made, in Konkani, by the UGP leaders.

But none of these meetings were getting the publicity they deserved in the mainstream media of Goa. The Navhind Times, whose owner Vaicuntrao Dempo was the Congress candidate, had blacked out both the local parties. It was only about the Congress, Congress, and Congress, except for a few mentions of the MGP or the UGP when some political developments took place.

Similar was the case with A Vida, a Portuguese-English- Romi Konkani daily published from Margao. The owner, Bernardo Do Reis, was contesting as a Congress candidate from Navelim. His daily was filled with news of Congress meetings, detailed profiles of the Congress candidates, and a little news about the UGP or the articles written by its leaders. But not a single line covering the MGP’s election campaign.

I was always under the impression that the MGP had with it Goa’s leading Marathi daily Gomantak to publicise its views since B D Satoskar, the editor, was a strong proponent of the merger. But Gomantak had also blacked out the MGP, except when the PSP leaders from Maharashtra addressed the public rallies. Some mentions in single-column one-paragraph news reports were sometimes found, about the public meetings held by the MGP. Gomantak, owned by another mine owner, Chowgule, appears to have had a policy similar to The Navhind Times: Congress, Congress, and more Congress!

The mining lobby of Goa also made attempts to create hurdles in the MGP campaign. Bandodkar was extracting the ore and supplying it to the registered exporter, who was a mine owner. This mine owner suddenly began to delay Bandodkar’s payment, as Bhau was utilising this money for the election campaign. M S Prabhu, who was Goa’s leading insurance agent, had received Rs 40,000 as his commission. He used this towards the campaign expenses. However, at the local level, the finances were managed by the party workers from their own pocket. The MGP had no financial burden of organising the local meetings, so much was the commitment of the villagers.^17

There is one incident which Waman Radhakrishna narrates in his book. Bandodkar and Barrister Nath Pai were delayed for a meeting in a certain village in the interior Goa. It was totally dark when they reached the village road. Electricity had not reached the villages at that time. Nath Pai suggested that the meeting be cancelled since there wouldn’t be any crowd. Bhau insisted that the people would be waiting. And suddenly they saw a group of around 200 villagers coming to the main road, with chood (a torch made of coconut leaves) in their hands, to receive their leaders. Nath Pai was flabbergasted with this gesture and support. It was all happening very spontaneously. Similar was the enthusiasm in the UGP camp, especially in the Old Conquests. People were scared that they would become part of Maharashtra and that after the Portuguese had left yet another ‘foreign’ language would be imposed upon them.

The Congress, a seasoned party in electioneering, was far ahead of both these parties. They were pouring in money, getting experienced cadres from outside for election management and wide publicity. Special teams of senior journalists were brought down from Maharashtra and Delhi for select public rallies. A pageant of national leaders and union ministers was lined up in Goa to woo all kinds of crowds: Hindus, Christians, peasants, workers, migrants etc. Some of them camped in Goa till the campaign ended. The election campaign was launched by former union home minister Lal Bahadur Shastri on 11 November 1963. He came back once again to conclude the campaign in the first week of December, addressing meetings in the villages.

Congress stalwarts among them were Congress President D Sanjivayya along with Maniben Desai, former Orissa chief minister Biju Patnaik, former union ministers Jagjivan Ram, Morarji Desai, Y B Chavan, S K Patil, Rajya Sabha Deputy Chairperson Violet Alva, her husband and MP Joachim Alva, Mohan Dharia, Kerala Congress leader Dr Henry Austin Fernandes, P K Sawant etc. While each leader was pleading not to make Goa’s merger an election issue, Christian leaders like Fernandes and Alvas were asking Goans not to mix religion with politics. They were not just going to the cities but even visiting the villages, from Pernem to Salcete to Bicholim.

The most interesting among these were two meetings held in Pernem and Mandrem, from where mighty landlords like Vaicuntrao Dempo and Raoraje Deshprabhu were contesting. Sanjivayya, at a meeting held in Pernem, tried to impress the crowd claiming that Vaicuntrao Dempo has been the supporter of Congress for a long time and how his contribution to the liberation movement was praiseworthy. He also called it ‘mischievous’ to say that the Congress had betrayed the cause of socialism by giving tickets to the landlords and industrialists like Dempo.^18

There was a reason for Sanjivayya to reach to this level to convince the Pernem voters. A fortnight before this, K K Shah had been cornered by the voters when he visited Pernem and Mandrem along with the Lok Sabha and Assembly candidates to meet his party workers. Hearing the news, around a thousand Pednekars gathered at the meeting venue and Shah had no other option but to reply to their blunt questions, in Pernem as well as in Mandrem:

How is it that you have given tickets to landlords and capitalists when your profession is that you are working for the poor?

Shah : We adopted such people as candidates in India, also in other states. But we got them bound to our principles and programme. We told them that they must subscribe to tenancy legislation and other legislation which sought to ameliorate the conditions of workers in factories. That is the way Congress wants to bring in the Socialist pattern by stages.

T V Parvate : Deshprabhu and Dempo are wedded to the Congress programme which stands for improving the standard of life of the peasants and workers. In fact Deshprabhu has already granted reasonable rent and security to the peasants, even before Congress brought this legislation.

Dempo : I stand by the programme of the Congress to work for Socialism and to satisfy people’s basic necessities like food, clothing and shelter. I will personally work for it.

Deshprabhu : I have nothing new to tell you. You should take into consideration the services of the Congress to India during the last 75 years and particularly during the last 16 years and decide for yourselves that under Congress rule you would be happy.^19

Neither Dempo nor Deshprabhu stood by the socialist programme of the Congress. In fact, even after the Tenancy and Mundkar Acts were enforced during the MGP regime, over three-fourth of Pernem and its villages still belong to the Deshprabhus. I am told that the tenants still give Khand to the mighty Bhatkar and a receipt is issued to them. The reason is simple. To extend the existing house or to build a new house, the common Pednekar needs to obtain an NOC from the landowner, just as the Sattari people need to do with the land belonging to the Khashe or the Government. The whole land of Pernem still belongs to the Bhatkars even after 60 years of Goa’s independence. They have sold it to the North Indian hoteliers in the coastal belt, and our own Goan politicians have bought land around the proposed Mopa airport.

Coming back to the campaign of 1963, it was a sheer coincidence that when Sanjivayya was facing flak from the farmers of Pernem due to Dempo and Deshprabhu’s candidatures, Maharashtra-based Congress leader Yeshwantrao Chavan was greeted by the farmers in areas like Bicholim and other places. He was the icon of Goan farmers due to the revolutionary land reforms he had enforced as the first CM of Maharashtra. He was blunt enough to accept the factual position and provide practical solutions to the voters. ln his first rally in Vasco he said:

“I liken the Goa election to the churning of the sea by the Gods and the Demons. Just as from that churning emerged the 14 precious jewels including the world-consuming poison, some less vitriolic poison may emerge from this election also. But just as Shankar was found to arrest its spread, the Congress can scotch this poison too.”

Whether in Vasco or Panaji, Chavan had to face slogans on the merger issue. But in Bicholim, thousands of people welcomed him by shouting pro-merger slogans. In response, he told the crowd that if and when Goa had to be merged, it would only be in Maharashtra. But the time is not now, you are not going to have a referendum on that point in this election, he said.

Chavan argued the case of ‘Why Congress’ in his own style. He felt the Congress should be elected to power with a clear majority to foil the demand of a separate State by the United Goans Party. They are not only Christians but also have ‘some Hindus’ with them, he said. According to him, a separate state at this juncture was a dangerous move. In his Panaji rally, he had termed it as an attempt to create a ‘Black Portugal’. He had also assured them full freedom to practice their western culture, music, clothing, food and way of life.

But the real master stroke was what he said in Bicholim, tilting his argument in favour of the MGP:

“I have heard it said that Congress must be returned to power in order to avail of central aid for development. I am against this spirit of bargaining. Development funds for Goa will be there even if it continues to be a Union Territory directly governed by the Centre or even if, in this election, the Congress government does not come to power…”^20

The impact of Chavan’s visit was so much that Shah finally took the mergerists head on at a meeting in Calangute, a day before the polling. He reached Calangute at around 7 pm, when a meeting of the mergerists was going on, while his meeting was scheduled 15 minutes later. The mergerists asked him to address the same meeting as a friendly gesture and Shah jumped at it. (The newspaper report does not state if it was the MGP meeting). While justifying the stand taken by the Congress on maintaining Goa as the Union Territory and assuring Rs 100 Crore for its development if Congress is brought to power, he asked the audience:

“Whose advice are you going to take? Mr Yeshwantrao Chavan’s or Mr Dayanand Bandodkar’s"?

The Navhind Times, who published this incident with this question itself as a headline, reported that the audience shouted: “Of course, Mr Chavan!”

Congress Routed, MGP-UGP Rise

And then came D-Day, 9 December 1963, to decide on Chavan or Bandodkar. The response was much more than the Panchayat elections. Over 75 per cent Goans exercised their franchise all across Goa, with women outnumbering men as voters. Long queues were witnessed practically at every booth and Lt Governor Mulk Raj Sachdev personally monitored the election by visiting the polling booths all around Goa.

The counting began three days later, on 12 December, and ended the next day. By midnight, 15 results were declared, spreading a wave of panic in the Congress camp and making the UGP jubilant. The Congress had not won a single seat in Goa, except one in Daman. The UGP had won nine seats, the MGP took four, and one by an independent in Diu. Dr Jack de Sequeira was the first victor announced in the history of Goa’s first democratic election. In a close encounter, he had defeated MGP candidate Govind Dhume by 414 votes and polled 42 per cent votes. Congress candidate Alvaro Pereira could somehow manage to save his deposit but could not garner more than 21 per cent votes.

This was the scenario at all the 13 seats of which results were declared. Almost nine Congressmen among them had forfeited their deposits. Except in Mandrem and St Andre, Congress was pushed to the third position in all other constituencies. Eminent freedom fighters like Shankar Sardesai (St Estevam, 641 votes) and Ravindra Kelekar (Madgao, 1113 votes) lost miserably, besides A Vida owner Bernardo do Reis (Navelim, 750 votes) and Irene Barros (Benaulim, 1711 votes). The only person who lost honourably was Vishwanath Lawande (St Andre), in a close fight, by 112 votes.

The UGP winners were Dr Jack Sequeira (Panaji), Dr Álvaro Loyola dá Furtado (Navelim), Joaquim Arauzo (St Cruz), Vasudev Sarmalkar (Madgao), Maurelio Furtado (Benaulim), Teotónio Pereira (St Andre), Sebastiao Mazarelo (Cuncolim), Enio Pimenta (Curtorim) and John M D’Souza (Calangute).

But it was not a disappointment for the MGP camp at all. In fact, on the first day itself, the party of the Bahujan Samaj had created history in Goa’s electoral politics. In two constituencies of Pernem taluka, three mighty landlords were defeated miserably by two common men. Vaicuntrao Sinai Dempo (Congress), the landlord and Goa’s leading mine owner, lost by polling only one third of votes (1912) while Kashinath Shetgaonkar, an illiterate farmer, polled half of the votes (3185). Similarly, Raoraje Deshprabhu, the Visconde de Pernem, was pushed down to the third position. He could not manage to get more than 14 per cent votes (1410). Sadhashiv Desai (UGP), another landlord, also could not garner more than 15 per cent votes (1536). Vijay Kamulkar, a teacher, won with a huge margin of over 5000 votes, by polling 65 per cent votes (6663). Indian democracy had shown its real shining colours!

Besides these, MGP’s leader P P Shirodkar (Siolim) and Dattaram Chopdekar (St Estevam) were also declared victorious. The next day brought shame to the Congress. The MGP became the first ruling party of Goa and the UGP became the prime opposition. The Congress could not win a single seat. The UGP won three more, taking its tally to 12. The MGP-PSP swept the poll, adding 12 more seats to its kitty. With 16 seats out of 30, the Lion was all set to rule Goa, Daman and Diu. The UGP got all its 12 seats from the Old Conquests (15 seats). Besides winning all the 13 seats in the New Conquests, the MGP-PSP combine also won three seats from Bardez: Siolim, Tivim and Mapusa.

All the dreams of the Congress were shattered. The only respite was one seat, that too from Daman, which was won by Kalidas Patel (7237) in a straight fight by polling 81 per cent votes. The whole ‘secret exercise’ of distributing cabinet berths amongst themselves had gone in vain. Forget winning a seat, nearly two third of their 28 candidates in Goa, 19 to be precise, lost their deposits. The politics of embracing royal landlords and mine owners had boomeranged royally. The pan-India formula of ‘accommodative politics’ of the Congress had proved to be a big flop in Goa, which Nehru had once called a pimple on the face of India!

Source: Election Commission of India

The Diu seat was won by an independent, Mamadali Ravji (1745), by defeating the Congress-supported Independent Puspasen Wandas (1373). Interestingly, the battle in Diu was between four independents, without a single party officially contesting there. In a four-cornered fight, Mamadali became the MLA by polling only 33 per cent votes. The other two Independents Ramji Anjani and Gokal Patel polled 1317 and 844 votes respectively.

The additional 10 seats won by the MGP on the second day were Raghunath Tople (Mapusa), Shambhu Palienkar (Tivim), Kusumakar Kadkade (Bicholim), Atchut Usgaonkar (Pale), Vasant Velingkar (Madkai), Pundalik Sagun Naik (Shiroda), Tony Fernandes (Sanguem), Ganaba Desai (Canacona), Dattaram Desai (Quepem) and Vithal Subray Karmali (Curchorem).

The UGP won three more seats: Orlando Lobo (Aldona), Dr Luis Proto Barbosa (Cortalim) and Urminda Lima Leitao Mascarenhas (Mormugao).

The MGP-PSP combine had also won both the Lok Sabha seats. Peter Alvares (53%) of the PSP had defeated the sitting MP and one of the most eminent freedom fighters Dr Pundalik Gaitonde (16%) of the Congress as well as Umakant Surlakar (29%) of the UGP. Janardan Shinkre, who had revolted against Bhau, polled only 3226 votes − three per cent!

Mukund Shinkre (39%), who was shifted for the Lok Sabha contest at the last minute due to a tie-up with the PSP was also declared victorious in a tough battle against A D Loyola Furtado (36%) of the UGP. The margin was just 3000 votes. Eminent freedom fighter Laura D’Souza (18%) of the Congress was pushed to third position. This was the first and last victory for the MGP from South Goa. The seat was then won by the UGP, Congress, and even the BJP, but never again by the MGP.

The Winners & The Losers

The winners of the MGP in the Assembly poll included two Saraswat Brahmins: Atchut Usgaonkar (Pale) and Vithal Subray alias ViSu Karmali (Curchorem), one Christian - Tony Fernandes (Sanguem), and the rest belonging to the non-Brahmin Bahujan Samaj. Though Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru later claimed that the election had taken place on religious lines, the MGP winners belonged to all the three sections, including progressiveminded Brahmins who supported land reforms. In fact, Tony Fernandes was elected from Sanguem, where the Christian population was just 25 per cent. He polled 58 per cent votes.

The UGP established its mark in the Old Conquests. The ‘Party of Christians and Hindu Brahmins’ won 12 seats of Calangute, Aldona, Panaji, St Cruz, St Andre, Cuncolim, Benaulim, Navelim, Margao, Curtorim, Cortalim, and Mormugao.

Except for Teotonio Pereira, the Mapusa-based bus operator belonging to the Sudir caste, all other 11 MLAs of the UGP belonged to either Bamonn or Chardo castes, nine of whom were also wealthy Bhatkars, including Vasudev Sarmalkar from Margao. In a bastion of Hindu and Christian Brahmins, Vasudevbab polled 51 per cent votes.

1963: GOA ASSEMBLY POLL

PARTY | CANDIDATES | VOTES
MGP-PSP | 29 | 119788
UGP | 24 | 74081
Cong | 29 | 41727
Frente Popular | 8 | 4589
PSP ‘Independents’ | 8 | 410
Other Independents | 51 | 16603
TOTAL | | 257198

Note:

MGP candidates include Ashraf Aga (Sattari) & Mukund Shinkre (Ponda), who were withdrawn later in support of PSP candidates Jaisingrao Rane (Sattari) & Gajanan Raikar (Ponda). MGP did not field candidates in Curtorim. Also in Daman & Diu.
UGP did not contest Pernem, Shiroda, Madkai and St Estevam seats in Goa as well as Daman and Diu.
The 8 PSP Independents means those who officially did not withdraw but were not given party forms, publicly withdrawn from the fray and remained on the ballot paper as Independents.

Participation in the freedom struggle was also an important criteria laid down by all the parties while choosing their candidates. Altogether 39 freedom fighters had entered the fray from five different parties. From among them, 10 were elected to the first Assembly of Goa and two among them also became ministers in the first MGP government.

Among them, a maximum number of 18 freedom fighters were fielded by the Congress and six equally towering personalities had entered the fray from Frente Popular. All 24 of them had played an inspirational role to win the ‘Battle of Independence’, but they lost the ‘Battle of Democracy’, along with all other candidates of their parties. However, the MGP could get six freedom fighters elected out of the nine fielded by the party. Both the PSP MLAs were freedom fighters too. A total of eight out of 16. Two among these, Fernandes and Karmali also became ministers.

The UGP had also fielded four freedom fighters. Among them, only John M D’Souza (Calangute) and Enio Pimenta (Curtorim) could make it to the Assembly. The other two, Shivaji Dubhashi (Bicholim) and Cristovao Furtado (Sanguem) lost the battle to the MGP.^21

The entire battle was fought neither on Hindu-Christian religious lines nor on Brahmin versus Bahujan Samaj caste lines as it appeared to have been projected all these years. There were freedom fighters elected from all the parties including the UGP, which was allegedly termed as pro-Portuguese by their opponents. On the other hand, the most prominent freedom fighters from the Congress and the Frente Popular were defeated.

There were Christian MLAs elected from Hindu-dominated areas like Tony Fernandes (MGP) from Sanguem and Dr Jack de Sequeira (UGP) from Panaji. In fact the main battle in Sanguem was between two Christians. There were Brahmins elected from constituencies that had a negligible presence of upper castes, as in Atchut Usgaonkar’s case in Pale. Eminent freedom fighters like Dr Ram Hegde, in a straight fight, had lost to a common man like Pundalik Sagun Naik. He polled 74 per cent votes. And the startling outcome in the remote areas like Pernem and Mandrem was that the farming community had taught a lifetime lesson to the mighty landlords and mine owners that electoral literacy had nothing to do with educational illiteracy. It was truly a revolutionary battle that was won in this so-called ‘backward’ border taluka of North Goa.

Through this fierce battle on economic lines and Goan identity, the new battleground emerged. The first Goa Assembly had some Bhatkars and some Kull and Mundkars. There were Brahmins and upper caste Chardos with Bhatkar mentality as well as some having a progressive outlook for land reforms.

There were also professionals like lawyers, doctors, teachers, small traders, and even farmers. A perfect combination of crosssections of the society to run the first ever democratically elected Assembly of Goa!

The core component of the first ever democratic battle of Goa was: The Ownership of Land!

A Vida; 4 October 1963↩︎

Loyola Furtado A De; A Vida 20 October 1963↩︎

गोमंतक; 4 ऑक्टोबर 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; 3 October 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; 19 October 1963↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा, पान 18↩︎

Shirodkar Dr P P; Who’s Who of Freedom Fighters↩︎

The Navhind Times; 31 October 1963↩︎

गोमंतक; संपादकीय 5 नोव्हेंबर 1963↩︎

Pais e Martins Sharmila; The Encounter with the Ballot in Colonial Goa (1821-1961) P 314↩︎

The House of Dempo website (https://www]:dempos]:com/kalpavriksha-family/)↩︎

Pais e Martins Sharmila; The Encounter with the Ballot in↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा, पान 18↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा, पान 23↩︎

गोमंतक; 19 नोव्हेंबर 1963↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा, पान 23↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; महाराष्ट्रवादी गोमंतक, स्थापना आणि वाटचाल, पान 25↩︎

The Navhind Times; 5 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; 23 November 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times; 6 November 1963↩︎

Shirodkar Dr P P; Who’s Who of Freedom Fighters↩︎

Chapter 11

BEGINS THE BAHUJAN ERA

12 December 1963. Bhausaheb Bandodkar was nowhere in the forefront while the MGP and UGP camps were rejoicing over their victories in Goa. He was not even in Goa. He was resting at his Dadar flat in Bombay and listening to the news on Goa’s election on the radio, in the company of Jayantrao Tilak, Shashikant Narvekar, Ramdas Prabhugaonkar, Principal Venkatesh Narayan Naik and others. Overjoyed with the unexpected result, Bhau said:

“Now we have to think about who will be the Chief Minister.”

“No need to think. You will be the Chief Minister of Goa,” replied Jayantrao Tilak.

Bhau was dumbfounded on hearing this. The others instantly supported Tilak’s words.

“How is that possible? I am not even elected,” said Bandodkar.

Bhau was then told that the Constitution of India allows any Indian citizen to become a chief minister or minister, provided he or she gets elected within six months, for which one legislator would have to step down to create a vacancy for a by-election.^1 Bhau was not convinced. He went to meet his friend Vasantrao Naik, who by then had become the CM of Maharashtra. He too echoed the same opinion, adding to Bhau’s confusion. Meanwhile, Nath Pai in Delhi met Prime Minister Pandit Nehru, Defence Minister Y B Chavan and Union Home Minister Gulzarilal Nanda, conveying to them that the people of Goa had voted in favour of Goa’s merger.

The next day was a very hectic one in Goa as well as in Bombay. Nath Pai immediately flew down to Bombay, met other leaders like Madhu Dandavate along with Bandodkar and also spoke to the media. Bandodkar, as the MGP President, told the media that he would be happy if Goa was immediately merged into Maharashtra. However, since it would not happen immediately, the MGP would not shirk from its responsibility to form the government in Goa. The leader would be elected in Goa by evening. Nath Pai announced that the MGP government would have a three-member cabinet.

Bhau also gave financial justification as to why Goa should not continue as a Union Territory. According to him, the central government would be spending four crore rupees on the administration of an area with a population of only six lakhs. Contrary to this, Ratnagiri district in the Konkan, which was three times more populated than Goa, was managed with only Rs 50 lakhs.^2

Immediately both of them, along with Shivraj Patil, flew down to Goa to address a public rally to celebrate the victory in Panaji. Around 10,000 people had gathered late evening, with a huge participation of women. South Goa MP Mukund Shinkre said at the rally that the MGP victory had strengthened the hands of Pandit Nehru. Tony Fernandes said the results had proved that the MGP was not a communal party. He was elected from Hindu-dominated Sanguem, Shinkre from the Christian-dominated South and Peter Alvares from Hindu-dominated North Goa. Late at night, the MGP legislature party elected Bandodkar as their leader, to take over as Goa’s first chief minister.^3

There are two different tales of how Bhau’s name was proposed in the first legislature party meeting held to elect the leader. One tale claims that Shambhu Palienkar proposed that P P Shirodkar be elected the leader and made the chief minister. Kusumakar Kadkade seconded it. At this juncture, Nath Pai entered the room and proposed that Bandodkar be made the CM, informing them of what had been discussed in Bombay.

The second tale is more significant. According to M S Prabhu, Mukund Shinkre was supposed to propose Bandodkar’s name. As he remained quiet, Prabhu himself proposed Bandodkar’s name. He opposed Shirodkar becoming the CM, as the MGP needed a non-controversial leader. Shirodkar had made a public statement that if the MGP came to power, women from Saraswat Brahmin families would have to wash utensils at the houses of the Bahujan Samaj. Shirodkar denied this story, as well as making such a public statement. What is more significant is that at that moment, the MGP did not want to antagonise the Saraswat Brahmin community but wanted to take everybody together.^4

The media was later told that Bhau was elected the leader unanimously, with P P Shirodkar proposing his name. The meeting was presided over by Nath Pai. Technically, it was a hung Assembly since the largest single party − the MGP − had only 14 seats in the 30-member House. But besides the twomember PSP who had a pre-poll alliance with the MGP, the MLAs of Daman and Diu were also supporting the MGP, raising the strength to 18. Kalidas Patel, Daman MLA of Congress, wanted his region to be merged into Surat district while Mamadali Ravji, Independent MLA of Diu, wanted to merge with Saurashtra.^5

The Bahujan Formula

The MGP also announced a six-point agenda for governance. ‘Land to the Tiller’ was the topmost priority:

To give relief to the tenants and mundkars by introducing, as soon as possible, the tenancy and similar agrarian legislations
To provide as many medical amenities as possible particularly in the rural areas
To provide better road communications, particularly in the rural areas
To ensure that the Gram Panchayats function effectively and efficiently
To remove all possible obstructions in the way of the Gram Panchayats
To rehabilitate the political sufferers as fast as possible.^6

Bhau, along with Tony Fernandes and ViSu Karmali, were sworn in on 20 December, the day after the third anniversary of Goa’s Liberation. Vice President Dr Zakir Hussain specially flew down from Delhi to preside over the swearing-in ceremony at the Raj Bhavan. Bhau’s three-member cabinet with a Christian and a Brahmin corresponded with his firm belief which he had expressed while founding the party. There was to be no antagonism towards any caste or religion, including the upper caste, but there would be no compromise on land reforms. He had replicated the Bahujan formula which Y B Chavan had followed in Maharashtra.

Bhau’s next cabinet in 1967, after the Opinion Poll, was also three plus one. Besides Bhau, freedom fighter Anthony D’Souza and educationist Gopalrao Mayekar were the cabinet ministers. Atchutrao Usgaonkar was made the minister of state. This was the moment when ViSu Karmali went into depression, as he felt Bhau had not reposed similar trust in him, and committed suicide at a Bombay guest house on 2 September 1967. K B Naik entered here as the leader of the majority Bhandari Samaj by getting elected at the by-election to fill Karmali’s seat. Later, he led a revolt against Bhau when both D’Souza and Mayekar resigned from the ministry. Bhau’s third ministry in 1972 included Atchutrao Usgaonkar and Pratapsingh Rane as the cabinet ministers and Shashikala Kakodkar as the minister of state.

A little before his sudden demise in 1973, Bhau had finalised the plan to merge the MGP into Congress. Uma Shankar Dixit, the influential union minister in the Indira government, had succeeded in mediating the merger. He had agreed to all the three major conditions laid down by Bandodkar, based on his Bahujan Formula: 1) Elections of the Congress party would be held as per the advice of Bandodkar; 2) Maximum candidates of the Congress should come from the Bahujan Samaj; and 3) Christians must have representation in the cabinet.^7

Later on Shashikala-tai, when she took over the reins after Bhau’s demise, continued with the formula. And it was also followed by Pratapsingh Rane later as the Congress chief minister. The Bahujan formula continues to be followed in Goa till date, no matter which party forms the government − the MGP, the Congress, the BJP or any splinter groups of defectors.

Perhaps this is also another reason why the BJP did not go ahead with hard Hindutva in Goa, and then even soft Hindutva got converted to “appeasing the minorities”.

The Congress could come to power only when the party adopted the Bahujan formula with the MGP and UGP leaders shaking hands under one umbrella. With this formula, the Congress ruled for a decade uninterruptedly till 1990. And precisely because of this formula, it continues to be the prime political force even after defections have become the order of the day. The BJP too could come to power only when it had conquered the hearts of the Christians, besides the Hindu Bahujan Samaj.

Riding on the wave of the Babri Masjid-Ram Janmabhoomi issue, when in 1994 the BJP made its debut in the Assembly with four MLAs, it had given a ticket to only Anthony Fernandes in Cortalim out of the total 12 seats they contested in alliance with the MGP. When the saffron brigade went alone in 1999, the representation to the minorities rose to four: Socorro Fernandes (St Cruz), Anthony Fernandes (Cortalim), Julio D’Silva (Cuncolim) and Shaikh Jina (Navelim) among its 39 candidates. None of them got elected in either of these elections, but the Hindutva party was compelled to follow the Bahujan formula: Hindus and Christians including the Brahmins. In fact, in 1994 itself, BJP’s four MLAs included two Saraswats − Manohar Parrikar and Digambar Kamat.

By the 2002 election, the BJP had replaced Soft Hindutva with Good Governance by increasing the minority representation to nine, with Francisco D’Souza among them getting elected from Mapusa. The other candidates were Tony Rodrigues (Taleigao), Shaikh Hassan Haroon (Mormugao), Anthony Vaz (Cortalim), Jose Pinheiro (Loutolim), Laxmi Gonsalves (Benaulim), Julio D’Silva (Cuncolim) and Shaikh Jina (Navelim). In addition, the party also supported Filipe Neri Rodrigues (Velim) to get elected as an Independent MLA.

In the 2007 election, Francisco D’Souza was re-elected while other candidates from among the 33 the BJP fielded were Agnelo Silveira (Taleigao), Antonio Caido (St Andre) and Milagres Gonsalves (Cuncolim).

The real turning point however was the 2012 election.

The Church unofficially supported the BJP to teach a lifetime lesson to the corrupt and opportunist Congress, which had been taking the Christians for granted. The BJP rose to 21 from among its 28 candidates, out of which six were Christians: Francisco D’Souza (Mapusa), Michael Lobo (Calangute), Glenn Ticlo (Aldona), Carlos Almeida (Vasco), Matanhy Saldanha (Cortalim) and Nilesh Cabral (Curchorem). The party also supported the Goa Vikas Party, electing Mickky Pacheco (Nuvem) and Caitu Silva (Benaulim) as the MLAs. GVP’s third candidate Joseph Gonsalves (Quepem) lost. In addition, the Hindutva party also got two independents elected from the minorities: Avertano Furtado (Navelim) and Benjamin Silva (Velim).

The trend continued in 2017 election when BJP’s 13 MLAs included seven Christians, a majority of minorities: Francisco D’Souza (Mapusa), Michael Lobo (Calangute), Glenn Ticlo (Aldona), Carlos Almeida (Vasco), Mauvin Godinho (Dabolim), Alina Saldanha (Cortalim) and Nilesh Cabral (Curchorem). The party candidate Arthur D’Silva (Curtorim) and the independent Avertano Furtado (Navelim) did not win.

Today, after engineering a series of defections to make the BJP government ‘stable’, out of 27, more than half − 15 − are Christian MLAs.

Whether it is a government formed by popular mandate, a coalition government with other parties, or a defectors’ government, no political group can escape this Bahujan formula. Perhaps this is the reason caste or religion does not become an issue for a voter while electing the candidate, provided the societal balance is maintained in the government formation. However, this balance is getting wobbly nowadays when governments are either formed in a hung Assembly or alternate governments are formed through defections. Parrikar sailed comfortably through his 2012 victory. Out of 21, he had six legislators from the majority Bhandari community, seven Christians, Marathas, Shet, Tribals, and himself a Saraswat Brahmin. Francis D’Souza was the deputy chief minister.

Alliance partner Sudin Dhavalikar was in the third position. Four ministers were Bhandaris − Dayanand Mandrekar, Mahadev Naik, Dilip Parulekar and Milind Naik. Avertano Furtado and Alina Saldanha were also in the cabinet, besides tribal minister Ramesh Tavadkar and Rajendra Arlekar elected from an SC constituency sitting in the Speaker’s chair.

This whole combination tumbled when in the 2017 election, the BJP slipped down to 13. All the Bhandaris lost except for Milind Naik. Tawadkar and Arlekar also lost, and the Christians MLAs became a majority. On roping in the MGP, Goa Forward Party and the Independents to form the government, the Parrikar cabinet became dominated by Saraswat Brahmins and Christians. BJP minister Babu Azgaonkar, who later split from the MGP with his colleague Deepak Prabhu Pauskar, made a public statement that he was proud that his government was being guided by learned Saraswat Brahmins: Parrikar as CM, Sudin Dhavalikar of the MGP and Vijai Sardesai of the Goa Forward as the deputy CMs and independent Rohan Khanute as an equally influential minister.

This opportunistic formula angered the Bhandari Samaj, through which emerged a new executive committee through the most controversial election of the Gomantak Bhandari Samaj.

After the organisational election, senior BJP leader and ex-MLA Dayanand Mandrekar blessed the new committee, wishing them “good luck in what they have planned”. Meanwhile, after Parrikar’s demise, Dr Pramod Sawant took over, dropped the Goa Forward Party members, Rohan Khaunte as well as MGP leader Sudin Dhavalikar from the cabinet. The other two MGP members crossed over to the BJP. On the other hand, 10 more members of the Congress also crossed over to the BJP. Babu Kavlekar hailing from the Dhangar community and Babu Azgaonkar from the SC community became the deputy CMs under ‘Maratha’ CM Dr Sawant. He proudly started making public statements that his was truly a Bahujan Samaj government.

But this did not stop the Gomantak Bhandari Samaj from going ahead with its political agenda. The GBS has now publicly admitted its political intention. Its president Ashok Naik has categorically stated that they would support any party that would field maximum candidates from their community and make a Bhandari the CM. Falling prey to this casteist politics, AAP national Convener Arvind Kejriwal has announced that they would have a Bhandari Chief Minister and a Christian Deputy CM. The TMC also followed suit by splitting the Goa Forward Party and bringing Kiran Kandolkar and his wife into Didi’s camp. The Congress on the other hand is in a quandary since the parties it plans to align with are headed by upper caste Brahmins, may they be from the MGP or the Goa Forward Party. In that sense, Poll 2022 is a testing time for Goan politics.

We need to see if the Goan voters get into ‘national integration mode’ by embracing caste politics promoted by national parties during polling or prefer the Bahujan Formula devised by Bhausaheb Bandodkar of giving equal representation to Goan society while governing the state.

Bhau Loves Panditji

In the first election, the MGP did not have a separate manifesto. The Congress manifesto was the same as the MGP manifesto, except for its stand on the immediate merger of Goa into Maharashtra. After the MGP victory, the PSP leaders from Maharashtra began to press for Goa’s immediate merger.

Socialist leaders including S M Joshi and N G Goray came down heavily on the Congress, calling the party opportunistic and saying the Goa verdict was a lesson not to encourage factional elements like the UGP.^8 Joining the chorus was the seniormost and most respectable Congress leader C Rajgopalachari. In the periodical Swarajya he edited, Rajaji hit out at Pandit Nehru, alleging that he wanted to keep Goa as ‘streedhan’ for New Delhi. Rajaji wanted Pondicherry to merge with Madras and Goa with Maharashtra.^9

Nehru dismissed their claim that the Goa verdict was a verdict for the merger. He countered it by alleging that the MGP had won the election by creating a communal divide. Former Union minister S K Patil, originally from Kudal in Konkan, was the only Congress leader justifying Nehru’s stand. He argued that it was an election to elect the government and not a plebiscite to decide the merger issue. He even went a step ahead and said that the Centre would hold a plebiscite to decide the issue of Goa’s identity, but after 10 years.^10

Though Bandodkar was guided throughout this phase by the PSP leaders and especially Nath Pai, the elected MGP MPs and MLAs had taken an altogether divergent stand on PSP’s attack on the Congress. Soon after the election results, the party had two victory rallies, in Margao and then in Panaji on 13 December. In both the meetings, MGP MP Mukund Shinkre, Sanguem MLA Tony Fernandes and Bandodkar himself claimed that the MGP victory meant the strengthening of the hands of Pandit Nehru at the Centre.^11 After taking over as the legislature party leader to sit on the throne, Bandodkar had a lengthy press conference on 17 December. Rather than attacking Nehru on his allegations of communal divide, Bandodkar said he was deeply pained with Nehru’s remark and suggested that he should find out what the reality actually was.

“I don’t feel this is a defeat of the Indian National Congress, the organisation which we all love. It is a defeat of the narrow minded leadership which had taken control of elections in Goa on behalf of the Congress… The Congress would have easily won the elections if it had remained in tune with the urges and aspirations of the people…. I would very humbly urge Panditji to analyse the cause of the Congress defeat scientifically… The success of the MGP is the success of the Congress ideals. It is a success of the people who had remained oppressed and suppressed for centuries and who are awakening themselves, thanks to the untiring efforts of our beloved Prime Minister.”^12

More surprising than this was the stand Bhau took on the issue of immediate merger of Goa. After taking over as the chief minister, on the eve of Christmas, Bhau announced that he would not press for immediate merger of Goa into Maharashtra since he didn’t want to impose the merger on anybody. He also clarified that liquor prohibition would not be enforced in Goa and that land reforms would not be brought in hastily, but only after discussing the Land Reforms Commission’s report in the Assembly.^13 The very next day, at a press conference held in Bombay, PM Nehru welcomed Bandodkar’s statement on the merger:

“It was true that those who were elected did not differ much from the Congress and he was glad that the Chief Minister Mr Bandodkar had decided not to raise the issue of merger for the time being, he said…. There was a considerable section of Roman Catholics there. They feared that their religion would be endangered. That fear would vanish in the course of time. There would be no harm if the decision about the future of Goa was taken after some time but it would certainly cause harm if it was taken immediately, he said. Mr. Nehru said he was glad that the elected representatives were following this policy.”^14

After personally meeting PM Nehru in Bombay, Bandodkar told the media in the national capital that all the misunderstandings between them have been resolved. The PM was misguided by the opposition about voting on communal lines. He also said their topmost priority would be to introduce land reforms in Goa and not an immediate merger.

“We are in a position to pass a resolution right now to merge Goa immediately into Maharashtra. But ultimately it is the Centre that needs to take the necessary steps to make it happen. We would try to canvas our case with the legislators, members of Parliament and others.”^15

Bandodkar’s strategy of one step backward irked the two legislators of the PSP. They resolved to resign as the MLAs and push the Bandodkar government into minority. Now it was time for the top PSP leaders to step in. North Goa MP Peter Alvares as well as PSP supremo S M Joshi requested their party legislators to withdraw their decision, stating that the Socialist party would not take any such step that would make the Opposition forces stronger in the Goa Assembly. The MGP fully supported Bhau’s decision.^16 Joshi flew down to Goa to resolve the deadlock.^17

The issue also erupted once again in the first Assembly session held for six days from 13 January. Since then the Konkani versus Marathi and merger versus anti-merger have become chronic issues in the Goa Assembly.

Bhau Faces Mistrust And Rebellion

The first Assembly lasted roughly for three years, from December 1963 to 1966. It was dissolved prematurely to hold the Opinion Poll on the merger issue. But it was not smooth sailing for Bhausaheb Bandodkar. He faced three no confidence motions, two from the opposition and one from his own party colleagues. The first two were moved by the UGP and were defeated on 24 July 1964 and 25 March 1965 by 16 against 12. In fact Leader of Opposition Dr Jack de Sequeira wanted to withdraw his first motion after discussion. The ruling MGP pressed for it and the Speaker also rejected the opposition leader’s demand.^18

But the third motion, moved by two MGP legislators, would have resulted in the collapse of the Bandodkar government, if the two-month long internal party battle had not been resolved amicably. Even the Congress and PSP leaders from Maharashtra and Delhi had to intervene. It began on 4 September and was resolved on 10 November, one day before the no-trust motion came up for voting in the Assembly. The MGP legislators were on a warpath when India was involved in a war against Pakistan.

In 1990, when Speaker Dr Luis Proto Barbosa led a rebellion and toppled Pratapsingh Rane’s Congress government, the Supreme Court finally ruled that the Speaker could not be a part of toppling activity. Dr Barbosa was accordingly disqualified as the MLA. But Dr Barbosa was not the first such case. The foundation was laid down by Goa’s first Speaker P P Shirodkar, who was earlier tipped to be the CM. He was actively collaborating with the rebel group against Bandodkar, even within the party forum. He had three MGP MLAs on his side: Shambhu Palienkar (Tivim), Dattaram Desai (Quepem), and Dattaram Chopdekar (St Estevam). In the party organisation, they were supported by vice president Vishwanath Lawande, Narayan Naik, M S Prabhu, Vithal Bablo Naik and Zotico D’Souza.

Jaisinghrao V Rane and Gajanar Raikar, the PSP MLAs, had opposed the no-trust motion, alleging that the hidden motive behind the motion was that the rebels wanted to become ministers.^19 Maharashtra Chief Minister Vasantrao Naik and home minister D S Desai of the Congress as well as PSP MP Nath Pai tried their best to bring peace. But both sides were adamant. Finally Bhau had to surrender to a compromise formula by dissolving the 25-member executive committee of the party and not holding both the posts − party president and chief minister. This was the outcome of a series of meetings in Goa and Bombay, proposals and counter-proposals as well as open threats and challenges. The internal battle turned into open mudslinging. As a result, the UGP decided to support the motion and the Congress also started reorganising itself, predicting mid-term polls.

The no confidence motion moved by two MGP MLAs − Dattaram Desai and Shambhu Palienkar – made nine serious charges against Bhau: 1) The CM was behaving like an autocratic despot and had called only two meetings of the MGP executive committee; 2) Not having legislature party meetings, and reducing party legislators to rubber stamps; 3) Not respecting MLAs and insulting and ridiculing them in front of civil servants; 4) Actively supporting a magazine Janagarjana, whose editor N B N Gaonkar was imprisoned for breach of privilege of the Assembly; 5) Remaining continuously absent from the Assembly on flimsy and false grounds, 6) Complete lack of sympathy for freedom fighters; 7) Making statements against the Co-operative movement and Panchayati Raj; 8) Interfering in the portfolios of other ministers and antagonising the bureaucrats; and 9) Bandodkar was a complete reactionary who wanted to safeguard only the vested interests of mine owners, capitalists, big businessmen and landlords, against the poor, downtrodden and exploited masses.^20

The UGP had also filed another motion, listing out the failures of the Bandodkar government in rice procurement and supply, resolving the grievances of government servants, sending back deputationists, and running an efficient administration. The opposition had also made a serious charge of misusing the government machinery for intimidating political opponents, with an open charge that dissident MLA Dattaram Chopdekar’s house had been searched.

This reminds one of similar accusations made against the BJP chief minister Manohar Parrikar by the opposition, his party colleagues, and even RSS leaders like his political guru Subhash Velingkar. There were also incidents like raids being conducted on his political opponents, who were running hospitals and bakery shops.

The two-month long mudslinging against Bhau finally stopped when he agreed to dissolve the party executive and hold fresh organisational elections within six months, set up an ad-hoc steering committee, and till then give powers to the Parliamentary Board to look after the party affairs and set up a sub-committee to draft a constitution of the party.^21

The One-Sixth Factor

‘Land to the Tiller’ was the topmost priority of the MGP government. But CM Bandodkar had also made it clear that no legislation would be enforced unless it was thoroughly debated in the Assembly. That too only after the Dias Commission, set up before the Assembly was constituted, submitted its report on land reforms. Accordingly, based on the report, Law Minister Tony Fernandes introduced the Goa, Daman and Diu Agricultural Tenancy Bill on 28 July 1964. After heated debates in two consecutive sessions, it was finally passed on 10 November the same year.

When it was moved formally on 4 August 1964, Bhau made it clear that the bill certainly aimed at eventually giving ownership of land to the tenant. But it had not neglected the small Bhatkar (landlords), who should not suffer in the bargain. This was an intermediary legislation where the landowners would also get a share of the produce until the land survey was conducted and the Land to the Tiller Act would be finally enforced in the future. The landowners would also be allowed to retain cultivable land for themselves, with a ceiling, provided they personally tilled the land.

The bill was also moved to the Select Committee, headed by Chief Minister Bandodkar, on 5 August, after debating the preliminary draft for two days. The Committee comprised two ministers Tony Fernandes and V S Karmali, MGP member Vijay Kamulkar, PSP’s Jaisingrao V Rane as well as three UGP members: Leader of the Opposition Dr Jack Sequeira, Dr Alvaro Loyola Furtado and Enio Pimenta were the members.

The bill was finally passed after debating the revised draft based on the Select Committee report, for nine long days from 26 October to 10 November. However, the bone of contention of the debate, right from the first day, remained the Khand (share of produce), which was fixed at one-sixth uniformly to all kinds of lands − Ker, Khajan and Morod.^22 It was made mandatory to the tenant to pay this share to the landlord. The cut-off date for being a tenant was 1 July 1962. Sub-letting or sub-division was prohibited. The bill also provided the right of resumption of land to the landlord for personal cultivation; two hectares for khazan land and four hectares for other land. The intention was that small landlords should not suffer due to the new legislation.

Most of the UGP MLAs were bhatkars. They became the voice of landlords in the Assembly. Though they kept on admitting that the ownership of the land should finally go to the tenant, the uniform share of one-sixth of the produce as a token was opposed vehemently. Instead, they demanded half, one-third, one-fourth, and one-sixth of share to different kinds of land. It was also argued that Goa hardly had any big zamindars, that most of them were small bhatkars owning two to five hectares of land on an average.

The Leader of the Opposition Dr Jack de Sequeira argued that only 40 per cent of the land in Goa was effectively agricultural and 28 per cent was lying fallow. Around 60 per cent of land was privately owned but divided and fragmented within the families. The Communidades and the Government were the biggest landholders. In order to increase agricultural production, he proposed that the government should immediately divide the one-third uncultivated fallow land in the New Conquests like Canacona, Sanguem, etc. into large units, form governmentsubsidised cooperative societies, and that landless peasants and displaced tenants should be made its shareholders.

He admitted that most of the shareholders of Communidades were neither agriculturists nor did they live in the village. They had sub-let it to the landless peasants. He proposed that such ‘jonoeiros’ (shareholders) should be compensated in 20 instalments, Communidades should also be converted into cooperatives, and their tenants and sub-tenants should be made shareholders, by making the whole land as one cultivable unit.

In the case of 60 per cent of land owned privately by bhatkars, Dr Sequeira proposed that they should be allowed to resume land for personal cultivation up to a fixed ceiling. If the owner did not exercise the right within two years, then only the tenant would have the right of ownership. He also justified the period of two years claiming that most of the landlords may not be conversant with the law.^23

All kinds of arguments were made by the opposition members, claiming that they were not speaking in favour of bhatkars but comprehensive land reforms. J L G Araujo, the St Cruz MLA, gave an example of three brothers, each one investing money in a field, a bus, and a shop, respectively.

“There is some kind of injustice here. Whoever is a worker should be regarded as a worker and should get the share in the profit. Why injustice to a person who invested money in the field? In saying this, I am not against this Bill.”^24

Urminda Mascarenhas Lima Leitao, the Vasco MLA, landlord and mine owner, asked why hay had not been included in the gross produce. Today hay also brings in a lot of income, she contended. She was perhaps not prepared to spare even hay, which was used as a natural feed for the cattle that the tenants keep for ploughing the fields.^25 And then there was a comprehensive question posed by Navelim MLA Dr Alvaro Loyola Furtado:

“Then the next and most important question is why one-sixth? … Why has it not been fixed at 50 per cent of the gross produce for irrigated lands and 45 per cent of the produce for dry lands? Why not one-fourth of the gross produce for irrigated lands and one-fifth in other cases or three to five times the land revenue according to the class of soil, which is less as in Telangana? Why not one-fifth of the produce or its value if the share-cropper supplies plough, cattle etc and one-fourth of its value if the landowner provides plough, cattle, etc. as in Assam? Why not one-fourth of the gross produce as in Bihar? Why not one-fourth of the produce for wetland and one-third for dry lands and in the case of small owners half of the produce as in Jammu and Kashmir? Then why not 35 per cent where irrigation is supplemented by lift irrigation and 33 and one third per cent in other cases as in Madras? Why not one-fourth of the gross produce for lands irrigated from tanks or river channels and one-fifth in other cases or value thereof as in Mysore?”^26

In reply, Law Minister Tony Fernandes said:

“But the fact that this territory of ours is not >in Kashmir, neither it is in Mysore, nor in Madras, has been >forgotten. It is here on the Konkan coast bordering Maharashtra where it has >been already fixed that the rent should not be more than one-sixth. >I say not more than one-sixth because it is misunderstood by the >Opposition that it is just a fraction – one-sixth. But it is not so. In >the subsequent section it has been further clarified that the >ratio of rent will be fixed after the survey and settlement.”^27

Well-studied lengthy and argumentative speeches in favour of the bill were also made by almost all the MGP and PSP members, from the day the bill was introduced till it was passed. Mandrem MLA Vijay Kamulkar, a teacher who had defeated two mighty landlords Raoraje Deshprabhu of the Congress and Sadhashiv Desai of the UGP, said:

“The farmers had faced all kinds of harassment from the landlords with the blessings of the Portuguese rulers. The Portuguese would have not been a mighty empire if these landlords had not helped them. In return, the Portuguese protected the interests of the landlords and gave them extensive powers to extort the produce the farmers were growing in their fields. I am grateful to all the Shetkari Sanghatana as well as Prime Minister Jawaharlal Nehru, who made us aware about our rights, after Goa was made independent. However, I wish this act would not antagonise but establish a cordial relation between the landlords and the tenants. The landlords should also be not deprived of some land for cultivation, but with a ceiling. I also urge the government to set up a council to monitor the implementation of the act. Otherwise the landlords would keep on approaching civil courts to stall its implementation.”

The bill was finally passed with UGP staging walkouts on two consecutive days. On 9 November, Calangute MLA J M D’Souza did not join the protest: “I do not wish to walk out because I wish to place my faith in the Government that it will see its way doing something, to give some kind of satisfaction to the Opposition.” The next day, however, he joined them. Dr Jack de Sequeira, before the walkout, termed the bill as absolutely obnoxious and vexatious, ill-advised, ill-timed and ill-conceived; full of ‘ills’.

Even before Bhau could complete one year, he had succeeded in winning the hearts and souls of the whole farming community of Goa, irrespective of caste, creed, or religion. A real masterstroke of his Bahujan Formula!

Interview with Ramdas Prabhugaonkar, Ex-Secretary, Goa Hindu Association, Mumbai↩︎

Press Trust of India, Bombay, 13 December 1963 269↩︎

The Navhind Times, 14 December 1963↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन; महाराष्ट्रवादी गोमंतक पक्ष, स्थापना आणि वाटचाल, पान 27↩︎

The Next Steps, Editorial, The Navhind Times, 13 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times, 18 December 1963↩︎

राधाकृष्ण वामन: मुक्तीनंतरचा गोवा, पान 75↩︎

The Navhind Times, 12 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times, 18 December 1963↩︎

Press Trust of India in Mumbai, 24 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times, 14 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times, 17 December 1963↩︎

The Navhind Times, 25 December 1963↩︎

Press Trust of India, Bombay, 26 December 1963↩︎

Press Trust of India, New Delhi, 28 December 1963↩︎

गोमंतक, 7 जानेवारी 1964↩︎

गोमंतक, 11 जानेवारी 1964↩︎

The Navhind Times, 24 July 1964↩︎

The Navhind Times, 20 October 1964↩︎

The Navhind Times, 9 November 1964↩︎

The Navhind Times, 11 November 1964↩︎

Goa Agricultural Tenancy Act: “Ker land” means land having↩︎

Legislative Assembly of Goa 1964: 4 August 1964, P 1202-1205↩︎

Legislative Assembly of Goa 1964: 4 August 1964, P 1214↩︎

Legislative Assembly of Goa 1964: 9 November 1964, P 1825↩︎

Legislative Assembly of Goa 1964: 9 November 1964, P 1827↩︎

Legislative Assembly of Goa 1964: 9 November 1964, P 1829↩︎

Chapter 13

The Politics of Land

Whether it was the revolutionary Assembly election of 1963 or the historic Opinion Poll of 1967, it was a battle for land. The land you cultivate, the land on which you have built a house, or the whole land of Goa you belong to. Precisely this is the reason the majority of Goans voted for the MGP but rejected its mergerist agenda. And precisely due to the same reason the pro-farmer ‘reformist’ Bhau Bandodkar was elected back to power in 1967 with 16 seats and once again in 1972 with 18 seats. After his sudden demise in 1973, his daughter Shashikala Kakodkar carried forward his legacy successfully.

In 1975, the MGP government brought about yet another ‘socialist’ legislation, the Goa, Daman and Diu Mundkars (Protection from eviction) Act, 1975.^1 Right in the beginning the Act states: It is meant to provide for better protection to mundkars against eviction from their dwelling houses and for granting them the right to purchase the same and to make certain other provisions connected therewith, where such houses have been built at a reasonable price; it is expedient to abolish the system of free services rendered by mundkars and turn it into a remunerated one.

Following this, based on an extensive land survey conducted by the government, the MGP government in 1976 amended the Agricultural Tenancy Act 1964, with a fifth amendment. At last, the tenant who was paying one-sixth of their agricultural produce for 12 years, was made the deemed owner of the cultivable land, provided he purchased it through legal procedures. He was free from the clutches of Bhatkarshai. Was he? Was the dream fulfilled?

Dragging Cases & Snailing Courts

As per the procedure laid down in the Act, the Mamlatdar or the Deputy Collector is authorised to complete the formalities including hearing the case and issue a Sanad of ownership to the tenant. The Assembly sessions are full of questions asked by the MLAs about the pending cases of tenancy. The latest one was asked by Ponda MLA Ravi Naik in 2021 regarding pending cases since 2012. Revenue Minister Jennifer Monserrate replied that 2846 cases are still pending and only 527 sanads have been issued in 10 years.^2 Similarly, 819 cases of Mundkars are still pending. In the last 10 years, 2296 mundkars have officially purchased their house from the Bhatkars while 1147 have still not been able to purchase the houses, in spite of declaring them as deemed owners.^3

The legislations were enacted in 1975-76, but the actual implementation started in the last decade of the 20th century, after 1990, almost 15 years later. Even after three decades the tillers have not become the deemed owners of the cultivable land or their houses. Isn’t it a tragedy of Indian democracy? The MGP was supported mainly by the people from the New Conquests. But still suffering are a large number of people from the Old Conquests. The pending cases in each taluka of the Old Conquests are between 500 to 750. A few hundreds have become owners of their rightful land in the last 10 years.

Similar is the plight of the mundkars. More cases are pending in the Old Conquests than the New Conquests. In eight talukas of the New Conquests, only 318 people have not been able to purchase their houses in spite of their cases being disposed of. But in the Old Conquests, over 700 families in four talukas have not been able to purchase their houses. Is this the reason they are still migrating even at the cost of giving up their citizenship, as they could raise money to either buy their mundkarial houses or build a decent house in the place of a hut-like structure? No political party or the elected legislator has bothered to inquire about their plight.

STATE OF TENANCY & MUNDKAR CASES FROM 2012-2021

TALUKA | COURTS | TENANCY | | MUNDKAR | |
| | PENDING | DECLARED | PENDING | PURCHASED | NOT PURCHASED
OLD CONQUESTS | | | | | |
Bardez | 7 | 753 | 114 | 225 | 606 | 327
Tiswadi | 6 | 520 | 183 | 192 | 618 | 120
Salcete | 8 | 503 | 60 | 112 | 187 | 241
Mormugao | 5 | 60 | 4 | 33 | 83 | 24
TOTAL | 26 | 1836 | 361 | 562 | 1494 | 712
NEW CONQUESTS | | | | | |
Pernem | 4 | 489 | 70 | 12 | 356 | 71
Bicholim | 5 | 229 | 22 | 15 | 245 | 75
Sattari | 2 | 37 | 1 | 18 | 67 | 6
Ponda | 4 | 43 | 26 | 192 | 49 | 117
Quepem | 1 | 94 | 7 | 5 | 54 | 24
Canacona | 2 | 42 | 42 | 13 | 18 | 17
Sanguem | 1 | 60 | 0 | 1 | 0 | 5
Dharbandora | 2 | 16 | 0 | 1 | 15 | 3
TOTAL | 21 | 1010 | 168 | 257 | 804 | 318
GRAND TOTAL | 47 | 2846 | 529 | 819 | 2298 | 1030

Source: Assembly Questions

Delay Tactics Of Bhatkars

Nearly six decades have passed but the tiller has still not become the owner and the mundkar has not become the owner of his or her ancestral house. While debating the Tenancy bill in 1964, Vijay Kamulkar, the MGP MLA who defeated two mighty landlords Raoraje Deshprabhu and Sadashiv Desai, had predicted this. He had urged the government to set up a council to monitor the implementation of the act. Otherwise the landlords would keep approaching the civil courts to stall its implementation, he had cautioned.

Everything was going smooth as long as the tenant was paying a fixed Khand of one sixth of the produce to the bhatkar. But the landlords bounced back the minute the fifth amendment to the Agricultural Tenancy Act was passed in the Assembly in 1976. Five petitions were filed before the Judicial Commissioner by the Bhatkars, challenging its constitutional validity. The government had deleted Chapter III from the Act, which was permitting landlords to resume the land for personal cultivation, with a ceiling. Instead, Chapter IIA was inserted. Its section 18A permitted transfer of land to the cultivating tenant for a price to be paid to the landlord. Landlords feared that a tenant cultivating lands under different landlords may have far larger areas of land than his landlord. On 4 April 1979, the Judicial Commissioner struck down the amended act, terming it unconstitutional and not constituting agrarian reform.

The Shashikala government swiftly moved to the Supreme Court, challenging the judgement of the Judicial Commissioner. Her government was pushed into trouble by two young rebels − Dayanand Narvekar and Dilkhush Desai. Despite that she managed to survive a no-trust motion with the help of two independents from Daman and Diu. But then her own minister Shankar Laad quit the ministry, pushing her government once again into a minority. Laad was offered the Chief Minister’s seat by the Leader of the Opposition and architect of the rebellion Anant Narasimh alias Babu Naik, the Congressman belonging to the landlord community. Shashikala-tai succeeded in getting President’s Rule imposed by convincing the then Janata Party Prime Minister Morarji Desai. The opposition did not succeed in forming an alternate government, but the MGP government was out.

Simultaneously, Tai also managed to convince the Centre to move before the Parliament an amendment to include the Agricultural Tenancy Act in the ninth schedule of the Constitution. As per the provision, acts included in the ninth schedule cannot be challenged in the courts of law. Meanwhile, the Janata government collapsed, fresh elections were held and Indira Gandhi’s Congress government came back to power. On 31 July 1983, the Centre moved the 47th amendment to the Constitution in the Parliament. It included tenancy acts related to land reforms enacted by the states of Assam, Bihar, Haryana, Tamil Nadu, Uttar Pradesh and West Bengal as well as the union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu. The amendment bill included both the acts of Goa, the original Tenancy Act of 1964 as well as the fifth amendment of 1976. The Statement of Objects and Reasons stated:

“The various Acts which have been suggested for inclusion have been examined and it is proposed to include in the Ninth Schedule such of these Acts as have either been challenged or are likely to be challenged and thereby ensure that the implementation of these Acts is not adversely affected by litigation.”^4

The constitutional amendment was passed by the Parliament and it was assented to by the President of India on 26 August 1984. The Goan landlords challenged the inclusion of the fifth amendment in the ninth schedule in the Supreme Court, which was also hearing Goa government’s appeal against the high court order striking down the ninth amendment. The landlords were defended by a phalanx of India’s eminent lawyers including Fali Nariman, M N Phadke, S K Mehta and even Goa’s topmost lawyer Manohar Usgaonkar.

Meanwhile, in the 1980 Assembly election, Congress rode to power with an absolute majority and Pratapsingh Raoji Rane Sardesai, the Khashe from Sattari, became the chief minister of Goa. He ruled the state for 10 long years uninterrupted. The case in the Supreme Court was moving at a snail’s pace. Ravi Naik, the MGP MLA since 1984, also filed an intervention application on behalf of his Akhil Gomantak Kull-Mundkar Sanghatana to expedite the case, but all in vain. Rane became the CM for the third consecutive term after the 1989 election, but his government was toppled on 27 March 1990. The Progressive Democratic Front, a coalition government of the Congress rebels and Ramakant Khalap-led MGP, was formed. The MGP leaders pursued the case in the Supreme Court.

Within four months, on 23 July 1990, the apex court delivered the judgement. It set aside the high court judgement and upheld the ninth amendment bill.

“The judgment of the Judicial Commissioner declaring the Act as ultra vires is accordingly set aside and the writ petitions filed by the respondents are dismissed. Consequently it is not necessary to deal with the writ petition (W.P. No. 864 of 1988) filed in this Court under Article 32 challenging the inclusion of the impugned Act in the 9th Schedule of the Constitution and the same is rejected.”^5

Meanwhile, the budget session of Goa Assembly was going on. Deputy CM Ramakant Khalap suddenly entered the House in a dramatic manner and made the announcement of the Supreme Court, calling it a historic day. Agriculture Minister Ravi Naik distributed sweets to the journalists in his cabin. Revenue Minister Dr Kashinath Jalmi moved into action, authorising the Joint Mamlatdars to issue sanads to the tenants after completing the formalities of purchasing the land. But lots of water had flown through the paddy fields in 30 years. The rural population had slipped from 85 per cent in 1960 to 59 per cent in 1990 due to large urbanisation.^6

1990 was also the year that had started showing a negative growth in operational holdings in the agricultural sector. The area under cultivation had reduced from 92,000 hectares in 1970 to 66,000 hectares in 1990, a decline of 15 per cent.^7

The 60 per cent workforce involved in agriculture in 1960 had declined to 16 per cent. The contribution of agriculture to the Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP) had dropped to just 10 per cent^8 In my own village of Loliem-Pollem in Canacona on the Goa-Karnataka border, agriculture and allied activities had stopped completely, the lands had fallen fallow, cowsheds had turned into garages and only our old parents were left in our homes. We all had migrated to the towns for our livelihoods. The Economic Survey 2002 I am quoting here had also pushed the chapter on ‘Agriculture & Allied Services’ to the second last position, before ‘Other Sectors’:

“The declining interest towards agriculture may be attributable to small land holdings, high cost of wages and nonavailability of agriculture labourers. In addition to this, increasing urbanisation has exerted pressure on land making the agriculture activity economically less viable on relative terms. On the other hand Goa being a major tourist destination attracting over 1.3 million tourists every year, which is equivalent to the population of the state, there is a tremendous scope for high value added crops like horticulture, floriculture, medicinal plants, vegetables etc.”

But rather than meeting this scope by diverting the agro economy of Goa to cash crops, the politicians preferred to meet the growing demand of land for housing for the outsiders and hotels including large five-star resorts for the tourists. Converting agricultural land into commercial became the prime ‘business’ of politicians. The Assembly elected in 1990 witnessed a spurt of defections, topplings, seven chief ministers in five years and the Town and Country Planning Department − which converts the land − becoming the most lucrative portfolio. The Planning and Development Authorities (PDAs), which prepare the Outline Development Plans (ODPs), became the battlegrounds for cronies of politicians to grab ‘commissions’. Ravi Naik, the one-time president of the Tenants and Mundkars Association, himself became one of the prime ‘broker-politicians’ of Goa.

There were varied modus operandis followed to convert the agricultural land. The fifth amendment had widened the scope of tenanted land from paddy and arecanut to horticulture, cashew cultivation and coconut garden too. The tenant was considered the deemed purchaser and he had no right to transfer the land even by way of lease. Once the property was purchased under tenancy, the same could not be leased, mortgaged, or sold nor could it be converted to non-agricultural use without the permission of the Mamlatdar. It could be taken and given to another person, but only to cultivate, through the Mamlatdar. However, the landlord could sell his property if his land was not tenanted. Giving this background, Dr Nagesh Colvalkar, the Assistant Professor of V M Salgaocar College of Law, states:

“After 1975, landlords and builders filed several litigations based on Survey Records and Land Revenue Code claiming the ownership right. Litigations between tenants and landlords became more cumbersome due to non-preparation of Record of Rights, having no receipt of payment of rent to the Landlord with the Tenant and contract of lease. Under the Goa Agricultural Tenancy Act 1964 to claim tenancy right, the Tenant had to prove (a) possession of the land (b) Personal cultivation (c) Existence of lease (d) Payment of rent.”^9

There was also a spurt of complaints recorded at police stations, that tenants and mundkars were forcibly evicted from the land, allegedly at the behest of builders and with the blessings of politicians. Some of the ‘eviction experts’ also entered active politics. However, many builders followed a path of amicable settlements with the tenants or mundkars by providing them flats and shops in the buildings. And in many cases, yet another method was followed, called ‘negative declaration’ by the tenants. It means that the tenant swears in front of the Mamlatdar that his name has been wrongly entered as a tenant in the I & XIV form of Land Records and withdraws from the land, in collusion with the builder and the landlord. In fact, this has now become a legal practice from the time the Supreme Court has upheld the order of Pernem Mamlatdar accepting negative declarations of the tenants. The Bombay High Court at Goa, in this case, had earlier struck down the Mamlatdar’s order of negative declaration, issued on 28 October 1986. This case was related to the controversial Golf Course project at Terekhol, where half of the tenants had withdrawn as tenants from the disputed property. Apparently, it was “amicably settled” while the villagers as well as the social activists were up in arms against the golf course project.^10

From the time this judgement has been delivered by the Honourable Supreme Court, says young activist lawyer from Pernem Adv Prasad Shapurkar, hundreds and thousands of negative declarations have been given by the tenants with ‘free will’, in collusion with the landlord and the builder. But he is equally proud of the remaining half of the tenants of the Terekhol property, who did not bow down before the pressure from the golf course promoters, including the local politicians and the brokers. He is equally worried about the genuine tenants whose cases are simply dragging on in the courts of Mamlatdars for various reasons.

THE ‘SUNSET’ OF THE BJP

And why are the cases dragging on for so long despite having set up so many courts of Mamlatdars, Joint Mamlatdars and Deputy Collectors? Salcete has eight courts and still over 600 cases of tenants and mundkars are pending while little more than 200 have been settled in 10 years. (See table on Pg 317). Margao MLA Digambar Kamat recently asked in the Assembly why the cases could not be expedited. And this is what the government officially told him:

“Courts of Mamlatdar & Deputy Collector are also handling election matters, other duties such as Law & Order, cases under various other Acts. There is less support staff in each court. The Government has initiated a Court Case Monitoring System which will help the government to monitor the progress of all the cases online. The process for recruiting additional staff is also in progress. Training has been given to the officers on the procedural aspects of hearing the matters. Idea of Saturday Courts have started taking up Tenancy and Mundkar cases.”^11

Interestingly, the joint mamlatdars were initially assigned to exclusively handle the cases of tenants and mundkars. Each taluka today has more than one or two Joint Mamlatdars. But apparently it has not remained a priority for any government headed by any political party, since 1990. In fact, the reply given by the Government to the Assembly question raised by MLA Aleixo Reginald Lourenco in 2014 reflects the apathy at the level of the Mamlatdar. One case of Constantino Pinto in Bardez has been dragging since 1972, and of Gurudas Talkar in Pernem since 1976 and Gurudas Ghatwal and others in Bicholim since 1983!^12

The politicians holding the reins of governance are no less irresponsible. Digambar Kamat, who raised the issue of dragging tenancy cases in 2018, was the chief minister for five long years from 2007. During his tenure, the Law Commission was headed by Adv Ramakant Khalap and assisted by Adv Mario Pinto Almeida and Adv Cleofato Coutinho. In 2009, the Commission framed a draft bill to set up exclusive revenue courts to deal with tenancy and mundkar cases, stating that the framers of the Constitution of India have adopted the principle of separation of Judiciary from Executive:

“The Commission is of the view that the judiciary work of Mamlatdars and Collectors must be separated from other routine work so that they can exclusively function as Courts and complete the judicial work before them expeditiously and without any interference. The Commission is of the opinion that a hierarchy of Revenue Courts can be created by establishing Taluka Revenue Courts with original jurisdiction and District Revenue Courts with appellate and revisional jurisdiction. We are also of the view that these courts should function under the overall supervision of the Administrative Tribunal.”^13

Despite being in power till 2012, the Kamat government did not pay heed to this most crucial legislation. Those were the days when illegal mining was at its peak. As though this apathy was not enough, the next Law Commission set up under the chief ministership of Manohar Parrikar and headed by Adv Narendra Sawaikar proposed in August 2013 an alternative to the exclusive revenue courts, which finally boomeranged on the BJP government. By that time, the cases had piled up to over 3000, with Bardez topping the list with 846 cases.

“...we are conscious that the said Commission (headed by Khalap) proposed ‘The Goa Revenue Courts Bill 2009’ in their Report no. 3 providing for a separate hierarchy of revenue officers solely to discharge judicial work under different laws. What this Commission proposes is to recommend amendment to the Goa Agricultural Tenancy Act and to give the core adjudicatory functions under the said Act which are presently given to the ‘Mamlatdars’ under the said Act to the courts of the Civil Judges appointed under the Goa Civil Courts Act designated as ‘Civil Judges’ and provide for a single Appellate authority which would be ‘Appellate Judge’ meaning the District Judges including all the Additional District Judges appointed under the Goa Civil Courts Act. Appellate Judges shall also exercise revisional jurisdiction over the proceedings before the Civil Judges. This Commission is of the considered opinion that utilisation of the Judges of the existing civil courts in the matter of tenancy declaration cases and determination of tenancy issues arising in civil suits and other proceedings should go a long way in expediting the decision-making in tenancy matters.”^14

By the time these amendment bills to the Tenancy and Mundkar Acts were passed on 21 August 2014, the pending tenancy cases had risen to 5000 and 2800 Mundkar cases. Besides transferring the cases to the civil courts, it had also proposed a system of contract farming as well as a ‘sunset clause’, setting a deadline of three years to file applications by tenants and mundkars before the Mamlatdar for the ownership of the land. The bill had initially set up the limit of only one year. BJP legislator Dr Pramod Sawant moved only one amendment to change it to three years, and both the bills were passed ‘unanimously’ by all the 40 legislators without much debate.^15

But there was an uproar all across Goa over the ‘sunset clause’ as well as transferring the cases to the civil courts. Revenue Minister Francisco D’Souza defended the legislation, claiming that “civil courts are better places for the disposal of cases simply because judges are trained. On the other hand, mamlatdars are not so trained because most of them are promotees from ‘awal karkuns’ to mamlatdars. They do not have a legal background. They manage, but progress is very slow.”

There were allegations and counter-allegations, while demanding withdrawal of the bill. Reiterating his demand for special revenue courts to deal with the tenancy and mundkar cases, Congress leader Ramakant Khalap alleged: “The legislation would develop a nexus between landowners and the real estate lobby to finish off the remaining agricultural land in Goa. Even though most of our agricultural land has already been bought by outsiders, now ‘upcoming moneybags’ will exploit the contract farming section of the amended act to eat up the remaining agricultural land in Goa.”

Laxmikant Parsekar, who by then had taken over as the CM with Parrikar becoming the defence minister of India, made a similar allegation, claiming that the opposition was politically motivated by the land sharks: “The amendments to the Goa Tenancy Act seek to get rid of land grabbers who survive on the discord between the land owner and the tenant. The same landgrabbers and politically motivated leaders are now misleading the people, provoking them against the amendment…. If a tenant fails to file the claim within three years, the state government can grant more time in some cases.”^16

Both sides were blaming each other, but were in agreement that the land sharks were looting Goa’s prime cultivable land! The BJP government remained adamant and transferred all the cases to the civil courts. Amidst the uproar came the 2017 Assembly election. In spite of introducing a series of social schemes for the cross-section of the society, building good infrastructure, and Parrikar holding one of the highest positions, of defence minister at the Centre, the BJP slipped down from 21 to 13 seats. The Congress, despite doing nothing but fighting among themselves and some of its ‘loyal soldiers’ hobnobbing with the Hindutva party, rose from nine to 17 and emerged as the largest single party in a hung Assembly. BJP supremo Amit Shah and influential union minister Nitin Gadkari moved into action and ‘managed’ to lift the anti-BJP regional outfits like the MGP and Goa Forward Party as well as the independents into the saffron camp to form its own government on 14 March 2017.

Apparently, the BJP had learnt a lesson. After reviewing the election results and the unexpected shocking debacle of the BJP, revenue minister Francisco D’Souza announced that the government would withdraw the controversial amendments of the tenancy and mundkar acts, including the sunset clause, and cases would be reverted back to the mamlatdars. He admitted that the decision was being taken in view of the strong criticism from the opposition and the tenants’ associations. He also assured to expedite the pending tenancy cases within three years. (Even after four years, over 3500 cases are still pending). Accordingly, the new amendments were moved in the third session of the Assembly in August 2017 to drop the controversial clauses. Revenue Minister Rohan Khaunte said roughly about 3900 cases (out of 4000 transferred to civil courts) would be transferred back to the mamlatdars. When the ruling party legislator Nilesh Cabral asked him if moving the cases to civil courts was detrimental to the tenants, Khaunte said: “.. the rate of cases going in favour of the landlords and against the tenants remained almost the same, with it being 21 per cent when it was with the Mamlatdars and 23 per cent when it was with the civil courts.”

The most interesting statement came from BJP’s own Sports Minister Babu Azgaonkar, who is known for his bold and blunt talk. “The BJP government’s decision to move the cases from the mamlatdar courts to the senior civil judge had backfired on the BJP and it was the reason why the Congress managed to win so many seats in the election. If there is anyone who has been embarrassed by this amendment, it is the BJP.”^17

Dealers Become Leaders

Dr Nagesh Colvalkar, concludes his research paper on Land Reforms in Goa, by aptly focussing upon the unholy nexus between the land sharks, politicians, and bureaucrats:

“...in Goa today, the scenario is totally adverse against land reform laws. Cultivators purchase the land under tenancy law which must be exclusively used for agricultural purpose, but these tenants in reality sell the tenanted lands to the big builders and estate developers for carrying out construction activity in violation of the provisions of the Goa Agricultural Tenancy Act under the blessing of political leaders, land mafias and bureaucrats. This needs to be stopped at all cost, failing which land reforms in Goa will be a futile exercise without any gain to the state of Goa.”

Earlier in the ‘60s and the ‘70s, politics was a ‘Mission’, for which freedom fighters, social reformers, teachers etc. were entering the political arena. By the ‘80s, politics slowly began to turn into a ‘Profession’ and full-time politicians began to mushroom. This also led to a rise in corruption. But since the 1990s, it has now completely turned into a business of ‘Commission’. Earlier political parties were collecting funds from the lobbies of mine owners, contractors, private bus owners, trawler owners, industrialists, hoteliers etc. and the governments were serving the interest of their lobbies, at the cost of suppressing the welfare of the toiling masses. This also led to a series of public agitations by farmers, workers, toddy tappers, traditional fishermen like ramponkars, students, women, etc. But nowadays, representatives of the business lobbies have personally entered into active politics, posing as ‘social workers’ by donating generously for sports tournaments, cultural extravaganzas, and other public causes.

These included a few landowners initially, but then came the private bus operators, trawler owners, contractors, hoteliers, and even mine owners. But now the Assembly is overflowing with the ‘social workers’ who are dealers of land, including builders, real estate developers, and even land brokers. The latest trend among these ‘broker-politicians’ is to get tickets for their brothers, wives and daughters so that they can increase their stake in power sharing. Perhaps this is the reason the cases of land grabbing, illegal land conversions, and encroachments of cultivable land are not topping the agendas of the Assembly debates. And the controversial amendments like 16B to the Town and Country Planning Act are passed smoothly.

We have six political leaders in the House, who are legally involved in construction business: Luizinho Faleiro, Ravi Naik, Digambar Kamat, Pandurang Madkaikar, Rohan Khaunte, and Tony Fernandes. The real estate developers like Babush Monserrate, Vijai Sardesai, and Nilesh Cabral have also entered the Assembly. People in political circles reveal that heavyweight politicians like Vishwajeet Rane, Dr Pramod Sawant, Isidore Fernandes etc. are known to be property brokers. In fact, before joining active politics, Dr Sawant was a land broker and is widely known till date in Sattari and Bicholim as ‘Property Sawant’. There was also a land dealing case in Canacona, which was widely reported since a sitting judge was expelled from the service. Junior Rane was allegedly involved in the land dealing. There is obviously nothing wrong with the land dealings since these are all legal businesses. But it is also a fact that illegalities in land conversions and land grabbing have become the order of the day with the entry of more and more land-dealing businessmen into the Goa Assembly. Today, in talukas like Pernem, where the tenants had once defeated mighty landlords of Goa, the prominent leaders contesting elections are the builders, real estate dealers, and brokers.

The trend of Family Raj in politics coincides with the increasing trend of converting agricultural land into settlement and selling it to land sharks, which began in the last decade of the 20th century. With the advent of the 21st century began the era of Family Raj politics. Otherwise, it was only Bhausaheb Bandodkar who had brought his daughter Shashikala into active politics or Dr Jack Sequeira fielding his son Erasmo to become the South Goa MP, in the 1960s and ‘70s respectively. During the tenure of Digambar Kamat, Vishwajit Rane was the minister while his father Pratapsingh Rane was the Speaker.

FAMILY RAJ POLITICS: SUCCESSES & FAILURES

ELECTIONS | NO | CANDIDATES (PARTY, SEAT) | CANDIDATES (RELATION, PARTY, SEAT)
1967 | 1 | Dayanand Bandodkar (MGP, Madkai) | Shashikala Kakodkar (Daughter, MGP, Mandrem)
1972 | 1 | Dayanand Bandodkar (MGP, Mandrem) | Shashikala Kakodkar (Daughter, MGP, Bicholim)
2002 | 1 | Churchill Alemao (Save Goa Congress, Navelim) | Joaquim Alemao (Brother, Save Goa Congress, Cuncolim)
2007 | 1 | Sudin Dhavalikar (MGP, Madkai) | Deepak Dhavalikar (Brother, MGP, Priol)
| 2 | Pratapsingh Rane (Congress, Poriem) | Vishwajit Rane (Son, Independent, Valpoi)
| 3 | Churchill Alemao (Congress, Benaulim) | Joaquim Alemao (Brother, Save Goa Congress, Cuncolim)
| 4 | Babush Monserrate (UGDP, Taleigaon) | Jennifer Monserrate (Wife, UGDP, St. Cruz, Lost)
2012 | 1 | Pratapsingh Rane (Congress, Poriem) | Vishwajit Rane (Son, Congress, Valpoi)
| 2 | Sudin Dhavalikar (MGP, Madkai) | Deepak Dhavalikar (Brother, MGP, Priol)
| 3 | Babush Monserrate (Congress, St. Cruz) | Jennifer Monserrate (Wife, Congress, Taleigaon)
| 4 | Pandurang Madkaikar (Congress, Cumbarjua) | Dhaku Madkaikar (Bother, Congress, Priol)
| 5 | Ravi Naik (Congress, Ponda) | Ritesh Naik (Son, Congress, Madkai)
| 6 | Churchill Alemao (Congress, Navelim) | Valanka Alemao (Daughter, Congress, Benaulim)
| 7 | Joaquim Alemao (Congress, Cuncolim) | Yuri Alemao (Son, NCP, Sanguem)
2017 | 1 | Pratapsingh Rane (Congress, Poriem) | Vishwajit Rane (Son, Independent, Valpoi)
| 2 | Babush Monserrate (UGP, Panaji) | Jennifer Monserrate (Wife, Congress, Taleigaon)
| 3 | Sudin Dhavalikar (MGP, Madkai) | Deepak Dhavalikar (Brother, MGP, Priol)
| 4 | Pandurang Madkaikar (BJP, Cumbarjua) | Dhaku Madkaikar (Brother, Independent, St. Andre)
| 5 | Churchill Alemao (NCP, Benaulim) | Joaquim Alemao (Brother, Independent, Cuncolim)
| 6 | Babu Kavlekar (Congress, Quepem) | Savitri Kavlekar (Wife, Congress, Sanguem)

Elected candidates are shown in bold

Similarly, the brother duo Churchill and Joaquim Alemao were holding the influential portfolios of PWD and Urban Development in the same ministry. In the Manohar Parrikar-led government from 2012, another brother duo Sudin and Dipak Dhavalikar were ministers with important portfolios like PWD, Transport, Cooperation etc. And in the subsequent government of Dr Pramod Sawant after Parrikar’s demise, Jennifer Monserrate is the revenue minister while her husband Babush is the chairman of the Panaji Planning and Development Authority (PPDA).

The tradition continues with nine duos within the families planning to contest the 2022 Assembly election. In fact some of them are negotiating with more than one political party and even jumping out from one party to another to bargain for their joint tickets. These are husband Babush and wife Jennifer Monserrate, brothers Sudin and Dipak Dhavalikar, husband Babu and wife Savitri Kavalekar, husband Michael and wife Delilah, husband Vishwajit and wife Divya Rane, husband Kiran and wife Kavita Kandolkar, father Ravi and son Ritesh Naik, brothers Rohan and Rajesh Khaunte, as well as father Churchill and daughter Valanka Alemao.

The dangers of this increasing trend of broker-politicians were experienced by Goans through the most controversial Regional Plan Goa 2011, known as RPG-11, when Babush Monserrate was heading the town and country planning ministry in 2006 in the Congress government led by Pratapsingh Rane. Though the legislators were dormant to the plan, the alert Niz Goenkars rose against it, led a state-wide historic agitation under the banner of the Goa Bachao Abhiyan and got the destructive RPG11 scrapped. In 2007, Digambar Kamat took over as the new Congress CM, and formed a Task Force of nationally reputed Goa architects and town planners under the chairmanship of internationally renowned architect Charles Correa. They later also framed a new RPG21, banning conversion of cultivable land and laying down guidelines for restricted construction activity by demarcating Economically Sensitive Zones as well as restricted Zones for village panchayats.

Even after this, the cases against violation of the RPG21 guidelines are piling up in the courts of law. In fact the major case the High Court of Bombay at Goa is hearing since 2018 is the controversial amendment passed by the Assembly on 30 July 2018. It was moved by then TCP Minister Vijai Sardesai, in the coalition government headed by Manohar Parrikar. A new section 16B was inserted in the TCP Act:

“16B. Change of zone in Regional Plan.—

(1) If at any time, after the Regional Plan comes into operation, the Chief Town Planner (Planning) receives a written request from any person for change of zone of his land in the Regional Plan, he shall, after carrying out such fresh surveys and examination of the matter as may be considered necessary, submit his report to the Board and the Government, along with plan showing details about change of zone in the Regional Plan…

(4) After the Regional Plan comes into operation, the Chief Town Planner (Planning) may, with the prior approval of the Government, make such changes in such Regional Plan as may be necessary for correcting any typographical or cartographical errors, omissions or details of proposals not fully indicated or changes arising out of the implementation of the proposals in the Regional Plan: Provided that all such changes are in the public interest and are notified to the public.”

Once again there was a public uproar, alleging that the hidden agenda of 16B was to change the agricultural zone to settlement and grant permissions for massive new commercial projects. TCP Minister Vijai Sardesai justified it, claiming that it would be done on a case-to-case basis and only in cases of public interest. Goa Congress President Girish Chodankar countered it, alleging that it would be on suitcase-to-suitcase basis. Finally, the Goa Bachao Abhiyan and others challenged the controversial amendment bill in the high court in November 2018. The hearing was not complete till December 2021. Meanwhile, the high court allowed the government to consider the proposals of changing the zones but no approval could be granted till the case is decided. The high court in its interim directive stated:

“In the meantime, we direct that any action that may be taken in pursuance of Section 16B of the Goa Town and Country Planning Act, 1974, shall be subject to the outcome of the present petition. This position is made clear so that no parties can claim any equities.”^18

Accordingly, the TCP Board started entertaining applications for land conversions under Section 16B, processing it and even granting ‘provisional approvals’, pending the court directive. Since the hearing also got delayed due to the Covid19 pandemic, the GBA lawyer Adv Norma Alvares requested the court to restrain the TCP from considering further applications.

After hearing both the sides, the high court observed: “Taking into consideration the fact that no final approvals have been granted relying upon the impugned provision or the fact that it is not likely that even provisional approvals are likely to be granted upon the fresh proposals received for at least the next two months, we make no further orders on the request of Ms. Alvares.”^19

Was it an error committed by the court in allowing the government to process the applications for land conversions under section 16B? Or was it a deliberate move by the learned judges to verify what kind of applications are received, from whom, for what purpose and who are the people willing to convert their cultivable land? Whatever may be the intention, the applications received by the TCP were an eye opener.

Over 2 Crore Square Metres?

After passing this controversial amendment of 16B in July 2018, two leading politicians held the town and country planning portfolios. Vijai Sardesai for one year, till July 2019, and from then till fresh elections, Babu Kavlekar. In reply to the question asked by Leader of the Opposition Digambar Kamat, Kavlekar told the Assembly in February 2020 that 5601 applications have been received for converting cultivable zones into settlement. Due to the assurance given to the High Court, no applications have been processed after November 2019.^20

The Assembly records show that applications for zone conversions have come from all across Goa and all the 12 talukas. In fact, more applications have come from the villages than the cities, with a maximum applied for settlement zones. The lands are also paddy fields, orchards, natural cover, under irrigation command area, and even within the coastal regulation zones. They are either for housing colonies or hotels and resorts. Hardly any proposals are for public institutions, in ‘public interest’.

The next table shows taluka-wise conversion applications placed before the TCP Board when Vijai Sardesai was the TCP minister till July 2019.

CONVERSION APPLICATIONS DURING VIJAI SARDESAI’S TENURE

TALUKA | APPLICATIONS | AREA (sq.mt) | %
Pernem | 530 | 3929400 | 20
Bardez | 1021 | 3609975 | 19
Ponda | 1401 | 2220587 | 12
Tiswadi | 205 | 1789033 | 9
Quepem | 400 | 1755931 | 9
Bicholim | 754 | 1745478 | 9
Salcete | 538 | 1515929 | 8
Canacona | 88 | 1025612 | 5
Sattari | 320 | 537980 | 3
Dharbandora | 116 | 514430 | 3
Sanguem | 75 | 269288 | 1
Mormugao | 83 | 259407 | 1
TOTAL | 5531 | 19173050 |

PROVISIONAL APPROVALS: VIJAI SARDESAI’S TENURE

Date | Applications | Area (sq.mt.)
10-01-2019 | 7 | 440499
28-02-2019 | 15 | 691505
10-07-2019 | 7 | 168200
TOTAL | 29 | 1300204

Source: Assembly Questions; Digambar Kamat on 25-07-19 & Vijai Sardesai on 19-10-21

All these 5531 applications were processed and were in different phases of scrutiny, involving over 1.91 crore square metres of cultivable land. Topping the list is Pernem taluka with nearly 40 lakh square metres of cultivable land and then comes Bardez with around 36 lakh square metres of land. Both are tourism zones. The maximum land in Pernem taluka proposed to be converted is in Mandrem constituency. Likewise with the coastal belt of Bardez taluka. Half of the land sought to be converted lies in the three talukas of Pernem, Bardez and Ponda, involving nearly 98 lakh square metres of cultivable land. More than half of the applications are also from these three talukas. The zone conversion applications received in Mandrem constituency of Pernem taluka, within a six months period of December 2018 to May 2019, under 16B, numbered 373. The land proposed to be converted is around 33.88 lakh square metres. The major chunk of it, around 21 lakh square metres, is owned by J M Township Real Estates Pvt Ltd, a Mumbai-based real estate company, which has tied up with a local company running a casino in Goa.

Interestingly, Vijai Sardesai asked a question in the Assembly after he was dropped from the cabinet and was forced to sit in the opposition, to know how many more people have applied for land conversion during the tenure of his successor Babu Kavlekar. This table is being compiled, based on the Assembly reply.

TCPB MEETINGS DURING BABU KAVLEKAR TENURE

TCPB Meeting | Applications | Area (sq. mt.) | Status
11-10-2019 | 87 | 84481 | Provisional Approval
30-06-2021 | 32 | 1218860 | Provisional Approval
TOTAL APPROVED | 119 | 1303341 |
30-06-2021 | 71 | 503660 | Considered
30-06-2021 | 9 | 184351 | Deferred
03-02-2021 | 59 | 402557 | Processed
GRAND TOTAL | 258 | 2393909 |

Source: Assembly Question: Vijai Sardesai on 19-10-21

These tables are not foolproof. TCP Minister Kavlekar, in a reply to another question asked by his predecessor Vijai Sardesai, told the Assembly that a total 878 provisional approvals have been given by the TCP Board from April 2017, when the Parrikar government was formed.^21 Out of these, I could trace records of only 148 applications approved, 29 during Sardesai’s tenure and 119 during Kavlekar’s. Barely 14 per cent of the applications. But that itself reveals that over 26 lakhs square metres of cultivable land have been provisionally approved to be converted. The figures of 730 more applications are still unknown.

Also in the pipeline at various stages are a total of 5670 applications. What it means in simple terms is that if proposals received during the whole tenure of the BJP governments led by Manohar Parrikar and Dr Pramod Sawant are counted and if the high court gives a green signal to the controversial clause of 16B, then Goa would lose forever the cultivable land of two crore and twenty five lakh square metres!

While browsing through the list of applications available in the Assembly replies, I could trace some applications made by our own lawmakers, present and former, who had ‘unanimously supported’ the Regional Plan 2021. The RPG21 clearly stated that no zone changing would be allowed for the next 10 years, especially for settlement purposes. This table lists out applications made by present and former MLAs, to convert zones from paddy fields, natural cover, private forest, land under irrigation command area, and even no development zone. The table is self-explanatory.

ZONE CHANGE FROM REGIONAL PLAN 2021 APPLIED 2021 APPLIED BY LEADING POLITICIANS, EX-MLAS & MLAS FOR CONVERSION TO SETTLEMENT

No | Applicant | Related MLA | Party | Sq.Mts | Location | Original Status
1 | Deepak Dhavlikar | Deepak Dhavalikar | MGP MLA (Ex) | 393100 | Dharbandora | Error marking eco-sensitive zone
2 | Rajendra V Deshprabhu | Vasudev Deshprabhu | MGP Candidate | 225000 | Arambol | Orchard, Within High Tide Line
3 | Jit Arolkar | Jit Arolkar | MGP Candidate | 65302 | Dhargalim, Torxem, Virnoda | Orchard, Paddy Field, Cultivable land, Irrigation command area
4 | Harish Zantye | Pravin Zantye | BJP MLA | 26320 | Sarvona, Bicholim | Partly paddy field
5 | Alex Sequeira | Aleixo Sequeira | Congress MLA (Ex) | 18075 | Nuvem, Salcete | Orchard and Natural Cover
6 | Sandhya Naresh Sawal | Naresh Sawal | MGP MLA (Ex) | 13975 | Latambarce, Bicholim | Natural Cover
7 | Anil Hoble | Anil Hoble | BJP Candidate | 11546 | Morombi-o-Grande, Tiswadi | Paddy Fields
8 | Pratapsingh Rane | Pratapsingh Rane | Congress MLA | 11465 | Podocem, Sattari | Partly natural cover with irrigation command area & canal abutting to the property
9 | Laxmikant Parsekar | Laxmikant Parsekar | BJP MLA | 10000 | Arambol | Orchard, Cultivable Land, Salt Pan
10 | Madkaikar Builder | Pandurang Madkaikar | BJP MLA | 9475 | Old Goa, Tiswadi | Orchard with Archaeological Parks
11 | Rajesh Khaunte | Rohan Khaunte | Ind MLA | 8445 | Azossim, Tiswadi | Partly Paddy Field & Khazan
12 | Naresh Sawal | Naresh Sawal | MGP MLA (Ex) | 7219 | Latambarce, Bicholim | Partly Natural Cover
13 | Dhaku Madkaikar | Pandurang Madkaikar | Ind Candidate | 2475 | Candola, Ponda | Partly Natural Cover
14 | Tonia Estates | Alexio Sequeira | Congress MLA (Ex) | 1575 | Colva, Salcete | Orchard
15 | Madkaikar Builder | Pandurang Madkaikar | BJP MLA | 1210 | Gaundalim, Tiswadi | VP2 Category settlement
16 | Megha M Azgaonkar | Babu Azgaonkar | BJP MLA | 1000 | Dhargalim, Pernem | Orchard

Source: Assembly Questions and replies by Town & Country Planning Dept, Govt of Goa Three-Fourth Illegal Tourism

Three-Fourth Illegal Tourism

After mining, tourism has been the economic backbone of Goa. It is flourishing day by day, not only as an international tourist destination but the most favoured destination of Corporate India and its executive class. However, its focus on beach tourism combined with vice tourism has resulted in the promotion of all kinds of immoral activities including prostitution, gambling, and consumption of drugs. Politicians have been accusing each other of protecting the underworld mafias and patronising the vice tourism. The coastland, predominantly located in the Old Conquests and also in parts of Pernem and Canacona, has thus become a hotspot of all kinds of illegalities and abuse of land.

Under the full protection of Goa’s political class, tourism all along the coast was ‘developed’ by mercilessly cutting all the protective sand dunes and the coastal vegetation to construct hotels and star resorts. Due to this mindless destruction of the coastland, Goa’s beaches are today facing sand erosion while Goa has not escaped from the worldwide phenomenon of rising sea levels. Similar is the fate of our six prime rivers. In order to control the future devastation of the coastal belt and protect the coastal ecology, the Government of India issued a Coastal Regulation Zone (CRZ) in 1991 under the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986. It was further amended from time to time since new loopholes were found which were arrested by the courts.

“In most of these areas, an area of 200 metres from the High Tide Line (HTL) has been declared as a no development zone. Several restrictions have been imposed for carrying out the development in the area between 200 to 500 metres from HTL. These measures have been adopted to protect the fragile ecosystem, which exists in the said area and which is vital to sustain ecological balance.”^22

Accordingly the Coastal Regulation Zones were divided into categories, like CRZ I, where no new constructions shall be permitted; CRZ II, where buildings shall be permitted only in the landward side of the existing road and no permission for construction of buildings on landward side of new roads; CRZ III is the area where up to 200 metres from the HTL is earmarked as ‘No Development Zone’.

“Goa Coast Line remained pristine till early 1970s. Human pressure on the coastal ecosystem started in the 1970s when tourism became a major source of revenue. This resulted in 80% of the urban growth being located along the coastal talukas. There has been a proliferation of hotels, resorts, residential flats, dwellings, small restaurants, beach side bars, roads and beach shacks along the coast. This has resulted in dense population, deterioration of the quality of life, loss of biodiversity and adverse effects on beaches, dunes, mangroves, water bodies and ‘Khazan lands’ – (reclaimed lowlands).

The main purpose of the CRZ notification was to control and minimise environmental damage to the coastal ecosystem. The Goa State Committee for coastal environment was empowered to enforce the provision of the notification. Despite this, blatant violation of CRZ provision through anthropogenic activities have resulted in severe negative impacts on coastal ecosystem like rapid elimination of sand dunes, damage to dune vegetation, increasing mobility of sand, transport of sand islands, instability of dunes, denudation of hill slopes, deposition of sediments into estuaries, progressive built up of plastic litter, reduction in mangroves, wetlands and breeding grounds of marine life, localised shore line erosion and seasonal salt water ingress.”^23

The Remote Sensing Survey Instruments of Hyderabad conducted an extensive survey in 2006 of the whole Goan coastline as well as the river line with the help of satellite data of 1991 and 2005, aerial photographs of 1993 as well as the actual physical survey including the field survey. These were the findings of the structures that have come up in violation of the CRZ guidelines all along the Goan coast as well as on the banks of six rivers of Goa.

STRUCTURES VIOLATING CRZ ON THE COAST: 1991-2006

TALUKA | VILLAGES IN 1991 | MORE TILL 2006 | TOTAL | ILLEGAL | %
Bardez | 3 | 1802 | 1585 | 3387 | 35
Salcete | 9 | 333 | 802 | 1135 | 56
Canacona | 5 | 959 | 781 | 1740 | 18
Pernem | 4 | 621 | 764 | 1385 | 14
Mormugao | 8 | 1445 | 569 | 2014 | 21
Quepem | 2 | 91 | 60 | 151 | 2
TOTAL | 31 | 5251 | 4561 | 9812 |

Source: Remote Sensings Instruments, Hyderabad

Analysis of the results of the first phase study in the CRZIII (between 200 m and 500 m from the HTL towards land) along the entire Goa Coast showed that in almost all the 35 villages the number of structures / dwelling units have increased compared to the situation at the time of enactment of CRZ legislation in 1991. The increase has been very significant in Querim, Arambol, Mandrem and Morjim villages in Pernem taluka, Anjuna, Candolim and Calangute villages in Bardez taluka, Colva, Benaulim, Varca and Cavelossim villages in Salcete taluka and Cola, Agonda, Nagorce-Palolem, Poinguinim and Loliem villages in Canacona taluka.^24

Bardez tops the list with a maximum number of 1585 new structures that have come up in 15 years, that too only in three villages: Calangute: 685, Candolim: 620 and Anjuna: 280. Comparatively, though Salcete taluka is second on the list with 802 structures, it comprises nine villages. Maximum among them are Cavelossim with 330 structures, 250 in Varca, 215 in Colva and 199 in Benaulim. Also in Mormugao, the third taluka of the Old Conquests, there were 569 new structures found in eight villages. Maximum among them are the 128 structures in Velsao. But the survey report does not mention how big the structures are. Goa’s top star hotels are located in the coastal belt of these three talukas.

The spread of structures within the CRZ is also found in three talukas and 11 villages of Pernem, Canacona and Quepem. Quitol in Quepem did not have a single structure till 1991, but 11 new structures came up in the CRZ in 15 years. Though tourism is spreading more widely in Pernem in four villages, and Palolem village alone in Canacona surpasses all the other villages of the New Conquests. It has 777 new structures including one seven star resort out of a total 781. Next in line is Arambol in Pernem taluka with 628 structures, 409 in Morjim, 203 in Mandrem, and 145 in Querim. Agonda in Canacona is rising with 365 structures and 320 in Cola. And it is not only on the beachside. Riverside tourism is also increasing rapidly. The CRZ violations were also found increasing even on the banks of six major rivers of Goa.

STRUCTURES VIOLATING CRZ ON RIVER BANKS: 1991-2006

RIVER | VILLAGES | IN 1991 | IN 2006 | TOTAL | AVERAGE/VILLAGE
Tiracol | 10 | 242 | 190 | 442 | 19
Mandovi | 42 | 1795 | 786 | 2623 | 19
Zuari | 24 | 611 | 449 | 1084 | 19
Sal | 11 | 208 | 190 | 409 | 17
Chapora | 22 | 890 | 349 | 1261 | 16
TOTAL | 113 | 3872 | 2067 | 6052 | 18

Source: Remote Sensings Instruments, Hyderabad

Analysis of second phase work showed that in the CRZ-I of Tiracol river a maximum number of structures (117) have come up in Pernem village… (It) showed that new structures/dwelling units have come up almost in all the villages along the rivers, most significantly in Pernem village, along Tiracol river; Parcem, Colvale and Camurlim villages along Chapora river; Panaji, Penha da Franca and Reis Magos villages along Mandovi river; Taleigao, Goa Velha, Cortalim villages along Zuari river; Cavelossim and Velim villages along Sal river and Poinguinim and Nagorcem-Palolem villages along Talpona river.

However, if this table is analysed by taking the average number of structures that have come up in each village (see the last column of the table), then we find that more structures are coming up along the Talpona river of Canacona, which has only four villages. It means the illegalities committed in the tourism belt are now witnessed not only on the coastland but also the midland.

The trend in the last 15 years also seems to be similar, with illegalities in terms of CRZ violations found to be more rampant in the three talukas of the New Conquests, along with the Old Conquests. No data is available in this regard, but the cases of CRZ violation in the High Court of Bombay at Goa as well as the National Green Tribunal are mounting day by day while the politicians are openly accusing the Green activists, especially the Goa Foundation, for “creating obstacles in developing Goa.” Dr Claude Alvares and his activist lawyer wife Adv Norma Alvares have become number one enemies of the Goa Assembly, across the party lines.

Growing through this in Goa is illegal tourism, just like illegal mining. The issue was first raised by Serafino Cota, a hotelier from Carmona and the president of Goa Small and Medium Hotel Owners’ Association. He succeeded in convincing the influential Travel and Tourism Association of Goa about this hidden truth. I once brought both these tourism bodies as well as top officials of Goa Tourism Development Corporation and Tourism Department together for a TV debate.

The revelations were quite shocking.

TTAG President Savio Messias alleged that 60 per cent of hotels and other structures accommodating tourists in Goa are not registered. While only 600 hotels are registered in the A and B categories, the actual number is 3000! Cota added to this, claiming that the total number of illegal rooms is over 10,000. And the entire racket of illegal tourism runs under the nose of the tourism authorities through online booking.

Cota explained the simplest modus operandi of illegal tourism. First a hotelier builds a small resort with around 10 rooms, which is registered. But the online booking is made for 20, 30, or even 100 rooms sometimes, which are the holiday homes built adjacent to the registered resort. The second method is that online booking companies are holding the keys of these holiday homes and even flats, mostly purchased by the outsiders. In both the cases, accommodations are provided at much cheaper rates than the official room tariff since they don’t need to pay any kind of fees or taxes to the government. While admitting the fact that the growth in the number of tourists is 10 to 12 per cent in road, rail and air traffic, the GTDC official informed that 10 to 12 new hotels are registered in Goa every week.

Soon came the Covid19 pandemic and Pandora’s Box was opened. Chief Minister Dr Pramod Sawant, in the official cabinet note of 8 April 2020, stated that “the authorities have identified 589 foreign tourists stranded in the registered hotels and guest houses. This number excludes the tourists staying in un-registered hotels, guest houses etc. However, as per the data available with the FRRO, it is estimated that more than 2500 foreigners alone were stranded.”

It meant that the government was fully aware of the unregistered hotels and other kinds of accommodations, which were run with political patronage and bureaucratic protection. But the actual number of foreign tourists was much beyond even the estimates worked out by the FRRO. The last official report of 24 May 2020 available stated that a total 7774 foreign tourists left Goa in 39 special flights arranged by the companies who booked them online.^25 And only 589 among them were found in registered hotels.

What it meant is that 12 times more number of foreign tourists were living in Goa, that too at the fag end of the tourism season, from February onwards. This number does not include the domestic tourists. Officially, in 2018-19, Goa received a total 79.38 lakhs of tourists, out of which 70.08 lakhs were domestic tourists (88%) and 9.30 lakhs were foreigners (12%).^26 It also meant that when we had 7774 foreign tourists in Goa, there were 57,000 domestic tourists here. And with the same calculation if we go further and calculate 79.38 lakh tourists, then the total number of tourists goes above nine crores! Maybe this is an exaggeration since we don’t know how many domestic and foreign tourists live in the unregistered hotels, guesthouses, etc.

But finally the cat was out of the bag. The tourism department took a serious note of this revelation. As the tourism industry was the worst hit due to the pandemic, the authorities pulled up their sleeves and prepared an excellent document on “Survival and Revival of Goa’s Tourism Industry,” a survey carried out by the Goa Tourism department. It was conducted, analysed, and concluded with firm and stern proposals. The report also estimates the actual tourist footfall at 1.5 crores. Almost 71 lakhs of illegal tourists!

What does it say about illegal tourism?

“Growth? Decline? Overgrowth? Whom to believe? The media, the industry, citizens and official data all seem to be telling a different story about the current fate of tourism in Goa. Where lies the truth? This report is in the opinion that, in fact, these narratives are all exact and happening simultaneously. Goa has recorded a growth in tourism footfall in the last few years, and yet hoteliers have been reporting a decline in their occupancy rate. This paradox seems largely due to the prevalence of informal/unregistered activities.

For accommodations, for instance, this report estimates that more than 70 percent of rooms available in Goa are outthe- radar from official data – this may include unregistered hotels, unregistered rooms or second homes rented to tourists on online platforms. As a consequence, given the inflation in the number of available rooms, formal registered units are facing harsher and harsher competition. The cake might get bigger – since the absolute number of tourists is increasing – but the pieces are getting smaller as more businesses are competing…

‘Illegal hotels are the elephant in the room: everybody knows about it’ told the owner of a hotel. Unregistered activities include business units operating without licence or operating at a higher volume of activities than officially declared (for instance a hotel with a licence for 20 rooms actually running 30 rooms). The Small and Medium Hoteliers’ Association estimates that up to 87% of rooms available for tourists in Goa are unregistered. The present survey estimates that the overall proportion of tourism activities operating without registration could be up to 43%...

The number of registered units was collected from the database of the Department of Tourism while the number of unregistered units was estimated based on the data available on online platforms such as Oyo, Airbnb, and Booking.com, inputs from tourism associations and observations on the field. In addition to these registered and unregistered units, the survey also considered other tourism activities which do not require registration at the Department of Tourism, restaurants and other ancillary entities. In total, it was estimated that 39,694 business tourists – formal or informal - are currently operating in the tourism sector in Goa.^27

ILLEGAL TOURISM OF GOA: ACCOMMODATION

HOTELS ETC | LEGAL | ILLEGAL | TOTAL | ILLEGAL %
A Category Hotels | 76 | 15 | 91 | 16
B Category Hotels | 252 | 101 | 353 | 29
C Category Hotels | 715 | 532 | 1247 | 43
D Category Hotels | 2784 | 4872 | 7656 | 64
Villas | 8 | 400 | 408 | 98
Flats, Vacation Homes | 0 | 6000 | 6000 | 100
TOTAL | 3835 | 11920 | 15755 | 76

Source: Survival & Revival of Goa’s Tourism Industry, A survey by GTDC, Govt of Goa

The TTAG and Small Hoteliers’ Association were alleging that 60 per cent of hotels etc. are illegal. But here is the official report which estimates that 76 per cent are illegal. The report has also suggested an Action Plan, in terms of action to be taken by the Government of Goa. Regarding the unregistered illegal units, it has suggested that a circular be issued by the Department of Tourism to register within 30 days, failing which a penal action would be taken.

The illegal tourism is a direct reply to the question of why so many hotels, resorts, villas, holiday homes, real estate projects and colonies are proposed to be set up by applying under 16b of the TCP Act in the no-development zones earmarked by the Regional Plan 2021. The GTDC report also proposes development of hinterland tourism while there are also hundreds of proposals for conversion of cultivable land into settlement zones. In fact these proposals also include some big private firms and companies listing out thousands of square metres of land for conversion. Though the GTDC report is one of the best documents ever produced on how to develop Goa’s tourism, it raises eyebrows regarding some proposals, on the lines of the controversial clause of 16B in the TCP Act. The GTDC report talks about land parcels:

Provision of land parcel for increased tenure: Getting land parcels for commercial development can be challenging in Goa’s hinterland, as most of the area is under forest cover or under no development zone. Also, in order to maintain a balance between the ecology of the area and the interests of investors, the government should provide land parcels for restricted development but for a longer tenure or lease. The increased tenure will enhance the feasibility of a project and the government will also be able to control the development of the sensitive area. Land will be provided on a case-to-case basis upon acceptance by the single window clearance cell.

Incentives to promote Homestays in Hinterland: Post Covid, a homestay in the hinterland could be an ideal accommodation for tourists to stay in Goa. To promote homestay facilities in the hinterlands, the government can provide following incentives:

Waiving off the registration fee and the licence fee payable to the department of tourism for 2 years.
To provide subsidy in utility charges such as electricity bill, water bill, etc. for 2 years.
Free provision of government approved eco-responsible labels for the eligible accommodations to promote sustainable practices for 2 years.
Subsidy in municipal charges / corporation charges, property tax, excise, trade licences, food safety etc. for 2 years.
Provision of land with increased tenure for glamping / camping accommodations.
Relaxation in FAR

Mind ‘OUR’ MINES

The Second World War was a blessing in disguise for Portuguese Goa. Mining took off as an industry when Japan started importing Goa’s iron ore from 1950 onwards. The mine owners were the wealthiest class of Goa, who were fully backing the Portuguese government during the whole liberation movement while some ‘nationalist’ mine owners were also secretly supporting the freedom fighters. Also in independent Goa, from the first election of 1963 till date, the ‘mine owners’ is the most powerful lobby that has been controlling Goan politics and almost all the major political parties, no matter whether they are ruling or in the opposition. Goenchi Maati, the organisation floated by Dr Claude Alvares of Goa Foundation, has described the whole journey of Goa’s mining industry in a concise manner.

“Reports of minerals in Goa date back very far. There are reports that Jains living in Cudnem used to extract Gold in Goa. The existence of iron ore mines was known to the Portuguese from the early 1700s, but it was hushed up for fear of invasion by others. However, iron ore was extracted through the entire Portuguese period by certain groups, notably the tribe known as Dovolos, based in Navelim and other areas of Salcette.

The first mining manifest was given in 1905… In 1910, a French company, Compagnie de Mines de Fer de Goa, made plans to extract manganese ore from the Bicholim area, and transport it by rail through Sanquelim, Ponda, Raia and Loutolim to Margao. Mining really took off after the World War as demand soared for the reconstruction. Japan in particular found it easier politically to import iron ore from Portuguese Goa instead of British India. By the time of liberation in 1961, some 800 mining concessions had been granted.

In 1987, after a number of previous efforts, the Indian Government passed the Abolition Act, which converted perpetual concessions into fixed term mining leases. The erstwhile concession holders were compensated under the Act for this change. There were two boom and bust cycles during this period, with busts in the late 1970s and early 1990s. At the bottom, things were very difficult, and making money was a struggle. Mining was barely profitable. It is likely that a number of questionable practises began at this time.

The China boom in the early 2000s caused iron ore prices to soar. Naturally, this was accompanied with a mad rush to extract everything and send it to China. Malpractices became commonplace. There were numerous PILs filed, and numerous mines shut down as well on different grounds. It all culminated with the release of the explosive Shah Commission Report in the Parliament, and the subsequent bans.

During the Supreme Court hearings following the Shah Commission, it became clear that there were numerous, nay countless, serious violations by the miners. The Supreme Court changed direction. It ruled that all mining after 22-Nov-2007 was fully illegal, raising the prospect of recovering some of the loot, and making a fresh start for mining in Goa. The Supreme Court also ordered the creation of the Goa Iron Ore Permanent Fund, laying down the path for a fair to all mining system, which we are proposing.

Yet the BJP government has thrown all this away, and restarted mining by renewing leases to the same miners. The estimated loss is Rs. 1,44,000 crores, Rs. 10 lakhs for every man, woman and child. If we do not act, how will we be remembered in history? The nalayak generation? The old fools?”

Justice Shah Commission said it’s a scam of Rs 35,000 crore and described it as a Theft, suggesting the people involved in the scam are nothing but Thieves. It was a daylight robbery. With the China boom, wheels had started moving in Goan politics while unabated mining had begun. Goa’s leading miner and owner of Fomento, Auduth Timblo personally took the initiative in 2004 to pull out three-time BJP MLA Digambar Kamat from the Manohar Parrikar-led BJP government and re-establish the Rane-led Congress government. Kamat continued to be the mining minister. After the 2007 Assembly election, Kamat was made the chief minister. Thanks to illegal mining and practically the whole political class jumping at the opportunity of looting Goa’s treasure, the Kamat-led Congress government completed the whole term without any trouble from any political party.

At that moment, 117 mining leases were operational, covering 259 square kilometres of land of Goa. CM Kamat had set up a Task Force and then the State Level Committee (SLC) under the chairmanship of internationally renowned architect Charles Correa along with India’s and Goa’s leading town planners, in order to prepare a new Regional Plan 2021. Besides mapping the cultivated land and marking zones for housing, the SLC also marked areas to develop agriculture, tourism, industry and even mining. It had also provided an Action Plan and how to phase out mining by providing an alternative to the mining dependent population. Perhaps for the first time, the areas of land of mining were classified into the forest, private forest, orchard, cultivated paddy fields, catchment area of water bodies, industrial areas as well as settlement areas.

TYPE OF LAND OF ACTIVE MINING LEASES (2010): %

| LEASES & LAND | | | | | | | | SANGUEM | BICHOLIM | QUEPEM | SATTARI | TOTAL | |----------------|---------|----------|--------|---------|-------| | No of Leases | 66 | 38 | 10 | 18 | 132 | | Forest | 38 | 20 | 14 | 13 | 27 | | Private Forest | 3 | 0 | 0.39 | 0 | 1 | | Orchard | 53 | 68 | 74 | 72 | 62 | | Paddy Fields | 1 | 2 | 5 | 3 | 2 | | Water Bodies | 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 2 | | Industry | 0.35 | 0.29 | 0.04 | 0 | 0.25 | | Settlement | 3 | 7 | 4 | 8 | 5 |

Source: Release Two; Regional Plan of Goa 2021, Government of Goa P 60-62

The ‘mine owners’ of Goa still claim that they are not the lease holders but the owners of the mines since the Portuguese had given it to them as perpetual concessions. They have challenged the Goa, Daman and Diu Mining Concessions (Abolition and Declaration as Mining Leases) Act, 1987. It is still lying in the Supreme Court.

By releasing a document regarding the types of land allotted for mining leases, the SLC in 2010 had listed out the kind of damage mining has caused in the midland and hinterland and brought it to the notice of Kamat government.

“Mining has caused incalculable direct and indirect damage to both the environment and the people in these areas - by affecting the quality of air, water and forests, as well as health, agriculture, employment and living conditions of the people. The major impacts are as under:

About 1110.81 hectares of forest land has been diverted to mining as per the data furnished by the Forest Dept.
A number of mining leases are located in the catchment areas of water bodies and in the case of Selaulim dam, even within the buffer area of the dam. This threatens the quality and the holding capacity of this primary water source which caters to the entire South Goa district.
There are no controls on the depth of the mines. As a result mining is done even below the water table at the cost of underground aquifers, causing acute water shortage in mining areas (should be brought under Goa Groundwater Regulation Act 2002).
Open ore transportation by trucks is causing severe air pollution and disrupting the health and social lives of villagers in the mining talukas.
Agriculture is severely affected in the areas around mines because of siltation and lack of ground water for irrigation.
The siltation of the Zuari and Mandovi rivers is a direct result of the mining activities occurring upstream along these rivers and the failure of anti-erosion measures.
Barge building activity has been mushrooming all along the river banks to keep up with the increase in mining activity.

The SLC had also made 26 recommendations for sustainable mining, stating that action needs to be taken to minimise the brutal environmental fall-outs of mining, and for deciding on options for the future. Until this task is completed, the SLC had clearly suggested that no new mines should be allowed to start (including those with valid licences), nor should any new leases be considered.

These recommendations are nothing different from what the Supreme Court has suggested to revive Goa’s mining. In fact the RPG21 had tackled the issue in a more holistic manner while the Supreme Court has limited its scope to have mining activity within a legal framework. The RPG21 has even suggested an alternative economy for the mining-dependent areas. If these recommendations were implemented immediately after the plan was submitted to the government, Goa would not have faced the blanket mining ban, due to which the associated people are suffering for the last 10 years. But neither Digambar Kamat during his remaining tenure nor Manohar Parrikar, who succeeded him and faced the mining ban, bothered to implement it. The whole political class, including the Communist Party of India and its AITUC trade union leader Christopher Fonseca, took pride in holding Dr Claude Alvares and his Goa Foundation responsible for the mining ban. Rather than accusing the thieves, the one who caught the thieves was blamed. These recommendations were made two years before even the Goa Foundation had approached the Supreme Court, seeking a ban on mining to put a stop to the madness of the whole political class in destroying Goa.

Have a look at some of the crucial recommendations the Charles Correa Committee had made:

Bring an immediate halt to mining and dumping outside delineated and mapped 117 working Mining Leases.
Terminating at earliest, from the 117 working mines, those mines which are located within 200 metres from existing settlement fences, 200 m from river banks, Wild Life Sanctuaries and National Parks and within their surrounding one km buffer zones, 500 metres around ASI and State protected monuments and two kms from the boundary of the Submergence Area for reservoirs of the State Water Supply system, like Selaulim, Anjunem etc.
Phase out, within the next three years, those mines that are located within 500 metres from the fence of settlement areas having a population of 100 persons, one km from the fence of settlement areas having a population of 500 persons and above, Catchment areas of Reservoirs of Selaulim and Anjunem and one km to two kms of the boundaries of the Wild Life Sanctuaries.
No area or number of existing 117 mines should increase till 2021.
Leases from among 117 that are in Eco- I zone and have not yet been mined should not be allowed to start operation.
Remaining non-operational 219 mining leases should not be allowed to start operation.
Restrict mining above the water table.
No new forest area to be diverted to mining since there is no land available in the State for compensatory afforestation.
No transportation of topsoil beyond the lease area should be allowed as per mining regulations.
In order to prevent malpractice, all mines must have all the necessary clearances under Environment Act, Air Act, Water Act, Forest Conservation Act, NOC from the National Board of Wildlife and Pollution Control Board as well as valid approval of mining lease from the government.
Utilise mining for solving the existing land filling material scarcity for public projects like roads etc. This will help avoid unnecessary cutting of hills that is otherwise necessitated.
Rehabilitate all non-working/closed mines for water harvesting and restoring damaged water tables.
Make rehabilitation of farm land (Paddy Fields) an integral part of the Mining Policy. The owner should restore the land to its original use of forest, agriculture or orchard after the mine is exhausted.
Examine the options of replacing ore-transported general roads either by a much narrower (18m) road, or by a dedicated mining covered conveyor belt system from the mining areas to the jetties.
Construct a bypass road as a Growth corridor by 2021, which allows northbound and southbound traffic coming in from Belgaum to bifurcate and bypass Goa, which passes right through these devastated areas.
Build new growth centres along this belt which will also help take the pressure off the coastal belt, their development should be on a fast track, and a new planning and implementation cell created to identify the land needed (preferably wasteland).
Appoint a High Power Task Force to look at all the issues related to mining in the State and define a rational and long-term sustainable mining Policy for the State.

Neither any government nor the two subsequent Assemblies of 2012 and 2017 have even bothered to discuss this whole plan and its valuable recommendations. If it was implemented, mining would have not been banned by the Supreme Court, workers would have not been retrenched, mining-dependents would have not starved and Goan economy would have not been affected. But unfortunately Goa did not have a single lawmaker elected who could alert the authorities. Who was responsible for this most irresponsible attitude that led to the economic downfall of Goa?

RICH POLITICIANS AND POOR POLITICS

There was a time when only the Congress was considered to be a poor party of rich politicians. But now it is across the board. Politics is a shortcut to become filthy rich within no time. This is a pan-India phenomenon. Prime Minister Narendra Modi came to power with a thumping majority in 2014 by assuring the people of India that he would get back the black money of corruption accumulated in India and the banks abroad. His experiment of demonetisation to get the black money out of bags, fight corruption, get rid of fake notes and contain terror funding failed miserably. Withdrawing currency notes of 1000 and 500 denominations amounted to 86 per cent of India’s currency. Modi was expecting that one third of Rs 15 lakh crore would not be returned to the banks since it was ‘black’. But in reality, the Reserve Bank of India announced that 99.3 per cent of currency notes were deposited.

RISE IN INCOME OF MLAS: 2007-2017 (Figures In Crores)

MLAS | PARTY | 2007 | 2012 | 2017 | RISE %
Deepak Dhavalikar | MGP | 1.41 | 13.40 | 14.44 | 924
Babu Kavlekar | BJP | 1.31 | 5.31 | 9.37 | 615
Laxmikant Parsekar | BJP | 1.26 | 10.74 | 8.98 | 613
Pandurang Madkaikar | BJP | 5.07 | 12.37 | 32.18 | 535
Benjamin Silva | Ind | 1.21 | 2.86 | 6.38 | 427
Pratapsingh Rane | Congress | 9.57 | 25.87 | 50.00 | 422
Luizinho Faleiro | TMC | 1.77 | - | 9.09 | 414
Aleixo Reginald Lourenco | Congress | - | 1.16 | 5.17 | 346
Mauvin Godinho | BJP | 2.73 | 7.96 | 10.74 | 293
Sudin Dhavalikar | MGP | 3.00 | 5.58 | 10.58 | 253
Agnelo Fernandes | Congress | 5.35 | 10.16 | 17.87 | 234
Pravin Zantye | BJP | 3.97 | 5.55 | 13.23 | 233
Digambar Kamat | Congress | 3.23 | 6.21 | 10.74 | 233
Aleixo Sequeira | Congress | 3.03 | 9.38 | - | 210
Vishwajit Rane | BJP | 7.46 | 6.28 | 21.31 | 186
Vijay Sardesai | GFP | 5.45 | 25.21 | 14.75 | 171
Jennifer Monserrate | BJP | 11.49 | 23.07 | 30.81 | 168
Michael Lobo | BJP | - | 20.69 | 54.59 | 164
Ravi Naik | BJP | 3.89 | 7.09 | 10.12 | 160
Churchill Alemao | TMC | 5.61 | 11.68 | 13.06 | 133
Pramod Sawant | BJP | - | 1.26 | 2.78 | 121
Babush Monserrate | BJP | 15.32 | 23.07 | 30.81 | 101
Joaquim Alemao | Congress | 9.12 | 31.26 | 16.26 | 78
Subhash Shirodkar | BJP | 1.10 | 4.81 | 1.93 | 75
Rohan Khaunte | Ind | - | 5.87 | 9.34 | 59
Nilesh Cabral | BJP | - | 13.42 | 19.95 | 49
Lavoo Mamledar | TMC | 1.81 | 1.35 | 2.67 | 48

Source: Association of Democratic Reforms (ADR) (Party affiliation as on 15 December 2021)

It is not an easy task to prove which politician is corrupt and who is not. There are different tactics used to hoodwink the income tax authorities and accumulate black money. But even then total income cannot be hidden. The Election Commission of India has now made it compulsory for the candidates to file an affidavit where the legal income needs to be shown. Since then, the Association of Democratic Reforms (ADR), the NGO, has been keeping a watch on the contestants and analysing their performance as well as their earnings, shown legally. The table supplied by the ADR has analysed the income shown by the contestants since 2007.

Unlike the common man or the normal businessmen, the income of politicians is not only doubling in five years but raised by even over 900 per cent, like in case of two-time MLA and one-time minister Dipak Dhavalikar. When these MLAs contested in 2017, the richest man among them was twotime MLA Michael Lobo, representing Goa’s tourist hotspot, Calangute. Pratapsingh Rane, the 11-time MLA and five-time chief minister, is next in the line. Then comes Pandurang Madkaikar, who travelled from the MGP to the Congress to the BJP; Babush and Jennifer Monserrate, Vishwajit Rane and so on. This has been a ‘rich journey’ of Goan politicians, till 2017. The latest figures will be known when they file nominations for the 2022 poll. (The ADR did not provide figures of those MLAs who have expired, like Manohar Parrikar, Francisco D’Souza and Vishnu Wagh).

In comparison, if we analyse the whole journey of Goan politics till date, what we observe is mindless misuse of our land rather than utilising it for the development of the people who cultivate this land. No thought is given to sustainable and balanced development of Goa that would not kill the villages and congest the cities. It is not just mining or agriculture or tourism or industry, but the Politics of Business and the Business of Politics that has ruined Goa by the short-sighted political class of Goa. The vision of Bhausaheb Bandodkar and Dr Jack de Sequeira has absolutely faded away.

For example, Goa’s urban population is today not less than 10 lakhs. We also receive 1.50 crores of tourists every year, meaning on an average 12.50 lakh tourists every month. This whole lot of around 22 lakhs needs on a daily basis vegetables, rice, wheat, cereals, fruits, flowers, milk, eggs, meat etc. Goa is certainly equipped enough with the basic natural resources like land and water required to produce these necessities. But the sad part of Goa’s ‘developing economy’ is that the land available to cultivate it is either lying idle, barren or is being converted every day for short-term monetary gains. Instead, we import all these necessities from the neighbouring states at a much higher cost, making our economy costly.

In short, Goa’s politics has been moving around the Land right from the ancient period till date. It has gone through many phases of community farming, feudal dynasties, the feudal Communidades and Bhatkarshai. Then through democratic means we achieved Land to the Tiller but the political class who succeeded the architects of Goa made a mockery of the whole ‘socialist’ concept. And now it is being ridiculed further by reckless conversion of cultivable land into a saleable commodity. The land sharks from all over the world are simply looting Goa’s precious land in collusion with the businessminded politicians and spineless bureaucrats. This is the state of our Bhangarachem Goem (Golden Goa)! The Golden Goose? The whole journey of the Politics of Land could be defined in three simple phases:

Land to the Tiller! Land to the Dealer!! Land to the Killer!!!

“mundkar” means a person who, with the consent of the bhatkar or the person acting or purporting to act on behalf of the bhatkar lawfully resides with a fixed habitation in a dwelling house with or without obligation to render any services to the bhatkar and includes a member of his family but does not include— (i) a person paying rent to the bhatkar for the occupation of the house; (ii) a domestic servant or a chowkidar who is paid wages and who resides in an out-house, house-compound or other portion of his employer’s residence… (Definition in the Mundkar Act).↩︎

Naik Ravi; LAQ No 066 dated 28 July 2021↩︎

Naik Ravi; LAQ No. 018A, ID 22555 dated 27 January 2021↩︎

The Legislative Department, Ministry of Law & Justice, Government of India↩︎

Supreme Court of India: Union Territory of Goa, Daman and Diu & Anr v/s Lakshmibai Narayan Patil etc etc, Judgement dated 23 July 1990↩︎

Census of India 1991↩︎

10th Agri Census Report 2015-16↩︎

Economic Survey 2002↩︎

Colvalkar Dr Nagesh; Land Reforms in the State of Goa: An Assessment↩︎

Madhumati Atchut Parab vs Rajaram V Parab & Ors, Supreme Court of India, 29 January 2009↩︎

Kamat Digambar, Assembly LAQ No 045, 25 July 2018↩︎

Lourenco Reginald Aleixo, Assembly LAQ No 001, Id 2147, 1 August 2014↩︎

Report No 3, Law Commission, Government of Goa,↩︎

Report No 25, August 2013, Law Commission, Government of Goa↩︎

Goa Assembly; A brief report of the Business transacted during 22 July - 21 August 2014↩︎

Times of India (Goa edition); 24-28-31 October & 8 December 2014↩︎

The Goan; 3 August 2017↩︎

Directive by Bombay HC at Goa on 16 January 2019 in PIL of GBA vs State of Goa↩︎

Directive by Bombay HC at Goa on 7 November 2019 in PIL of GBA vs State of Goa↩︎

Assembly Question Id 21370 by Digambar Kamat on 5 February 2020↩︎

Assembly Question Id 23150 by Vijai Sardesai on 29 January 2021↩︎

Sonak Sangeeta M; Environment and Development: Goa at Crossroads, P 156↩︎

Survey and Inquiry of CRZ Areas in Goa; By Remote Sensing Instruments, Hyderabad↩︎

Survey and Inquiry of CRZ Areas in Goa; By Remote Sensing Instruments, Hyderabad↩︎

Minutes of the State Executive Committee of Covid19, Government of Goa, held on 24 May 2020↩︎

Coping with Covid-19: Survival and Revival of Goa’s Tourism Industry; A survey undertaken GTDC, Govt of Goa↩︎

Coping with Covid-19: Survival and Revival of Goa’s Tourism Industry; A survey undertaken GTDC, Govt of Goa↩︎